<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Sion and Parnassus, or, Epigrams on severall texts of the Old and New Testament to which are added [brace] A poem on the Passion, A hymn on the resurrection, ascention, and feast of Pentecost / by Iohn Hoddesdon.</title>
            <author>Hoddesdon, John, fl. 1650.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1650</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 179 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 72 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A44052</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2295</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R35999</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">15586021</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 15586021</idno>
            <idno type="VID">103970</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A44052)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 103970)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1150:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Sion and Parnassus, or, Epigrams on severall texts of the Old and New Testament to which are added [brace] A poem on the Passion, A hymn on the resurrection, ascention, and feast of Pentecost / by Iohn Hoddesdon.</title>
                  <author>Hoddesdon, John, fl. 1650.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 132 p., [1] leaf of plates : port.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by R. Daniel for G. Eversden, and are to be sold at his shop ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCL [1650]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: tightly bound, with print show-through and loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible --  Paraphrases, English.</term>
               <term>Epigrams, English.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:103970:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:103970:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:103970:2"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <l>Though, in this darker Shade, there ſomthing lyes,</l>
                  <l>Might bee the load-stone of all learned eyes:</l>
                  <l>There's ne'r a leafe in which I cannot ſpie</l>
                  <l>Th'Author in's more true Anatomie:</l>
                  <l>Yet All's too little: Hee is but made leſs</l>
                  <l>By th' Painters Pencil, or the Printers Preſs.</l>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:103970:2"/>
            <p>SION <hi>and</hi> PARNASS<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S, <hi>OR EPIGRAMS On ſeverall texts of the Old and New Teſtament. To which are added,</hi> A Poem on the Paſsion. A Hymn on the Reſurrection, Aſcention, And feaſt of Pentecoſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By JOHN HODDESDON.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Horat. de arte Poet.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Omne tulit punctum qui miſcuit utile dulci.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, <hi>Printed by</hi> R. Daniel <hi>for</hi> G. Everſden, <hi>and are to be ſold at his ſhop over againſt the little north gate of S. Pauls Church. MDCL.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:103970:3"/>
            <p>Imprimatur.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Iune <hi>7. 1650.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Nath. Brent.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:103970:3"/>
            <head>To my worthy friend, and honoured Uncle, <hi>CHRISTOPHER HODDESDON</hi> Eſquire, Secundary of the Upper bench.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He happy (although too late) acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance which I have had with you as a Friend, and the kind reception which I have found from you as a Kinſman, hath encouraged me to dedicate theſe Epigrams to you; not doubting, but that you who have already owned the Authour, will alſo Patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nize the Work. Sir, I ſhall not herein ſeek my ſelf, or flatter you. That I preſent you with this book, is more out of reſpect to you, then any deſigne for my ſelf; and not ſo much to beg new favours, as to give thanks for ſuch as I have already received. The great reward that I look for, is onely your kind Acceptance; by which yet I ſhall be a gainer: your name in the frontiſpiece will adde credit to the book, and grace to</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your obliged, and ever dutiful nephew <hi>J. HODDESDON.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:103970:4"/>
            <head>Ad Juvenem optimae ſpei atque indolis <hi>JOHANNEM HODDESDON,</hi> Hujus libelli autorem.</head>
            <l>NOſtra juventatuos pingat Cithereia vultus</l>
            <l>Suſpendat<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> comis carmina vana tuis.</l>
            <l>Tu ſacrata nova texiſti Biblia veſte,</l>
            <l>Prima<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> divinum pagina tractat opus.</l>
            <l>Nulla Venus, nulla his laſcivit Lesbia chartis,</l>
            <l>Nec Minus eſt facies inde venuſta libri,</l>
            <l>Charta Deum brevis illa capit: liber atria coeli</l>
            <l>Et pius, &amp; doctus, (quid volo plura?) Tuus.</l>
            <l>Hoc Juvenis folio juſte-mirabilis, in ſe</l>
            <l>Omnia quod potuit claudere, clauſit opus.</l>
            <bibl>
               <hi>Tuis Amicus ſtudiis</hi> Henricus Bromley.</bibl>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:103970:4"/>
            <head>To his much reſpected friend the Authour on his divine Epigrams.</head>
            <l>NO more, ye Roman Theaters, reherſe</l>
            <l>Your Maro's, Ovids, or Tibullus verſe:</l>
            <l>Here's ſuch an honour as great Virgil mist,</l>
            <l>Though to attain't he turn'd Evangeliſt.</l>
            <l>This work, which metaphras'd in proſe requir'd</l>
            <l>A Septuagint, and often Synods tir'd;</l>
            <l>Is perfected by one, if one he be,</l>
            <l>Who hundreds ſeems in ingenuity.</l>
            <l>Onely this work in one thing don't agree,</l>
            <l>But differs quite from our Theology.</l>
            <l>Both ſacred pages, old and new, in it</l>
            <l>Make but one teſtament of th' Authours wit.</l>
            <bibl>
               <hi>R. Marſh.</hi>
            </bibl>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:103970:5"/>
            <head>To his friend the Authour on his divine Epigrams.</head>
            <l>LO here's a muſe, whoſe active nimble wings</l>
            <l>Soar up aloft to reach at heavenly things:</l>
            <l>Who makes a higher Helicon his abode,</l>
            <l>With eager pride, ſcorning the common rode</l>
            <l>Of vulgar meditations: one whoſe wit</l>
            <l>Aim'd at the nobleſt ſubject, and moſt fit:</l>
            <l>The holy Bible: and although this ſtory</l>
            <l>So ex'lent be, that none can adde more glory;</l>
            <l>Yet heathens, which do moſt reſpect the letter,</l>
            <l>Will be allur'd to like it farre the better.</l>
            <l>Go on, go on,; if thy firſt enterpriſe</l>
            <l>Doth mount ſo high, we muſt get eagles eyes</l>
            <l>To ſee thy next: but if thou flieſt high'r,</l>
            <l>Then all that we can do, is to admire:</l>
            <l>Fear not mortality; Gods name ſhall be</l>
            <l>(Which here you mention) thine's eternitie.</l>
            <bibl>
               <hi>W. Iames.</hi>
            </bibl>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:103970:5"/>
            <head>To his friend the Authour, on his divine Epigrams.</head>
            <l>THou haſt inſpir'd me with thy ſoul, and I</l>
            <l>Who ne're before could ken of Poetry</l>
            <l>Am grown ſo good proficient, I can lend</l>
            <l>A line in commendation of my friend;</l>
            <l>Yet 'tis but of the ſecond hand, if ought</l>
            <l>There be in this, 'tis from thy fancy brought?</l>
            <l>Good thief who dar'ſt Prometheus-like aſpire,</l>
            <l>And fill thy poems with Celeſtiall fire:</l>
            <l>Enliven'd by theſe ſparks divine, their rayes</l>
            <l>Adde a bright luſtre to thy crown of bayes.</l>
            <l>Young Eaglet who thy neſt thus ſoon forſook,</l>
            <l>So lofty and divine a courſe haſt took</l>
            <l>As all admire, before the down begin</l>
            <l>To peep, as yet, upon thy ſmoother Chin;</l>
            <l>And, making heaven thy aim, haſt had the grace</l>
            <l>To look the ſunne of righteouſneſſe ith face.</l>
            <l>What may we hope, if thou goſt on thus faſt!</l>
            <l>Scriptures at firſt; Euthuſiaſmes at laſt!</l>
            <l>Thou haſt commenc'd, betimes, a ſaint: go on,</l>
            <l>Mingling Diviner ſtreams with Helicon.</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:103970:6"/>
            <l> That they who view what Epigrams here be</l>
            <l>May learn to make like, in just praiſe of thee.</l>
            <l>Reader, I've done, nor longer will withhold</l>
            <l>Thy greedy eyes; looking on this pure gold</l>
            <l>Thou'lt know adult'rate copper, which, like this,</l>
            <l>Will onely ſerve to be a foil to his.</l>
            <bibl>
               <hi>J. Dryden of Trin. C.</hi>
            </bibl>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="testament">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:103970:6"/>
            <head>THE CREATION OF THE WORLD.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p>Come and behold the works of God.</p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>PSAL. LXVI.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <l>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>OME and behold the works of God, and ſee</l>
            <l>If any greater then our God there bee:</l>
            <l>Come, and behold his works, by whoſe words ſayd</l>
            <l>The fabrique of this Univerſe was made.</l>
            <l>And when th'haſt view'd all the world doth containe;</l>
            <l>Looke on thy ſelfe, and view them o're againe.</l>
            <div type="book">
               <head>GENESIS</head>
               <div n="1" type="epigram">
                  <head>1. <hi>God eternall.</hi> Ch. 1.</head>
                  <l>In the beginning God did all things make:</l>
                  <l>Himſelfe from no time did beginning take.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="epigram">
                  <head>2. <hi>The Chaos.</hi> Ch. 1. v. 11.</head>
                  <l>This rude unmoulded maſſe, this Four-in-One</l>
                  <l>Earth, Water, Fire, and Ayre, made Union</l>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:103970:7"/>
                  <l> In diſcord, but could not have long ſubſiſted:</l>
                  <l>The Fire had Water, Earth had Ayre reſiſted,</l>
                  <l>And infant-Nature worne with jurres at length</l>
                  <l>Had been conſumed with her proper ſtrength;</l>
                  <l>But that great word, which firſt did bid them be.</l>
                  <l>Made ſeparation, and yet unitye.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="epigram">
                  <head>3. <hi>Light created.</hi> ch. 1. v. 3.</head>
                  <l>All things were cloath'd with univerſall Night</l>
                  <l>When God created beames of radiant light:</l>
                  <l>In imitation ſtrive we that we may</l>
                  <l>Be children now not of the night, but Day.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="epigram">
                  <head>4. <hi>The Firmament.</hi> ch. 1. v. 7.</head>
                  <l>'Twas now high time God ſhould fulfill's intent</l>
                  <l>To build his high Watch-Tower, the Firmament:</l>
                  <l>Which might divide the waters here below,</l>
                  <l>From thoſe Nectarean ſtreames, that there doe flow.</l>
                  <l>This is his Palace, whoſe all-ſearching eye</l>
                  <l>The inmoſt cavernes of the earth doth ſpy.</l>
                  <l>Vaſt is the Houſe, but heere the wonder is;</l>
                  <l>Himſelfe is greater then the Aedifice.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>5.</hi> The Sea ſeparated from the Land. <hi>ch. 1. v. 9.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>The Ocean's wide wombe yawnes, and Earth ginns peepe</l>
                  <l>From out the confines of the watry deepe:</l>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:103970:7"/>
                  <l>'Twixt whom ſo firme a fixed league is plight</l>
                  <l>That neither dare uſurp the others right:</l>
                  <l>Theſe ſenſeleſſe Elements thus ceaſe to jarre;</l>
                  <l>Yet Man with earth ſeas, Heav'n, himſelf doth warre.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>6.</hi> The earth bringing forth fruit. <hi>ch. 1. v. 12.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>Plenty enſues on this eſtabliſht peace.</l>
                  <l>Trees, flowrs, roots, herbs, graſſe, ſeeds yield their increaſe.</l>
                  <l>O Let us to bring forth good fruits begin!</l>
                  <l>Onely be barren in the fruits of ſin.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>7.</hi> The Sunne and Moon created. <hi>ch. 1. v. 16.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>The earth repleniſh't thus, adorn'd, and grac'd;</l>
                  <l>The candles now above the room are plac'd.</l>
                  <l>The Sunne to rule the day: the Moon is given</l>
                  <l>To guide the night: the ſtars made ſignes in heaven;</l>
                  <l>But O what need is there in heav'n of them!</l>
                  <l>God's preſence gilds the new Jeruſalem.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="epigram">
                  <head>8. <hi>Fiſh.</hi> ch. 1. v. 20.</head>
                  <l>The fruitfull Sea gives ſundry creaturs birth</l>
                  <l>More and more monſtrous then or ayre or Earth:</l>
                  <l>Thetis, whilſt theſe ſhe dandles in her lappe,</l>
                  <l>Wayles in ſalt teares her ſpeechleſſe iſſues happe.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="epigram">
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:103970:8"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>9.</hi> Birdes and Fowles. <hi>ch. 1. v. 21.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>Fowle, the firſt liveing creatures, did repaire</l>
                  <l>Into the open manſion of the Ayre</l>
                  <l>Where though their bodyes confin'd are to th'sky;</l>
                  <l>Mans ſoule a far more lofty courſe doth fly.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>10.</hi> Beaſtes and creeping things. <hi>ch. 1. v. 24.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>After the Ayre was filled, and the ſea;</l>
                  <l>The Earth brought forth her beaſtly progeny.</l>
                  <l>But ſince Man fell from keeping God's beheſts</l>
                  <l>Hee's turn'd more <hi>foule</hi> then <hi>Fowle,</hi> more <hi>beaſt</hi> then <hi>Beaſtes.</hi>
                  </l>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="epigram">
                  <head>11. MAN <hi>Created</hi> ch. 1. v. 26.</head>
                  <l>His Palace fully furniſht; MAN was made</l>
                  <l>To enter it, and be by all obeyd</l>
                  <l>Who with a reaſonable ſoul indu'd</l>
                  <l>Doth in himſelf another World include:</l>
                  <l>He hath o're all the creatures maſtery;</l>
                  <l>Thrice happy! if God's ſervant he could be.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="12" type="epigram">
                  <head>12. <hi>The end of the</hi> CREATION. ch. 2. ADAM.</head>
                  <l>He was in paradiſe, in innocence,</l>
                  <l>But haveing fell from grace, he fell from thence;</l>
                  <l>Well, Adam, yet be cheerd in this hard happ,</l>
                  <l>Thou falſt no lower, then thy Mothers lapp.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="13" type="epigram">
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:103970:8"/>
                  <head>13. <hi>Aliud.</hi> ch. 3. v. 7.</head>
                  <l>Adam, who dureing his firſt ſtate, had none,</l>
                  <l>Then firſt ſought clothes, when righteouſneſſe was gone,</l>
                  <l>Truth naked is: when truth from him was fled</l>
                  <l>Noe mar'l he ſought a <hi>cloak</hi> for what he did.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="14" type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>14.</hi> On the forbidden fruit. <hi>ch. 3. AD EVAM.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>Shee'l eate it, though, for eating it, ſhe dye;</l>
                  <l>O'tis a pretious apple in her eye!</l>
               </div>
               <div n="15" type="epigram">
                  <head>15. CAIN. ch. 4.</head>
                  <l>Is't not a faire example thou doſt give</l>
                  <l>(Bloud-thirſty Cain) to them that after live,</l>
                  <l>That thus times Annalls ſhould record of thee</l>
                  <l>The firſt man borne, the firſt manſlayer he?</l>
                  <l>Hold, hold thy impious hand; but tis too late;</l>
                  <l>Thy brothers bloud cryes lowd at heavens Gate</l>
                  <l>Lowdlike <hi>A-Bell</hi> for vengeance, who being ſlain,</l>
                  <l>Thou'rt markt: Hell knowes thee by that brand again.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="16" type="epigram">
                  <head>16. <hi>Aliud.</hi> ch. 4.</head>
                  <l>Who firſt the art of Tillage found,</l>
                  <l>With's Brothers bloud manur'd his ground:</l>
                  <l>A fruitfull harveſt followed</l>
                  <l>A crop of Vengeance on his Head.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="17" type="epigram">
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:103970:9"/>
                  <head>17. ABEL. ch. 4.</head>
                  <l>More innocent, more harmleſſe then thoſe ſheep;</l>
                  <l>Whome though he kept, himſelf he could not keep.</l>
                  <l>His Offring GOD accepts; he there fore dyes,</l>
                  <l>Unto his Brother's wrath, a Sacrifice.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="18" type="epigram">
                  <head>18. SETH. ch. 5.</head>
                  <l>Seth's pillars which inſcrib'd with learning ſtood</l>
                  <l>Firme'gainſt th'incurſions of the ſwelling flood;</l>
                  <l>Are now conſum'd with time, and ſo is he:</l>
                  <l>Theſe lines help to ſupport his memorie.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="19" type="epigram">
                  <head>19. ENOCH. ch. 5. v. 24.</head>
                  <l>Bleſt Enoch in the Heavens is thy abode.</l>
                  <l>Thou walkſt with God before thou walkſt with God.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="20" type="epigram">
                  <head>20. METHUSALEM. ch. 5. v. 27.</head>
                  <l>Good Enoch lived here a little ſpace,</l>
                  <l>And was tranſlated to a better place.</l>
                  <l>Methuſelah liv'd long, how was this done?</l>
                  <l>The Sire tranſlated's years unto the ſon.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="21" type="epigram">
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:103970:9"/>
                  <head>21. NOAH. ch. 6.</head>
                  <l>When men from Adam, ſin from men had birth</l>
                  <l>And both were now grown Giants on the Earth;</l>
                  <l>God ſent a flood, whoſe proud o're-flowing waves</l>
                  <l>Drowne great and little world: his Arke Noy ſaves;</l>
                  <l>But when the world ſhall be deſtroyed agen,</l>
                  <l>Then AH-NO Arke ſhall be for mortall men.</l>
               </div>
               <div type="epigram">
                  <head>Aliud. <hi>ch. 6.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>The World is drown'd, Noah no deluge feares;</l>
                  <l>For he had drown'd himſelf before, in teares.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="23" type="epigram">
                  <head>23. <hi>Aliud.</hi> ch. 6.</head>
                  <l>When all mankind found in the ſea their graves</l>
                  <l>His fireof zeale Noy from the waters ſaves.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="24" type="epigram">
                  <head>24. NOAH's <hi>Husbandry.</hi> ch. 9.</head>
                  <l>After the flood Noah begann</l>
                  <l>To plant and play the husbandman.</l>
                  <l>But too much wine carouſing downe,</l>
                  <l>In drunkenneſſe himſelf doth drowne:</l>
                  <l>He now too had been ſav'd I gueſſe</l>
                  <l>Had he the Arke of Soberneſſe.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="25" type="epigram">
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:103970:10"/>
                  <head>25 NOAH's <hi>Sonnes.</hi> ch. 9.</head>
                  <l>HAM came and ſaw his Fathers nakedneſſe?</l>
                  <l>But SHEM and JAPHET cover't: Noy doth bleſſe</l>
                  <l>Theſe two, this curſe bequeatheth to their brother</l>
                  <l>That he ſhould bow the <hi>ham</hi> unto the other.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="26" type="epigram">
                  <head>26, ABRAHAM. ch. 12. V. 7.</head>
                  <l>With this good Patriarch God did covenant</l>
                  <l>Unto his ſeed bleſt Canaan to grant:</l>
                  <l>But ere God to fulfill his word began</l>
                  <l>Himſelf poſſeſt the heavenly Canaan.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="27" type="epigram">
                  <head>27. LOT. ch. 9.</head>
                  <l>Agodly life he liv'd, great wealth he got</l>
                  <l>God pleas'd with Lot, and Lot pleas'd with his <hi>lott.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Yet this ſtrange ſin by him was ſtrangely don,</l>
                  <l>He was the Grandfather of his owne ſon!</l>
               </div>
               <div n="28" type="epigram">
                  <head>28. SODOM and GOMORRAH. ch. 19.</head>
                  <l>Sinne reigned heere, God therefore on this towne</l>
                  <l>Doth <hi>raine</hi> from Heaven fire and brimſtone downe:</l>
                  <l>Which, as a ſad praeludium, doth foretel</l>
                  <l>What they heerafter muſt expect in Hell.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="29" type="epigram">
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:103970:10"/>
                  <head>29. BRAHAM, <hi>offering (his ſon)</hi> ISAAC. ch. 22. V. 10.</head>
                  <l>When he with willing heart, and outſtretch'd hand</l>
                  <l>Was ready to fulfill the hard command:</l>
                  <l>When now the fatall knife was drawn, which ſo</l>
                  <l>Was to have ſlaine all Iſrael at one blow;</l>
                  <l>God, for the Offering, did with him diſpence</l>
                  <l>Pleas'd with the <hi>offer</hi> of's obedience.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="30" type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>30.</hi> On the Ram caught in the Buſh. <hi>ch. 22. V. 13.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>Ram, this with thee will prove a bloudy day;</l>
                  <l>Thou with thy life the price of life muſt pay:</l>
                  <l>For Iſaack thou art made a Sacrifice,</l>
                  <l>And Chriſt the Paſchall lambe for Sinners dyes.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="31" type="epigram">
                  <head>31. ESAU. ch. 24. V. 33.</head>
                  <l>When, Eſau toild with hunting, now was come</l>
                  <l>To take up <hi>toyles</hi> and ſpoyles, returning home</l>
                  <l>Fainting for hunger: he his birthright gave</l>
                  <l>For pottage, his neere fleeting life to ſave.</l>
                  <l>O foole, that hunted had ſo hard all day,</l>
                  <l>Yet letts at laſt his brother take the prey!</l>
               </div>
               <div n="32" type="epigram">
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:103970:11"/>
                  <head>32. ISAAC. ch. 27.</head>
                  <l>Juſt Abraham in his old Age begat</l>
                  <l>Iſaac heir of his bleſſings, and eſtate,</l>
                  <l>Who blind with age, yet with foreſeeing minde,</l>
                  <l>The future fortunes of his ſon's divin'd;</l>
                  <l>No bleſſing gave to Eſau he lov'd beſt,</l>
                  <l>But Jacob whom he loved not, he bleſt.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="33" type="epigram">
                  <head>33. JACOB <hi>Getting the bleſſing.</hi> ch. 27.</head>
                  <l>Whilſt Eſau ranging ſeekes for Veniſon,</l>
                  <l>Mean ſpace the bleſſing which he ſought, is gone,</l>
                  <l>For <hi>Harts</hi> and fallow <hi>Deer</hi> ſeeks every whore</l>
                  <l>And looſeth what is to his <hi>heart</hi> moſt <hi>deare.</hi>
                  </l>
               </div>
               <div n="34" type="epigram">
                  <head>34. JACOB's <hi>Ladder.</hi> ch. 28. V. 13.</head>
                  <l>Jacob by pious fraud, and honeſt theft</l>
                  <l>Supplanted Eſau of his birthright: 'reft</l>
                  <l>Him of his bleſſing, more what could he do?</l>
                  <l>He did his beſt to have been born firſt too.</l>
                  <l>Nor was leſſe force then wiſedome to him given</l>
                  <l>By which he wraſtled and prevayl'd with heaven:</l>
                  <l>At laſt worne out with age, his <hi>ſtaffe</hi> layd by,</l>
                  <l>He takes his ladder, and ſo ſcales the sky.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="35" type="epigram">
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:103970:11"/>
                  <head>35. JUDAH. ch. 38.</head>
                  <l>From Judah, Jacob's third, but ſtrongeſt ſonne;</l>
                  <l>A greater lyon then himſelf there ſprung.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="36" type="epigram">
                  <head>36. JOSEPH. ch. 39.</head>
                  <l>Joſeph th'art ſold a ſlave, but yet made free</l>
                  <l>From their malicious hands, who envy'd thee.</l>
                  <l>A priſoner both for thine, and for their good</l>
                  <l>Sent into Egypt to prepare them food.</l>
                  <l>Thy Miſtreſſe would perſwade thee to her will</l>
                  <l>But found thee truſty honeſt Joſeph ſtill:</l>
                  <l>And when thy garment ſnatchd from thee was gone,</l>
                  <l>Thy naked truth more cleere then ever ſhone.</l>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="book">
               <head>Liber ſecundus Moſis dictus <hi>EXODUS.</hi>
               </head>
               <div n="37" type="epigram">
                  <head>37. MOSES. ch. 1.</head>
                  <l>HIs cradle's made of ruſh, he layes his head</l>
                  <l>On Nile's proud backe; that is his feather-bed:</l>
                  <l>Had he not bin ſo loſt, hee'd nere been found</l>
                  <l>If not caſt out to drowning, had been drown'd.</l>
                  <l>Bleſt Babel all things conſpire thy good: and chance</l>
                  <l>Out of thy danger works deliverance.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="38" type="epigram">
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:103970:12"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>38.</hi> The burning buſh. <hi>ch. 3. v. 3. &amp; 4.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>In midſt of fire, and unconſumed yet!</l>
                  <l>This doth a wonder in my minde beget.</l>
                  <l>A fire of zeale this was made by heavens-art,</l>
                  <l>Not to inflame the buſh, but Moſes heart.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="39" type="epigram">
                  <head>39. PHARAOH. ch. 7.</head>
                  <l>For Pharaoh's pride againſt the LORD of Hoſtes</l>
                  <l>An univerſall darkneſſe ſhades his coaſtes.</l>
                  <l>A darkneſſe ſuch as might be felt, a night</l>
                  <l>That long uſurped baffled Phoebus right,</l>
                  <l>He yet continu'd obſtinate (wee finde)</l>
                  <l>The greateſt darkneſſe then was in his minde.</l>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="commandments">
               <head>THE TEN COMMANDEMENTS</head>
               <div n="1" type="commandment">
                  <head>Command. 1.</head>
                  <div n="40" type="epigram">
                     <head>40. <hi>Heare O</hi> ISRAEL. <hi>I am the</hi> LORD <hi>thy</hi> GOD &amp;c.</head>
                     <l>Iſrael, that GOD, who gave, requires thine eare</l>
                     <l>He deignes to ſpeake; and ſhouldſt not thou, to heare!</l>
                     <l>So heare as after hearing to fulfill</l>
                     <l>The holy tenour of his heav'nly will:</l>
                     <l>Who hopes that GOD ſhould heare him, when he praies,</l>
                     <l>Attend what GOD, attend what juſtice ſayes.</l>
                     <l>Should we ſo ill requitall to him make,</l>
                     <l>Who fore all other people did us take?</l>
                     <pb n="13" facs="tcp:103970:12"/>
                     <l> To take a god'fore him? place him behind</l>
                     <l>The fancy'd <hi>Idols</hi> of our <hi>idle</hi> minde?</l>
                     <l>We have created gods indeed below</l>
                     <l>To whome obedience, honour, love we owe.</l>
                     <l>Whome would we ſee rightly to ſerve; O let</l>
                     <l>Them fore our eyes, but GOD fore them be ſet!</l>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="commandment">
                  <head>Command. 2.</head>
                  <div n="41" type="epigram">
                     <head>
                        <hi>41.</hi> Thou ſhalt not make to thy ſelf any graven Images. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <l>Whilſt to Bulls, Dogs, and Cats th'Egyptians bowe</l>
                     <l>They an egregious Hieroglyphick ſhowe</l>
                     <l>Of vaine Idolatry: but little more</l>
                     <l>Of reaſon then thoſe Animals they adore.</l>
                     <l>For why ſhould Man into whoſe ſoule his maker</l>
                     <l>Hath heavenly light infus'd, and made partaker</l>
                     <l>Of his own image, worſhip things that are</l>
                     <l>Inferiour to himſelf in worth ſo farre?</l>
                     <l>Or worſhip God by Proxy? dare to ſett</l>
                     <l>Of what we never ſaw, the counterfett?</l>
                     <l>If 'gainſt this we a remedy would finde;</l>
                     <l>Conſerve theſe precepts <hi>graven</hi> in our minde</l>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="commandment">
                  <head>Command. 3.</head>
                  <div n="42" type="epigram">
                     <head>
                        <hi>42.</hi> Thou ſhalt not take the name of the Lord thy God in vaine <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <l>Thou hurtſt God's name with vaine, and idle chat</l>
                     <l>But Foole thou hurt'ſt thy ſelf far more then that:</l>
                     <pb n="14" facs="tcp:103970:13"/>
                     <l> Thy words are wind, but when great God doth ſpeak</l>
                     <l>Thou'lt find he ſilence can in thunder break.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div n="43" type="epigram">
                     <head>
                        <hi>43.</hi> Aliud.</head>
                     <l>Is God thy fellow that thou ſtill</l>
                     <l>Doſt take his holy name at will?</l>
                     <l>The word that fram'd thee thou doſt mock</l>
                     <l>And makeſt it thy laughing-ſtock.</l>
                     <l>Thou oft invokeſt God to heare:</l>
                     <l>Take heed; too ſoon hee'l lend an eare.</l>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="commandment">
                  <head>Command. 4.</head>
                  <div n="44" type="epigram">
                     <head>
                        <hi>44.</hi> Remember thou keep holy the Sabbath day <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <l>'Tis hard if out of ſeaven we can't afford</l>
                     <l>One day to be kept holy to the Lord:</l>
                     <l>Reſt then from Labour and bleſſe him, that we</l>
                     <l>In ſixe dayes toyle of him may bleſſed be.</l>
                     <l>This Sabbath ſanctifie: an earneſt 'tis</l>
                     <l>Of that eternall one of heav'nly bliſſe.</l>
                     <l>Beſtow ſome hours in pious meditation</l>
                     <l>(Though we work not) on Gods work, the creation:</l>
                     <l>And if to that grand ſecret we would climbe</l>
                     <l>Of our Redemption; O redeeme this time!</l>
                     <l>What though the day be chang'd, as 'twas heaven's will;</l>
                     <l>Keep our devotion on't unchanged ſtill.</l>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="commandment">
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:103970:13"/>
                  <head>Command. 5.</head>
                  <div n="45" type="epigram">
                     <head>
                        <hi>45.</hi> Honour they Father, and thy Mother <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <l>Honour thy parents, and obey</l>
                     <l>What they, and what God here doth ſay.</l>
                     <l>To them obſervant if thou be,</l>
                     <l>And honour'ſt them, others will thee.</l>
                     <l>Long life is promis'd a reward</l>
                     <l>For thoſe who this command regard,</l>
                     <l>A long life ſhall on earth be given,</l>
                     <l>A longer afterwards in heaven.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div n="46" type="epigram">
                     <head>
                        <hi>46.</hi> Aliud.</head>
                     <l>Honour and love thy father naturall,</l>
                     <l>Politique, and Eccleſiaſticall:</l>
                     <l>For, in ſo doing, all may clearly know</l>
                     <l>Whether thou truly honoreſt God or no.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Nature's</hi> laws charge the firſt, which who reſiſts</l>
                     <l>Is of the rank of rankeſt <hi>naturaliſts:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Thother's enjoyn'd us by civility,</l>
                     <l>And that imp'd with a ſmack of policy:</l>
                     <l>The third, which teacheth, why this ſhould be ſhowne,</l>
                     <l>T'all three's the ſumme of all religion.</l>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="commandment">
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:103970:14"/>
                  <head>Command. 6.</head>
                  <div n="47" type="epigram">
                     <head>
                        <hi>47.</hi> Thou ſhalt doe no murther.</head>
                     <l>Murther's ſo foul a crime, 't may not be wrought</l>
                     <l>By us <hi>indeed</hi> in deed, in word, or thought.</l>
                     <l>To boyle with anger is manſlaughter, nay</l>
                     <l>We ſhall for grudgings be arraign'd one day.</l>
                     <l>Of murth'ring there be many peices mo</l>
                     <l>Then death which comes by murth'ring piece's blow.</l>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="commandment">
                  <head>Command. 7.</head>
                  <div n="48" type="epigram">
                     <head>
                        <hi>48.</hi> Thou ſhalt not Commit Adulterie.</head>
                     <l>O have a care and bridle each ill thought</l>
                     <l>Which this command may violate; let nought</l>
                     <l>That is but unbeſeeming be in thee</l>
                     <l>Do thou avoyd all wanton company.</l>
                     <l>Let not thy love be firmly fixt upon</l>
                     <l>Her, that's another mans and not thine owne.</l>
                     <l>Yet on Chriſt's ſpouſe the Church fixe thy firme love</l>
                     <l>Although her proper husband be above.</l>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="commandment">
                  <head>Command. 8.</head>
                  <div n="49" type="epigram">
                     <head>
                        <hi>49.</hi> Thou ſhalt not steale.</head>
                     <l>We are forbid to ſteale, and if we do;</l>
                     <l>In hell we ſhall be puniſht, and here too.</l>
                     <pb n="17" facs="tcp:103970:14"/>
                     <l> Whilſt (though we work in darkneſſe like the mole,</l>
                     <l>And ſteal) another ſteals from us our ſoul.</l>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="commandment">
                  <head>Command. 9.</head>
                  <div n="50" type="epigram">
                     <head>
                        <hi>50.</hi> Thou ſhalt not bear falſe witneſſe againſt thy neighbout.</head>
                     <l>God is the Father of all truth; but lies</l>
                     <l>Are onely wicked Satan's properties.</l>
                     <l>If thou then muſt <hi>bear</hi> wittneſſe, don't through fear</l>
                     <l>Speak falſe, God will not with a liar bear.</l>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="commandment">
                  <head>Command. 10.</head>
                  <div n="51" type="epigram">
                     <head>
                        <hi>51.</hi> Thou ſhalt not covet thy neighbours houſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <l>This laſt, and leaſt of Gods commandments lies</l>
                     <l>In order next, which we ought not deſpiſe.</l>
                     <l>Howe're: if ought we would contemn, begin</l>
                     <l>With deteſtation to deſpiſe this ſinne</l>
                     <l>Of coveting what's not our own; yet ſtill</l>
                     <l>Covet what's not our own, to have like will</l>
                     <l>With our Divine Creatour, that were rather</l>
                     <l>To keep, then break, the Law of him our Father.</l>
                     <l>What ſhould I covet, poor babe, under age?</l>
                     <l>But Chriſt my elder brother's heritage;</l>
                     <l>That, and his love, I prize all things before,</l>
                     <l>And covet I may covet nothing more.</l>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="book">
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:103970:15"/>
               <head>The third book of <hi>MOSES</hi> called <hi>LEVITICUS.</hi>
               </head>
               <div n="52" type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>52.</hi> The fire ſhall be ever burning, <hi>&amp;c. ch. 6. v. 13.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>THe Prieſt, leſt holy fire ſhould decay,</l>
                  <l>Duly, each morn, did on it fuell lay:</l>
                  <l>So, leſt our fire of zeal ſhould die, 'tis fit</l>
                  <l>Our prayers each morning give new life to it.</l>
                  <l>Whilſt we this flame foment, we need not doubt</l>
                  <l>But that the fire of Gods wrath will go out;</l>
                  <l>This on the Altar of our hearts being kept,</l>
                  <l>God us and our peace-offering will accept.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="53" type="epigram">
                  <head>53. NADAB <hi>and</hi> ABIHU <hi>burnt.</hi> ch. 10.</head>
                  <l>Your minds were <hi>kindled</hi> with a <hi>ſtrange</hi> deſire</l>
                  <l>Of offering <hi>incenſe</hi> with as <hi>ſtrange</hi> a fire:</l>
                  <l>This 'twas, <hi>incens'd</hi> Gods anger, made you wiſh</l>
                  <l>You had been <hi>ſtrangers</hi> to ſuch deeds as this.</l>
                  <l>Fire, ſent from God, your death, and ruine was,</l>
                  <l>Made heavenly martyrs, though not for heav'ns cauſe;</l>
                  <l>Whilſt theſe unſanctified flames you bring;</l>
                  <l>Your ſelves are turn'd to a <hi>burnt-offering.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sinne-offering</hi> you were none, ſince no expence</l>
                  <l>Of ſacred fire could expiate your offence:</l>
                  <l>Yet a <hi>ſinne-offering</hi> too you were, for in</l>
                  <l>Your <hi>offering</hi> there was nothing elſe but <hi>ſinne:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Had you one <hi>ſpark</hi> of grace, then had not heaven</l>
                  <l>Needed ethereall fire thus to have given.</l>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:103970:15"/>
                  <l> God gave you what you <hi>offer'd</hi> him, 'twas fit</l>
                  <l>For <hi>offering</hi> ſuch a treſpaſſe to commit.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="54" type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>54. SHELOMITHS</hi> ſonne, blaſpheming, is ſtoned, <hi>chap. 24.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>Thou'rt <hi>ſton'd</hi> blaſphemer, and 'twas thy deſert,</l>
                  <l>Juſt puniſhment for ſuch a ſtony heart;</l>
                  <l>That curſe thou dartedſt up at Heav'n, fell down</l>
                  <l>Heavy (as is <hi>ſtones</hi> nature) on thy crown:</l>
                  <l>Thy Sire was an Egyptian, which made thee</l>
                  <l>In th' <hi>holy language</hi> no more skil'd to be.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="55" type="epigram">
                  <head>55. <hi>The yeare of</hi> JUBILEE. ch. 25.</head>
                  <l>Bleſt year of reſt which was, as we may ſay,</l>
                  <l>Through all its courſe a laſting holy-day.</l>
                  <l>Whoſe <hi>priviledge</hi> of reſt did ſo abound,</l>
                  <l>That 'mongſt the <hi>reſt</hi> it priviledg'd the ground;</l>
                  <l>No crooked plough could now the leave obtain</l>
                  <l>To make her furrow up her face for pain:</l>
                  <l>Now Lands revolve to their right Lord: each skore</l>
                  <l>Of debt, and tears were wip'd off from the poor.</l>
                  <l>Bleſt yeare, more bleſt, if gratefull they had been,</l>
                  <l>And made this year their <hi>reſting</hi> year from ſinne.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="56" type="epigram">
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:103970:16"/>
                  <head>56. <hi>For unto me the children of</hi> ISRAEL, &amp;c. ch. 27. verſe the laſt.</head>
                  <l>Lord, 'tis confeſt we are thy ſervants, ſo</l>
                  <l>Are glorious Angels, farre our Betters, too.</l>
                  <l>But (might a ſervant ſay't without offence)</l>
                  <l>We'd be thy ſervants in a ſtricter ſence.</l>
                  <l>Wouldſt thou us manumize from bondage then,</l>
                  <l>As Denizons of new Jeruſalem;</l>
                  <l>Or by adoption make us thine, this done,</l>
                  <l>Each ſhall thy ſervant be although thy ſonne.</l>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="book">
               <head>The fourth book of <hi>MOSES</hi> called <hi>NUMBERS.</hi>
               </head>
               <div n="57" type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>56.</hi> The <hi>ISRAELITE</hi> gathering ſticks on the Sabbath day ſtoned. <hi>ch. 15.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>WHy didſt thou break his precept, who doth ſay</l>
                  <l>Abſtain from labour on the Sabbath day?</l>
                  <l>Theſe <hi>ſticks</hi> ſend thee to <hi>Styx,</hi> fool make thy mone.</l>
                  <l>Thus looking for a <hi>ſtick,</hi> thou'ſt got the <hi>ſtone.</hi>
                  </l>
               </div>
               <div n="58" type="epigram">
                  <head>58. <hi>The Rebellion of</hi> KORAH, DATHAN, <hi>and</hi> ABIRAM. ch. 16.</head>
                  <l>Thus clog'd with ſinne it was impoſſible</l>
                  <l>But ſuch a weight ſhould ſink them down to hell.</l>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:103970:16"/>
                  <l> A crime ſo foul that leſt it ſhould be ſpide,</l>
                  <l>The earth did it within her entrails hide;</l>
                  <l>She could not ſure, but breed herſelf diſquiet,</l>
                  <l>Clogging her ſtomach with ſuch lothſome diet.</l>
                  <l>Thus they were taken in their proper gin,</l>
                  <l>They <hi>digg'd a pit,</hi> and fell themſelves therein:</l>
                  <l>When thus you op'd your mouths, dire murmurers,</l>
                  <l>What marvell was't, the Earth ſo open'd hers?</l>
               </div>
               <div n="59" type="epigram">
                  <head>59. AARON'S <hi>rod budding.</hi> ch. 17.</head>
                  <l>That Aaron's rod ſhould bloſſome, ſhews that God</l>
                  <l>Would that the houſe of Levi ſtill ſhould bud</l>
                  <l>And flouriſh; what a wonder's here? O ſee,</l>
                  <l>A wither'd branch becomes a fruitfull tree!</l>
                  <l>But ſtill a <hi>rod,</hi> that if we bear no fruit,</l>
                  <l>The <hi>rod</hi> of chaſtiſement may force us to't.</l>
                  <l>Yet Almonds are poor fruit, I wiſh that mine,</l>
                  <l>Were not of them, but rather of the Vine.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="60" type="epigram">
                  <head>60. AARON'S <hi>death.</hi> ch. 20.</head>
                  <l>Thou now great prieſt approching to thy death,</l>
                  <l>Doſt firſt reſigne thy office, then thy breath;</l>
                  <l>Here thou aſcend'ſt a mount, whence thy ſoul will</l>
                  <l>Take her ripe flight unto the heavenly hill;</l>
                  <l>Thou leav'ſt thy people now, yet leav'ſt them ſo,</l>
                  <l>That thou art gather'd to thy people too.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="61" type="epigram">
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:103970:17"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>61.</hi> The brazen Serpent. <hi>ch. 21.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>That through Gods power virtue in this <hi>braſſe</hi> lay,</l>
                  <l>None is ſo impudent that dare gain ſay.</l>
                  <l>No cordiall nor yet <hi>ſimple,</hi> 'twould appear,</l>
                  <l>To humane ſenſe, a <hi>ſimple</hi> med'cine here:</l>
                  <l>Wondrous! yet wondrous eaſie to apply</l>
                  <l>Such precious ſalve ith' twinkling of an eye.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="62" type="epigram">
                  <head>62. BALAAMS <hi>Aſse.</hi> ch. 22.</head>
                  <l>Heaven gives a tongue and mind, the Aſſe 'gins break</l>
                  <l>Her ſilence, and hath now a <hi>mind</hi> to ſpeak.</l>
                  <l>Her maſter, and his pride, no longer <hi>bears,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Though ſhe his aſſe had been ſo many years.</l>
                  <l>She ſaw the Angell, and with terrour led,</l>
                  <l>Fell down upon the ground and worſhipped.</l>
                  <l>Had Balaam known in what a caſe he was,</l>
                  <l>And done like her, he had not play'd the aſſe.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="63" type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>63.</hi> Defile not the Land, <hi>&amp;c. ch. 35.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>Do not defile our land, and mak't an hell,</l>
                  <l>With ſins, wherein heavens God is pleas'd to dwell</l>
                  <l>But when that is defil'd, leſt he depart,</l>
                  <l>Be ſure keep one place pure, and that's thy heart.</l>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="book">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:103970:17"/>
               <head>The fifth book of <hi>MOSES</hi> called <hi>DEUTERONOMY.</hi>
               </head>
               <div n="64" type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>64.</hi> Thou ſhalt not plough with an ox and an aſſe together. <hi>ch. 22. v. 10.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>PRepoſterous ſin! what reaſon canſt thou find,</l>
                  <l>That thou, what nature would not, wouldſt have joyn'd?</l>
                  <l>Muſt the poor aſſe, for all paſt pains, at length</l>
                  <l>Be match'd thus with a beaſt above his ſtrength?</l>
                  <l>Although for humane cauſe deſiſt thou wouldſt not.</l>
                  <l>O <hi>joyn</hi> them not, 'cauſe God <hi>enjoyns</hi> thou ſhouldſt not.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="65" type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>65.</hi> Thou ſhalt not muzzle the ox that treadeth out the corn. <hi>ch. 25. v. 4.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>Before he took pains for thee at the plough,</l>
                  <l>And though he eat, why yet he labours now:</l>
                  <l>'Tis fit that he, with whoſe help thou doſt ſow,</l>
                  <l>Should eat the fruit, of what he toild for, too.</l>
                  <l>Thou'lt ſay, as he treads out he eats, 'tis true,</l>
                  <l>Yet as he eats, he ſweats; and give him's due:</l>
                  <l>Why doſt thou muzzle up his mouth? heav'n hears</l>
                  <l>His dumbe complaints, thou canſt not ſtop heav'ns ears:</l>
                  <l>But wilt thou tie his chaps up yet (accurſt?)</l>
                  <l>Tie up his legs withall, and do thy worſt.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="66" type="epigram">
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:103970:18"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>66.</hi> Joſhua encouraged. <hi>ch. 31.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>Joſhua in Moſes ſtead, by Gods command,</l>
                  <l>Was to guide Iſrael to the promis'd land:</l>
                  <l>Moſes now ready to <hi>depart</hi> doth make him,</l>
                  <l>This promiſe, that God never ſhould <hi>forſake</hi> him.</l>
                  <l>God would <hi>go up</hi> before him, were't not ſo,</l>
                  <l>Both he and Iſrael <hi>down</hi> the wind would go:</l>
                  <l>He'd be their Captains Captain, can they miſſe</l>
                  <l>To conquer Earth, whoſe Captain Heaven is?</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Beforehand</hi> God goes up, the cauſe we ſee,</l>
                  <l>That Iſrael never might <hi>behind hand</hi> be.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="67" type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>67.</hi> The Iſraelites freed by <hi>MOSES. ch. 34.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>He led Gods choſen from proud Pharaohs Land,</l>
                  <l>By miracles, and an outſtretched hand</l>
                  <l>Through the red ſea and Wilderneſſe of Sin</l>
                  <l>To th' confines of the promis'd land did bring;</l>
                  <l>Where having left his charge with Joſhua,</l>
                  <l>He went before hand to prepare their way.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="68" type="epigram">
                  <head>68. MOSES <hi>his death.</hi> ch. 34.</head>
                  <l>Moſes, who whilſt he liv'd, a bleſſing ſtill</l>
                  <l>Had been, leaves <hi>bleſsings</hi> as his dying will;</l>
                  <l>Whoſe corps leſt Iſrael ſhould prize too <hi>high,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And ſo <hi>fall</hi> into flat Idolatry;</l>
                  <l>God himſelf <hi>buried:</hi> Where, 's unknown to men,</l>
                  <l>In ſilence <hi>bury</hi> all ſuch queſtions then.</l>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="book">
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:103970:18"/>
               <head>The book of <hi>JOSHUAH.</hi>
               </head>
               <div n="69" type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>69. RAHABS</hi> preſerving the two ſpies. <hi>ch. 2. v. 15.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>IN ſaving them ſhe ſav'd herſelf, who by</l>
                  <l>Her craft ſo hid the <hi>ſpies,</hi> none could them <hi>ſpie;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And though an harlot, yet in this did well,</l>
                  <l>Proving a <hi>common</hi> friend to Iſrael.</l>
                  <l>Down by a <hi>cord</hi> ſhe let them, which did move</l>
                  <l>Their hearts, and drew them with a <hi>cord</hi> of love.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="70" type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>70.</hi> Bind this line of ſcarlet thread in the window. <hi>ch. 2. v. 18.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>Great Joſhuah dare not ſiege'gainſt this houſe lay,</l>
                  <l>Where Rahab doth her bloudy flagge diſplay.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="71" type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>71.</hi> Jordan dried up. <hi>ch. 3.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>Where Joſhuah goes, the Ark muſt go before,</l>
                  <l>An Ark muſt ſave part of mankind once more.</l>
                  <l>Jordan, though he o'reflows his banks, for fear</l>
                  <l>Retires, ſeeing the fiery pillar near.</l>
                  <l>The billows, from above, of leave debarr'd</l>
                  <l>T' run down, here rev'rently keep court of guard:</l>
                  <l>The waves below, ſeeing no ſuccour nigh,</l>
                  <l>Streight ſhrink away, and leave their channel dry:</l>
                  <l>O wonder! which, who looks on, ſees more clear</l>
                  <l>Then Jordans chryſtall waters do appear;</l>
                  <l>For they are <hi>troubled,</hi> and yet <hi>glad</hi> that ſo</l>
                  <l>Iſrael might o're them without <hi>trouble</hi> go.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="72" type="epigram">
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:103970:19"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>72.</hi> And <hi>JOSHUAH</hi> ſet up twelve ſtones in the midſt of <hi>JORDAN. ch. 4. v. 9.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>Twelve ſtones are fix'd, whereby, at once, are ſhew'd</l>
                  <l>Gods mercy and their humble gratitude.</l>
                  <l>Thoſe monuments may fail, in my mind, though</l>
                  <l>The thought of this ſhall ever freſhly <hi>flow.</hi>
                  </l>
               </div>
               <div n="73" type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>73.</hi> An Angel appears to <hi>JOSHUAH. ch. 5. v. 13.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>Now Angels meat 'gan ceaſe, though Manna fell</l>
                  <l>No more, yet Angels ſelves aid Iſrael;</l>
                  <l>And when they <hi>draw</hi> their ſwords, there's cauſe to fear</l>
                  <l>(Or rather, hope) that th' Heathens fall <hi>draws</hi> near.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="74" type="epigram">
                  <head>74. JOSHUAH. ch. 6.</head>
                  <l>Kings conquer'd were by his victorious hand,</l>
                  <l>The dayes bright Carman ſtaid at his command:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ay</hi>'s lofty towers, for <hi>aye,</hi> to wrack did go;</l>
                  <l>He with an engine beat down Jericho.</l>
                  <l>No <hi>iron-horn'd-ram</hi> 'twas, but the meer ſound</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>rams-horns</hi> raz'd its walls unto the ground:</l>
                  <l>Theſe ruines lift his name unto the skie,</l>
                  <l>Thoſe horns reſound his praiſe continually.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="75" type="epigram">
                  <head>75. ACHANS <hi>wedge.</hi> ch. 7.</head>
                  <l>Accurſed wretch, who by th' accurſed thing,</l>
                  <l>A <hi>generall</hi> curſe on Iſrael didſt bring;</l>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:103970:19"/>
                  <l> And almoſt on its <hi>generall:</hi> Ay could ſtrike</l>
                  <l>Iſra'l, when thou with hell hadſt done the like:</l>
                  <l>Hadſt <hi>ſtruck</hi> a bargain, wherein thou didſt prove</l>
                  <l>So faſt <hi>wedg'd in</hi> with filthy lucres love,</l>
                  <l>Yet <hi>looſe</hi> in thy deſires, burying thy pelf</l>
                  <l>Ill got, not getting buriall for thy ſelf.</l>
                  <l>If buried, yet alive, a heap of ſtones</l>
                  <l>Reward thine avarice, not precious ones.</l>
                  <l>Two hundred ſhekles! a ſufficient bait;</l>
                  <l>But they're not of the <hi>Sanctuary weight:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That thou for them ſhouldſt hazard life, it was</l>
                  <l>In my opinion <hi>too light</hi> a cauſe.</l>
                  <l>Waſt thou an Iſra'lite, and couldſt ſo dote</l>
                  <l>To covet thus a <hi>Babyloniſh</hi> coat?</l>
                  <l>Thou haſt what thou deſir'ſt, and more; for, ſee</l>
                  <l>How <hi>Babels</hi> ruines, wretch, are fell on thee.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="76" type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>76.</hi> The Sunne ſtanding still. <hi>ch. 10.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>Why this unuſuall Solſtice made the Sunne?</l>
                  <l>That with his ſpeed great Ioſhuah might runne.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="77" type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>77.</hi> Be ye the children of light. <hi>chap. 10.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>Sunne ſtand thou ſtill, thus Ioſhua ſaid; the Sunne</l>
                  <l>Amaz'd forgot's diurnall race to runne:</l>
                  <l>He truly is a child of light, whoſe faith</l>
                  <l>So great an influence o're Lights emp'rour hath.</l>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="book">
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:103970:20"/>
               <head>The book of <hi>JUDGES.</hi>
               </head>
               <div n="78" type="epigram">
                  <head>78. JAEL <hi>killing</hi> SISERA. ch. 4. v. 21.</head>
                  <l>THou woman Worthy, who ſhall aye rehearſe</l>
                  <l>Thy act heroick in heroick verſe?</l>
                  <l>For nailing that proud Pagan's temples down,</l>
                  <l>Thy temples do deſerve a laurell crown.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="79" type="epigram">
                  <head>79. GIDEONS <hi>fliece.</hi> ch. 6.</head>
                  <l>The fleece was wet, and yet no dew was found</l>
                  <l>Upon the ground:</l>
                  <l>The ground was wet, and yet the fleece did lie</l>
                  <l>Upon it dry.</l>
                  <l>Dry! 'twas a miracle, but when dew fell,</l>
                  <l>O then it fatneſſe drop'd on Iſrael.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="80" type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>80.</hi> Aliud. <hi>ch. 6.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>Admire the golden ſheep-skin, youths of Greece.</l>
                  <l>I find more wonder farre in Gideons fleece.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="81" type="epigram">
                  <head>81. GIDEONS <hi>ſtratagem.</hi> ch. 7.</head>
                  <l>How great, how glorious a conqueſt came,</l>
                  <l>From ſound of trumpets and of Gideons name!</l>
                  <l>Thoſe lamps in Iſraels darkeſt, gloomieſt night,</l>
                  <l>Were thoſe, that ſhone, and uſher'd in the light.</l>
                  <l>The Midianites, though ten and more to one,</l>
                  <l>By <hi>pitchers,</hi> not <hi>pitcht</hi> fight, were overthrown.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="82" type="epigram">
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:103970:20"/>
                  <head>82. <hi>A woman killeth</hi> ABIMELECH. ch. 9.</head>
                  <l>Great warriour, who ſo oft haſt vanquiſhed</l>
                  <l>Strong men, ſhall a weak woman break thy head?</l>
                  <l>Well I'll excuſe the matter as 'twas done;</l>
                  <l>Thou diedſt not of her hand but of the <hi>ſtone.</hi>
                  </l>
               </div>
               <div n="83" type="epigram">
                  <head>83. JEPHTHAH. ch. 11.</head>
                  <l>To vow, methinks, it was too raſh a thing,</l>
                  <l>But more to offer ſuch an offering:</l>
                  <l>With bloud thy vow and countrey thus <hi>to free,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For which thy daughter's not much <hi>bound</hi> to thee.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="84" type="epigram">
                  <head>84. SAMSON. ch. 11.</head>
                  <l>Samſon o'recome by her, whoſe <hi>arms</hi> entwine</l>
                  <l>About thee, not by th' <hi>arms</hi> oth' Philiſtine:</l>
                  <l>Shee blinded thee before, no wonder then,</l>
                  <l>That they could bind, and blind thee o're agen.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="85" type="epigram">
                  <head>85. <hi>Aliud.</hi> chap. 11.</head>
                  <l>Strong Samſon dallying with his Dalilah,</l>
                  <l>Confeſſed to her where his power lay.</l>
                  <l>She treach'rouſly rob'd him of that, and then</l>
                  <l>He differr'd not <hi>an hair</hi> from other men.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="86" type="epigram">
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:103970:21"/>
                  <head>86. RUTH.</head>
                  <l>RUth with malignant fortune long oppreſt,</l>
                  <l>At laſt with honour, wealth, and husband bleſt:</l>
                  <l>Freed from her wandring troubles and annoy,</l>
                  <l>And yet ſhe's <hi>Ruth-full</hi> now (I mean) of joy.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="87" type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>87. BOAZ</hi> his kindneſſe to <hi>RUTH. ch. 2.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>Boaz to Ruth a ſtranger, kind! O know</l>
                  <l>What kindneſſe God to her in that did ſhow.</l>
                  <l>So well ſhe <hi>husbanded</hi> this kindneſſe; from</l>
                  <l>Her ſeed the Prince of peace in time did come,</l>
                  <l>Springing from her in <hi>direct line;</hi> yet is</l>
                  <l>To us the <hi>centre</hi> of eternall bliſſe.</l>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="book">
               <head>The firſt book of <hi>SAMUEL.</hi>
               </head>
               <div n="88" type="epigram">
                  <head>88. SAMUEL. ch. 3.</head>
                  <l>FRom's infancy in Gods houſe made abode:</l>
                  <l>God called him, ere he could call on God.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="89" type="epigram">
                  <head>89. SAUL. ch. 10.</head>
                  <l>Fortune to thee, O ſonne of Kiſh, was kind,</l>
                  <l>Who looking for an aſſe a crown didſt find.</l>
               </div>
               <div type="epigram">
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:103970:21"/>
                  <head>DAVID. ch. 16.</head>
                  <l>Bleſt David, bleſt abroad, and bleſt at home;</l>
                  <l>Bleſt in the ſeed that from thy loyns did come:</l>
                  <l>But bleſt 'bove all in thy harps harmonie,</l>
                  <l>Which with thy minds rare temper did agree;</l>
                  <l>Whoſe tunes inſtruct the warbling orbs to ſing</l>
                  <l>Their Hallelujahs to their heavenly King.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="91" type="epigram">
                  <head>91. DAVID <hi>ſlaying</hi> GOLIAH. ch. 18.</head>
                  <l>A bold attempt it was and venturous</l>
                  <l>To offer to <hi>affront</hi> a Giant thus</l>
                  <l>With a poor ſling: this act of valour, when</l>
                  <l>Thou didſt, thou tookſt time by the <hi>foretop</hi> then.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="92" type="epigram">
                  <head>92. IONATHAN. ch. 18.</head>
                  <l>Of all Sauls iſſue, Ionathan alone</l>
                  <l>Merits high praiſe and commendation;</l>
                  <l>Who did, with all he had, to's girdle, part,</l>
                  <l>And ti'd that zone of love 'bout Davids heart,</l>
                  <l>Which with a knot of friendſhip he did ty</l>
                  <l>So faſt as laſts unto eternity.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="93" type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>93. SAUL</hi> enquireth of a witch at <hi>ENDOR. ch. 18.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>Had Saul live Samuels counſel followed,</l>
                  <l>He never would have ſought him being dead.</l>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="book">
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:103970:22"/>
               <head>The ſecond book of <hi>SAMUEL.</hi>
               </head>
               <div n="94" type="epigram">
                  <head>94. BATSHEBA, ch. IX.</head>
                  <l>THy <hi>bathing</hi> thee, to <hi>cool</hi> thy ſelf, did prove</l>
                  <l>The way to ſet David <hi>on fire</hi> in love.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="95" type="epigram">
                  <head>95. ABSALOM. ch. 14.</head>
                  <l>Thy hair, O Abſolom, the Scriptures ſaid,</l>
                  <l>Two hundred ſhekells every year it <hi>weigh'd:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Theſe locks, young-man, which now thou holdſt ſo dear,</l>
                  <l>Will <hi>weigh</hi> no leſſe then thy lifes price I fear.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="96" type="epigram">
                  <head>96. AHITHOPHEL. ch. 17.</head>
                  <l>Too wiſe a ſtateſman, curſt Achitophel,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe every word was thought an oracle.</l>
                  <l>'Twas not the wiſeſt part thou ere didſt play,</l>
                  <l>To rid thy ſelf, a traitour, out oth' way.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="97" type="epigram">
                  <head>97. ABSALOM <hi>hangedon a tree.</hi> ch. 18. v. 9.</head>
                  <l>Promotion on the throne, Abſalom, that</l>
                  <l>The chiefeſt thing was which thou aimedſt at.</l>
                  <l>Promotion, 'cauſe thou wilt, thou ſhalt; 't muſt be,</l>
                  <l>Not on thy fathers throne though, but a tree;</l>
                  <l>Which tree of all the trees that ever were,</l>
                  <l>Then bore the baſeſt fruit when thou hung'ſt there.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="98" type="epigram">
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:103970:22"/>
                  <head>98. DAVID <hi>weepeth for</hi> ABSALOM. ch. 18. the laſt v.</head>
                  <l>What aileth holy Davids grief to riſe?</l>
                  <l>Look how the tears runne trickling down his eyes.</l>
                  <l>'Tis for his ſonne, his deareſt ſonne, alas!</l>
                  <l>Which lately 'gainſt him in rebellion was.</l>
                  <l>His death ſo much he wails not, as 'cauſe he</l>
                  <l>Liv'd not t' repent him of his treachery.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="99" type="epigram">
                  <head>99. JOAB <hi>killeth</hi> AMAZA. ch. 20.</head>
                  <l>What fiend, foul Traitour, thy fell heart did move</l>
                  <l>To make thy malice in a ſeeming love?</l>
                  <l>O baſeneſſe! (with a complement to do't)</l>
                  <l>To take him by <hi>the beard,</hi> but mean <hi>the throat!</hi>
                  </l>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="book">
               <head>The firſt book of <hi>KINGS.</hi>
               </head>
               <div n="100" type="epigram">
                  <head>100. SOLOMONS <hi>choice.</hi> ch. 3. v. 9.</head>
                  <l>RIches and honour, Power and Majeſty</l>
                  <l>Were offer'd, Heav'n-bleſt Solomon, to thee.</l>
                  <l>Wiſdome was offer'd too amongſt the reſt,</l>
                  <l>Which thou prefer'dſt, as of all gifts the beſt:</l>
                  <l>That thou wert wiſe before, this wiſe choice ſhows,</l>
                  <l>Elſe thou hadſt never known ſo to have choſe.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="101" type="epigram">
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:103970:23"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>101.</hi> The two harlots. <hi>ch. 3. v. 16.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>Wiſeſt of Kings, who hear'ſt two harlots plead,</l>
                  <l>Both challenging the live child, not the dead:</l>
                  <l>How wilt thou find its mother! wilt thou go</l>
                  <l>To part the living babe, and kill that too?</l>
                  <l>The true one ſooner with her own will <hi>part,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Then have it <hi>parted,</hi> which would kill her heart.</l>
                  <l>By the remorſleſſe anſwer of the other</l>
                  <l>Thou cam'ſt to know which is, which not, the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</l>
                  <l>'Twas wiſdome that, but't had beeen greater rather,</l>
                  <l>Couldſt thou have then found out the childs <hi>true Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi>
                  </l>
               </div>
               <div n="102" type="epigram">
                  <head>102. SOLOMON. ch. 3.</head>
                  <l>What doth thy wiſdome boot thee, Solomon?</l>
                  <l>Thou'lt find it but an earths vexation;</l>
                  <l>Except thou know'ſt thy ſelf naked and poor,</l>
                  <l>Thou'lt know th'art not ſo wiſe, who know'ſt no more.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="103" type="epigram">
                  <head>103. <hi>The Queen of</hi> SHEBA. ch 10.</head>
                  <l>Fair Queen, thy coming is an honeſt ſtealth:</l>
                  <l>Thou tak'ſt more wiſdome, then thou leaveſt wealth</l>
               </div>
               <div n="104" type="epigram">
                  <head>104. REHOBOAM. ch. 12. v. 8.</head>
                  <l>Unlike his father Rehoboam makes</l>
                  <l>Youths of his counſell, and old age forſakes;</l>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:103970:23"/>
                  <l> He goes about with ſharp replies, not mild</l>
                  <l>Perſwaſions, to qualifie the wild</l>
                  <l>Uproars: how he could think to guide his Realme</l>
                  <l>That drove his boat againſt the common ſtream!</l>
               </div>
               <div n="105" type="epigram">
                  <head>105. <hi>Aliud.</hi> ch. 12.</head>
                  <l>Fond Rehoboam, hadſt thou ſerv'd one day</l>
                  <l>The people, they had ſerved thee for aye.</l>
                  <l>They now crown Jeroboam with applauſe,</l>
                  <l>Yet <hi>ſerve</hi> thee: how? truly <hi>in thine own ſauce.</hi>
                  </l>
               </div>
               <div n="106" type="epigram">
                  <head>106. JEROBOAM. ch. 12. v. the laſt.</head>
                  <l>By goodly words and ſly inſinuation</l>
                  <l>He <hi>reined in,</hi> and <hi>reigned</hi> o're a nation:</l>
                  <l>Whom God had promis'd, if he would perſevere</l>
                  <l>In righteouſneſſe, his ſeed ſhould rule for ever;</l>
                  <l>But having Golden <hi>calves</hi> for true Gods plac'd,</l>
                  <l>His race extirp'd, he prov'd the <hi>calf</hi> at laſt.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="107" type="epigram">
                  <head>107. <hi>The Prophet ſlain.</hi> ch. 13.</head>
                  <l>Hadſt thou but liſt'ned to Gods word aright,</l>
                  <l>Thou need'dſt not, fearing him, fear lions might.</l>
                  <l>Thy beaſt did ſcape, but thou wert ſlain, alas!</l>
                  <l>Perchance the lion took thee for the aſſe.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="108" type="epigram">
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:103970:24"/>
                  <head>108. JEROBOAMS <hi>wife,</hi> ch. 14.</head>
                  <l>Why didſt thou come diſguis'd? diſſembledſt too</l>
                  <l>Thy voyce, and thought to gull the prophet ſo;</l>
                  <l>His mind is clear, though blind his eye-ſight be;</l>
                  <l>Could he thy childs fate know, and not know thee?</l>
               </div>
               <div n="109" type="epigram">
                  <head>109. ELISHA. ch. 17.</head>
                  <l>Ravens preſerv'd thy life with food, I reade,</l>
                  <l>Who others with the bread of life didſt feed.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="110" type="epigram">
                  <head>110. BAALS <hi>prieſts and</hi> ELISHA. ch. 18.</head>
                  <l>Baul louder, Baal doth his friends forget,</l>
                  <l>He's thick of hearing ſure; baul louder yet,</l>
                  <l>Perchance his Godhead now a nap doth take;</l>
                  <l>And being drowſie,'s ſomewhat loth to wake.</l>
                  <l>He's gone a journey, pray him take the pain</l>
                  <l>To ſpur his ſteed, and ride home <hi>poſt</hi> again:</l>
                  <l>Or, 'midſt the groans of dying enemies,</l>
                  <l>Perchance, he cannot hear your feeble cries.</l>
                  <l>All done, yet nothing done, their fleſh they tear</l>
                  <l>And cut; yet ſullen Baal will not hear:</l>
                  <l>But at Eliſha's pray'r, is forthwith given</l>
                  <l>Fire to conſume his ſacrifice from heaven:</l>
                  <l>Then for theſe Prieſts, who ſpilt ſome bloud in jeſt,</l>
                  <l>The prophet in good earneſt ſpilt the reſt.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="111" type="epigram">
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:103970:24"/>
                  <head>111. AHAB. ch. 22.</head>
                  <l>Thou art forbid expreſſely; art thou mad,</l>
                  <l>Yet to go up to Ramoth-Gilead?</l>
                  <l>Diſmount quick from thy chariot again,</l>
                  <l>Perchance thou mai'ſt, perchance thou ſhalt, be ſlain.</l>
                  <l>Why, ſold to wickedneſſe, doſt thou go forth?</l>
                  <l>The devil's a chapman for that pennyworth:</l>
                  <l>Thou goeſt diſguiz'd for fear of being known,</l>
                  <l>But, to thy coſt, thou'lt know, he knows his own.</l>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="book">
               <head>The ſecond book of <hi>KINGS.</hi>
               </head>
               <div n="112" type="epigram">
                  <head>112. ELIIAH <hi>tranſlated.</hi> ch. 2.</head>
                  <l>VVHen thou in fiery carr wert drawn to th'sky,</l>
                  <l>Thy mantle dropt from thee immediately;</l>
                  <l>To ſhew that when we ſeek heav'n in our mind,</l>
                  <l>We ought to leave all earthly things behind.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="113" type="epigram">
                  <head>113. <hi>Aliud.</hi> ch. 2.</head>
                  <l>Good Prophet, almoſt with thy lateſt breath,</l>
                  <l>Thy ſoul thou to Eliſha didſt bequeath:</l>
                  <l>Thy body wond'rouſly to heaven doth go,</l>
                  <l>More wondrouſly thy ſoul did ſtay below.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="114" type="epigram">
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:103970:25"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>114. ELISHA</hi> increaſeth the widows oyl. <hi>ch. 4.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>The oyl pour'd out caus'd this poor widows ſadneſſe;</l>
                  <l>But thus pour'd out, it prov'd the oyl of gladneſſe:</l>
                  <l>Bring me, ſhe ſaid, another bottle, boy.</l>
                  <l>There's none: ſhe next will fill her heart with joy.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="115" type="epigram">
                  <head>115. <hi>Aliud.</hi> ch. 4.</head>
                  <l>The widow put ſmall truſt in God, ere while,</l>
                  <l>But as her faith increas'd ſo did her oyl.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="116" type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>116.</hi> Death in the pot. <hi>ch. 4.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>They ſay life's ſweet, nor do they ſay amiſſe;</l>
                  <l>Hence comes to paſſe that death ſo bitter is:</l>
                  <l>Eliſha flung in meal; for had he not,</l>
                  <l>They all were likely to have <hi>gone to pot.</hi>
                  </l>
               </div>
               <div n="117" type="epigram">
                  <head>117. NAAMANS <hi>leproſie.</hi> ch. 5. v. 10.</head>
                  <l>Waſh in no other but in Iordans floud,</l>
                  <l>'Tis <hi>holy water</hi> that muſt do thee good.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="118" type="epigram">
                  <head>118. GEHAZI. ch. 5. v. 26.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Went not my heart</hi> with thee, (Eliſha ſaid)</l>
                  <l>When Naaman with preſents did thee lade?</l>
                  <l>Ono, thou righteous prophet, ſay not ſo,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Thy heart</hi> did not <hi>along with that deed go.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>White</hi> innocence is gone, but in its room</l>
                  <l>A direfull <hi>white</hi> of leproſie is come.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="119" type="epigram">
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:103970:25"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>119.</hi> The Syrians ſtruck with blindneſſe. <hi>ch. 6.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>In vain, O Syrian, doſt thou counſel take,</l>
                  <l>Eliſha fruſtrate thy device doth make.</l>
                  <l>If thou thy ſecrets ſhouldſt to none impart,</l>
                  <l>He'd fetch them from thy <hi>ſecretſt</hi> cheſt, thy heart:</l>
                  <l>Nor fears he whom thou ſendeſt him to kill;</l>
                  <l>Horſemen, and fiery chariots guard him ſtill;</l>
                  <l>And now their eyes he doth not onely blind,</l>
                  <l>But ev'n infatuates their very mind,</l>
                  <l>Strikes them with blindneſſe doubly, leads them on</l>
                  <l>To death, yet ſaves them from deſtruction.</l>
                  <l>Ioram would ſmite them, he bids ſmite no more</l>
                  <l>With blindneſſe, they were ſmote enough before.</l>
                  <l>A banquet, laſtly, he prepares for them,</l>
                  <l>Who had prepar'd a bloudy one for him.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="120" type="epigram">
                  <head>120. IEZABEL. ch. 9.</head>
                  <l>Proud painted creatures ſee, and wonder at</l>
                  <l>This <hi>Queen,</hi> this <hi>Quean,</hi> by <hi>dogs dogg'd</hi> to her fate:</l>
                  <l>She, who but late in rich attire was found,</l>
                  <l>Now lies a prey for maſtives on the ground;</l>
                  <l>Although ſhe went moſt richly cloth'd in all</l>
                  <l>Her jewells, <hi>pride</hi> at laſt <hi>would have a fall:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Her carrion ſtinks now unperfum'd by art;</l>
                  <l>Now, Iezabel, thou in thy <hi>colours</hi> art.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="121" type="epigram">
                  <head>121. AHABS <hi>ſeventy ſonnes.</hi> ch. 10. v. 7.</head>
                  <l>Ahab, thou haſt a numerous ſeed,</l>
                  <l>But all before their time muſt bleed.</l>
                  <l>How in a moment all are gone!</l>
                  <l>Their bloud cementing Iehu's throne.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="122" type="epigram">
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:103970:26"/>
                  <head>122. BAALS <hi>prieſts ſlain.</hi> ch. 10.25.</head>
                  <l>So, near-ſpent candles give a blaze before</l>
                  <l>Their ſnuff's extinguiſh'd, and they ſhine no more?</l>
                  <l>When Iehu dignifies the prieſts of Baal,</l>
                  <l>I fear this pomp is for their funerall.</l>
                  <l>The offering to make ready, each one hies,</l>
                  <l>Poor fools your ſelves muſt be the ſacrifice.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="123" type="epigram">
                  <head>123. JOASH <hi>hid in the houſe of</hi> GOD. ch. 11.</head>
                  <l>O happy receptacle! happy he,</l>
                  <l>Who hid ſecure ith' houſe of God could be!</l>
                  <l>But O more happy Ioaſh, had the God</l>
                  <l>Of that houſe, in thy hearts houſe made abode!</l>
               </div>
               <div n="124" type="epigram">
                  <head>124. HEZEKIAH. ch. 20.</head>
                  <l>Good Hezekiah, ſick almoſt to death,</l>
                  <l>His life for fifteen years prolonged hath:</l>
                  <l>The ſigne whereof upon a diall made,</l>
                  <l>The Sunne fifteen degrees went retrograde.</l>
                  <l>Unthankfull he, in his hearts diall, ſo</l>
                  <l>The Sunne of righteouſneſſe did backward go,</l>
               </div>
               <div n="125" type="epigram">
                  <head>125. IOSIAH. ch. 23.</head>
                  <l>Ioſiah the high places down did throw,</l>
                  <l>And meekly his own heart did lay as low.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="126" type="epigram">
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:103970:26"/>
                  <head>126. ZEDEKIAH. ch. 25.</head>
                  <l>All things concurre, O king, to ruine thee;</l>
                  <l>Firſt thy rebellion, next thy perjury:</l>
                  <l>O, if thou Jeremies advice hadſt took,</l>
                  <l>To bear, perchance thou hadſt ſhook off, the yoke.</l>
                  <l>Thou ſaw'ſt thy children ſlain; new miſeries!</l>
                  <l>To ſee that object ere thou loſt thine eyes.</l>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="book">
               <head>The firſt book of <hi>CHRONICLES.</hi>
               </head>
               <div n="127" type="epigram">
                  <head>127. DAVIDS <hi>ſervants ſhav'd by</hi> HANUN. ch. 19.</head>
                  <l>MUſt thus Embaſſadours rewarded be?</l>
                  <l>You <hi>ſhavers,</hi> bearded thus deſpitefully;</l>
                  <l>To receive Legats you not worthy are;</l>
                  <l>Expect now Heralds to denounce a warre.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="128" type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>128.</hi> The Giant ſlain by Jonathan. <hi>ch. 20. v. 7.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>Defying Iſrael, thou ſoon ſhalt feel</l>
                  <l>The edge of Jonathans revengefull ſteel;</l>
                  <l>Not that ſo monſtrous bulk his force withſtands,</l>
                  <l>Though thou thy ſelf <hi>a man</hi> art <hi>of</hi> thy <hi>hands:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Six fingers, and ſix toes: and yet th' art <hi>dead,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Thy <hi>ſteddy</hi> feet have <hi>ſtood</hi> thee in ſmall <hi>ſtead.</hi>
                  </l>
               </div>
               <div n="129" type="epigram">
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:103970:27"/>
                  <head>129. DAVIDS <hi>choice.</hi> ch. 21. v. 12.</head>
                  <l>Sword, famine, peſtilence! hard choice; yet one</l>
                  <l>O'th' three thou haſt in thy election,</l>
                  <l>Chooſe quickly then; ſince thou muſt <hi>fall,</hi> it <hi>ſtands</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Thee in ſome ſtead to fall into Gods hands:</l>
                  <l>By numbring Iſrael what didſt thou get?</l>
                  <l>Since that's the way but to diminiſh it.</l>
                  <l>The Angel ſtretcheth out his hand, but 'tis</l>
                  <l>In vain, now David 'gins to ſtretch out his.</l>
                  <l>Bleſt Nuntius, hold; a fume t'aſcend begins,</l>
                  <l>Which drives away both ſtench of plague and ſinnes.</l>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="book">
               <head>The ſecond book of <hi>CHRONICLES.</hi>
               </head>
               <div n="130" type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>130. SOLOMONS</hi> prayer at the dedication of the temple. <hi>ch. 6. v. 13.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>THe temple by a pray'r is conſecrated,</l>
                  <l>To which ſole uſe 'twas to be dedicated:</l>
                  <l>Who, by Heavens wiſdome, knew this houſe to rear,</l>
                  <l>Knew, the main column of it muſt be pray'r.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="131" type="epigram">
                  <head>131. ASA. ch. 15.</head>
                  <l>To the Pyſicians thou did'ſt truſt, I find</l>
                  <l>The greateſt ſickneſſe then was of thy mind.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="132" type="epigram">
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:103970:27"/>
                  <head>132. JEHOSHAPHAT. ch. 18.</head>
                  <l>If thou with Ahab needs wilt partner go,</l>
                  <l>Look with his pleaſure to partake his wo.</l>
                  <l>Ahab and thou to mask your ſelves combin'd,</l>
                  <l>He to diſguiſe his body, thou thy mind.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="133" type="epigram">
                  <head>133. MANASSEH. ch. 33.</head>
                  <l>In thy proſperity, perverſly, thou</l>
                  <l>Did'ſt follow other gods, forſook'ſt the true:</l>
                  <l>Dealt'ſt with <hi>familiar ſpirits;</hi> but, brought low</l>
                  <l>By miſeries, thy heart was humbled too.</l>
                  <l>Thou from thy kingdome, and thy God waſt gone:</l>
                  <l>Return'ſt to God, return'ſt unto thy throne;</l>
                  <l>Yet with a <hi>ſpirit</hi> now thou deal'ſt, I gheſſe,</l>
                  <l>Not of the devil, but of <hi>righteouſneſſe.</hi>
                  </l>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="book">
               <head>The book of <hi>EZRA.</hi>
               </head>
               <div n="134" type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>134.</hi> The dedication of the ſecond temple. <hi>ch. 3. v. 12.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>TWo different effects ariſe and flow</l>
                  <l>From the ſame cauſe, both joy and ſorrow too,</l>
                  <l>'Tis hard to judge, whether the oyl of gladneſſe</l>
                  <l>Repells, or is repell'd, by th'ſtream of ſadneſſe:</l>
                  <l>Both torments ſtrive, but the old's limping courſe</l>
                  <l>At laſt is drowned by this freſher ſource.</l>
                  <l>Ancient, and young, to th' temples conſecration</l>
                  <l>Contribute: thoſe give cries, theſe acclamation.</l>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="book">
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:103970:28"/>
               <head>The book of <hi>NEHEMIAH.</hi>
               </head>
               <div n="135" type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>135.</hi> And their children ſpake half in the language of Aſhdod. <hi>ch. 13. v. 24.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>MIxing with forraign nations, you ſhall ſo</l>
                  <l>Be made partakers of their fortune too.</l>
                  <l>How ſhould they ſpeak pure Hebrew, when they had</l>
                  <l>Their firſt originall ſo impure and bad?</l>
                  <l>Their mothers nurtur'd them, and who's among</l>
                  <l>Children, that ſucks not in his Mothers tongue?</l>
                  <l>Whilſt thus you match with nations Orientall,</l>
                  <l>Your righteouſneſſe is in the Occidentall.</l>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="book">
               <head>The book of <hi>ESTHER.</hi>
               </head>
               <div n="136" type="epigram">
                  <head>136. <hi>Queen</hi> VASNTI. ch. 1.</head>
                  <l>KIng Ahaſuerus ſent for's beauteous Queen,</l>
                  <l>That ſhe of all his Nobles might be ſeen.</l>
                  <l>Why Vaſhti wouldſt not come? waſt pride, or fear,</l>
                  <l>Thou ſhouldſt not beauteous in their eyes appear?</l>
                  <l>Do not expect from him a ſecond call,</l>
                  <l>The next thou hear'ſt; Thou muſt not come at all.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="137" type="epigram">
                  <head>137. ESTHER. ch. 2.</head>
                  <l>Eſther elected in Queen Vaſhti's place,</l>
                  <l>Obtained both with King and people grace.</l>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:103970:28"/>
                  <l> The golden ſceptre was held forth t' aſſure</l>
                  <l>Her, that her ſutes his favour ſhould procure:</l>
                  <l>Good God, when I approch thy throne, hold thou</l>
                  <l>Thy mercies golden ſceptre forth, and bow</l>
                  <l>Thine eare to my requeſts: protect me ſtill,</l>
                  <l>And let no <hi>man,</hi> no <hi>Haman</hi> work me ill.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="138" type="epigram">
                  <head>138. HAMAN <hi>and</hi> MORDECAI. ch. 7. v. 10.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Hamanth'</hi> art but <hi>a man,</hi> why then doſt thou</l>
                  <l>Grudge that the Jew unto thee doth not bow?</l>
                  <l>Thou covet'ſt to be higher made then he;</l>
                  <l>Thou ſhalt, but, Haman, how? upon a tree.</l>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="book">
               <head>The book of <hi>JOB.</hi>
               </head>
               <div n="139" type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>139. JOBS</hi> patience.</head>
                  <l>HIs cattel ſtoln, goods ſpoil'd, and children ſlain;</l>
                  <l>Yet after all Jobs patience did remain:</l>
                  <l>On each part of his body ſores you'll find,</l>
                  <l>But not a ſpot of ſinne did taint his mind;</l>
                  <l>So that the tempter's ſelf was tired more,</l>
                  <l>With tort'ring, then he who the tortures bore.</l>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="book">
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:103970:29"/>
               <head>The book of <hi>PSALMES.</hi>
               </head>
               <div n="140" type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>140.</hi> The fear of the Lord is the beginning of wiſdome. <hi>Pſal. 111.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>DId little children Chriſts-croſſe truly know,</l>
                  <l>They quickly would be taught the reſt oth' row.</l>
                  <l>Had we but gain'd this fear, we need not fear</l>
                  <l>To gain all knowledge, worth our knowledge here.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="141" type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>141.</hi> I have thought upon thy name in the night-ſeaſon. <hi>Pſal. 119. v. 7. oct. 7.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>When others quiet reſt did take,</l>
                  <l>Toſſing in my bed lay I;</l>
                  <l>Nor would I let heav'n reſt to take,</l>
                  <l>Till heaven eas'd my miſery.</l>
                  <l>At laſt ſuch beams of grace did on me <hi>light,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>As made a ſunſhine in the midſt of night.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="142" type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>142.</hi> At midnight will I riſe to give thanks unto thee. <hi>Pſal. 119. v. 6. oct. 8.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>Ith' deadeſt time oth' night I'll riſe and ſay</l>
                  <l>My oraiſons, then down in peace me lay.</l>
                  <l>By pray'r, and faith, I hope 'bove ſtars to bide,</l>
                  <l>And ſtarres can onely in the night be ſpide.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="143" type="epigram">
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:103970:29"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>143.</hi> Behold how good and joyfull a thing it is, brethren to dwell together in unity. <hi>Pſal. 133. v. 1.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>God to ſend bleſſings down will never ceaſe,</l>
                  <l>On ſuch who live in amity and peace:</l>
                  <l>But O, what other bleſſing can there prove</l>
                  <l>A greater bleſſing unto love, then love!</l>
               </div>
               <div n="144" type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>144.</hi> But mine eyes look unto thee. <hi>Pſal. 141. v. 9.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>All worldly thoughts, forſake my breſt, away;</l>
                  <l>Since worldly pleaſures, like the world, decay:</l>
                  <l>At ſomewhat higher my ſoul aims; her birth</l>
                  <l>She had from heaven, why ſhould ſhe ſtoop to earth?</l>
                  <l>What worthyer object can our fancy find,</l>
                  <l>Then to contemplate him who gave the mind?</l>
                  <l>But why, ambitiouſly, ſeek I to climbe,</l>
                  <l>And ſee what no eye ſaw at any time!</l>
                  <l>Lord, give me faith, then by the eye of grace</l>
                  <l>I ſhall behold thee, though not face to face.</l>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="book">
               <head>
                  <hi>The</hi> PROVERBS <hi>of</hi> SOLOMON.</head>
               <div n="145" type="epigram">
                  <head>145. Chap. 1. v. 1.</head>
                  <l>WHen we for prudence would praiſe any one,</l>
                  <l>We ſay he is as wiſe as Solomon:</l>
                  <l>He who alive ſo many proverbs ſaid,</l>
                  <l>Is after death himſelf a proverb made.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="146" type="epigram">
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:103970:30"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>146.</hi> Cast in thy lot among us, <hi>&amp;c. ch. 1. v. 14.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>Come, let's have all one purſe, be Joviall ſtill,</l>
                  <l>Let's live in common, have the world at will.</l>
                  <l>No, no: my lot 'mongſt yours ſhall never fall,</l>
                  <l>T' have all one purſe, is to have none at all.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="147" type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>147.</hi> Enter not into the paths, <hi>&amp;c. ch. 4. v. 14.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>It is a fair broad way, plain, plauſible,</l>
                  <l>But yet beware, it is the way to hell,</l>
                  <l>Although't be ſtrow'd with roſes altogether,</l>
                  <l>I'll none on't: foh! it ſtinks of brimſtone hither.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="148" type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>148.</hi> Yet a little ſleep, a little ſlumber. <hi>ch. 6. v. 10.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>A little ſlumber more the ſluggard cries,</l>
                  <l>I'll take t'other od nap, and then I'll riſe;</l>
                  <l>Good 'las the weather's very cold indeed,</l>
                  <l>For certain I am glew'd unto my bed:</l>
                  <l>Thus trifles out his time, till poverty</l>
                  <l>Catch him, and 's belly in his face doth fly:</l>
                  <l>Go to the Ant, conſider her; why ſo?</l>
                  <l>The ſluggard will not take the pains to go.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="149" type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>149.</hi> Keep my commandments and live.</head>
                  <l>Keep Gods commandments ſure, and live thereby,</l>
                  <l>His precepts as the apple of thine eye.</l>
                  <l>Obſerve his laws, thou canſt not chooſe but thrive,</l>
                  <l>Since his commandments do command to live.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="150" type="epigram">
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:103970:30"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>150.</hi> Say unto wiſedome thou art my Siſter. <hi>ch. 7. v. 4.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>Since thou this charge, wiſe King, on me doſt lay,</l>
                  <l>Wiſdome, thou art my Siſter, I will ſay;</l>
                  <l>But O! I fear, that ſo unlike we be,</l>
                  <l>She'll not be ſuch a fool t'acknowledge me.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="151" type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>151.</hi> Doth not wiſedome cry? <hi>&amp;c. ch. 8. v. 1.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>Wiſedome about the ſtreets doth crying rome,</l>
                  <l>To ſee if any one will take her home.</l>
                  <l>O uſe her gently, do not with her part,</l>
                  <l>But lock her in the bottom of thy heart:</l>
                  <l>She cries, and cries to think, that all reject her;</l>
                  <l>I'm ſure there's none, but fools, who will neglect her.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="152" type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>152.</hi> I love them who love me. <hi>ch. 8. v. 17.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>I know 'tis wiſedome t' love them who love me;</l>
                  <l>To love mine enemy 'tis piety.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="153" type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>153.</hi> And thoſe who ſeek, <hi>&amp;c. ch. 8. v. 17.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>Wiſedome requires, who would her ſuiters be</l>
                  <l>Muſt ſeek her even from their infancy:</l>
                  <l>She woos us t' woo her early; if we do,</l>
                  <l>We ſhall be certain to wed her, not <hi>woo.</hi>
                  </l>
               </div>
               <div n="154" type="epigram">
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:103970:31"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>154.</hi> Wiſdome hath builded her houſe. <hi>ch. 9. v. 1.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>Wiſedome hath built her houſe, and finiſht it,</l>
                  <l>Made all her rooms, for Kings and Princes, fit.</l>
                  <l>The arts and ſciences do beautifie</l>
                  <l>This Palace, make it ſtand perpetually:</l>
                  <l>Needs muſt it laſt, built in ſo wiſe a ſort,</l>
                  <l>Whom ſev'n ſo mighty columnes do ſupport.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="155" type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>155.</hi> Stoln waters are ſweet. <hi>ch. 9. v. 17.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>Stoln things are like the book Ezekiel eat,</l>
                  <l>Which, to his palate, ſeem'd delicious meat;</l>
                  <l>But ſwallow'd in his belly, out, alas</l>
                  <l>More bitter there, then ever ſweet it was,</l>
                  <l>Let thieves beware, nor on ſtoln treaſures dote;</l>
                  <l>Though ſweet ith' mouth, 'twill choke them in their throat.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="156" type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>156.</hi> It is a ſport to a fool to do miſchief. <hi>ch. 10. v. 23.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>When wicked men do ill, as ſeems them beſt;</l>
                  <l>They ſay, to mend the matter, 'twas in jeſt,</l>
                  <l>And not in earneſt: well, I think not ſo,</l>
                  <l>I think it was not in <hi>good</hi> earneſt though.</l>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="book">
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:103970:31"/>
               <head>ECCLESIASTES.</head>
               <div n="157" type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>157.</hi> In much wiſdome there is much ſorrow. <hi>ch. 1. v. 18.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>IT grieves me much to heare of this; can grief</l>
                  <l>Be got in getting wiſedome? paſt belief!</l>
                  <l>And yet 'tis true: the more we know, the more</l>
                  <l>We grieve our knowledge doth no higher ſoar:</l>
                  <l>Wiſdomes Arithmetick contains but one</l>
                  <l>Grand head, and that's <hi>Multiplication</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of ſorrow: She and I, I ſee, muſt part;</l>
                  <l>What profit comes from ſuch a <hi>ſorry</hi> art?</l>
               </div>
               <div n="158" type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>158.</hi> A good name is better then pretious ointment. <hi>ch. 7. v. 1.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>Give't others: let their curious noſtrills dwell,</l>
                  <l>On precious ointments aromatick ſmell.</l>
                  <l>Beſmear them with thoſe liquid odours; me</l>
                  <l>Set out with thoſe oyl'd arts, let no man ſee:</l>
                  <l>Let me a good name keep; better by farre,</l>
                  <l>An holy <hi>good-man</hi> is, then greater are.</l>
                  <l>The box of ointment broke, ſents ſweet'ſt; but this,</l>
                  <l>Kept whole, moſt redolent and fragrant is.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="159" type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>159.</hi> Truly the light is ſweet. <hi>ch. 11. v. 7.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>Though Sols refulgent rayes dazle our ſight,</l>
                  <l>Thoſe beams are better then the ſhade of night:</l>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:103970:32"/>
                  <l> For who but darkneſſe children fancy it?</l>
                  <l>A time onely for Bats and Screetch-owls fit.</l>
                  <l>I'll look to th' ſunne, and looking may I be</l>
                  <l>Exhal'd a meteor to heav'ns axle-tree.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="160" type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>160.</hi> Remember thy Creatour. <hi>ch. 12. v. 1.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>In youthfull dayes do not forgetfull be</l>
                  <l>Of God, who alwayes doth remember thee;</l>
                  <l>And though thy years be green, yet humbly bring</l>
                  <l>Thy firſtlings; make an Autumn in thy Spring:</l>
                  <l>Thy ſpritefull bloud, as yet, is hot. O why</l>
                  <l>Should zeal, amidſt ſo great flames, frozen die!</l>
                  <l>Think on thy Maker; husband well thy time:</l>
                  <l>In the prime ſervice, O beſtow thy prime;</l>
                  <l>And thou who giv'ſt thy youth to God, wilt ſee,</l>
                  <l>That God will likewiſe give old age to thee.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="161" type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>161.</hi> God ſhall bring every work into judgement. <hi>ch. 12. v. 14.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>God is the judge, who, at the laſt grand day,</l>
                  <l>Shall the juſt guerdon of our labours pay:</l>
                  <l>All works ſhall into light be brought, though none</l>
                  <l>To light eternall, but good works alone.</l>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="book">
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:103970:32"/>
               <head>SOLOMONS SONG, <hi>or</hi> CANTICLES.</head>
               <div n="162" type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>162.</hi> I am black, but comely. <hi>ch. 1. v. 5.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>SOul thou art black, yet Chriſt loves thee,</l>
                  <l>Although nought lovely he can ſee.</l>
                  <l>Though nought but what is naught there grows,</l>
                  <l>He loves thee merely' cauſe he does.</l>
                  <l>It pleaſeth now th' eternall dove,</l>
                  <l>Not onely a white houſe to love.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="163" type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>163.</hi> Look not upon me becauſe I am black. <hi>ch. 1. v. 6.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>Becauſe the ſunne hath look'd upon thee, why</l>
                  <l>To look on thee doſt thou forbid mine eye?</l>
                  <l>Thoſe whom the Sunne of righteouſneſſe looks on,</l>
                  <l>Though they are black now, ſhall be white anon.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="164" type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>164.</hi> As the lillie among the thorns, <hi>&amp;c. ch. 2. v. 2.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>As doth the lillie 'mongſt the thorns; juſt ſo</l>
                  <l>Doth my beloved 'midſt the daughters ſhew:</l>
                  <l>More truly, Lord, were this appli'd to thee,</l>
                  <l>When hanging 'midſt two thieves upon a tree.</l>
                  <l>Thy ſelf's the lillie, not now white, but red;</l>
                  <l>And theſe the thorns are which embrace thy head.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="165" type="epigram">
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:103970:33"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>165.</hi> He brought me to the banqueting-houſe. <hi>ch. 2. v. 4.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>He brought me to a ſummer houſe, and there</l>
                  <l>Did feaſt me with abundance of good chear;</l>
                  <l>Thoſe dainties yet, did not to love me force,</l>
                  <l>Untill he ſerv'd his coarſe, the ſecond courſe.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="166" type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>166.</hi> Comfort me with apples. <hi>ch. 2. v. 5.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>Art ſick? of what diſeaſe? of love? O ſay,</l>
                  <l>What cordiall to thy love-ſick heart wilt lay?</l>
                  <l>Think'ſt thou an apple will give thee relief?</l>
                  <l>Poor ſoul! an apple firſt did cauſe thy grief.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="167" type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>167.</hi> Riſe up my love, my fair one, <hi>&amp;c. ch. 2. v. 10, 11, 12. &amp;c.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>Riſe up my fair one, come away, for lo,</l>
                  <l>The winter's paſt, the ſpring her head doth ſhow;</l>
                  <l>Let not fierce winter in thy chill heart ſtay,</l>
                  <l>I am thy Sun to thaw thoſe froſts away.</l>
                  <l>The chanting birds do imitate the ſpheres;</l>
                  <l>But thy voice were more muſick in my ears.</l>
                  <l>The ſparrows in loves dialect do prate;</l>
                  <l>The turtles bill, then come to me thy mate:</l>
                  <l>The fig-tre puts forth her green fruits; O ſee!</l>
                  <l>They load their boughs; a <hi>fig</hi> for all but thee.</l>
                  <l>The vines about the elms do twine; juſt ſo</l>
                  <l>Let thou and I, in love, together grow.</l>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:103970:33"/>
                  <l> Now preſſing time draws near, I'll vie a floud</l>
                  <l>Of purple with thee; thy vine, and my bloud.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="168" type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>168.</hi> He feedeth among the lillies. <hi>ch. 2. v. 16.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>True didſt thou ſay, wiſe King, indeed,</l>
                  <l>That Chriſt doth 'mongſt the lillies feed:</l>
                  <l>Chriſt loves a pure heart, white as ſnow,</l>
                  <l>Which yet with love of him muſt glow.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="169" type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>169.</hi> I held him, and would not let him go. <hi>ch 3. v. 4.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>Well done: hold faſt my ſoul; let him not go,</l>
                  <l>Nor think to be rid of thee ſo;</l>
                  <l>But he'l deſcend to hell, my ſoul, I fear;</l>
                  <l>Yet hell's no hell while he is there.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="170" type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>170.</hi> His lips drop as the honey-combe. <hi>ch. 4. v. 11.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>If I a <hi>Bee</hi> could <hi>be</hi> (my dear)</l>
                  <l>I'd gather all my hony here.</l>
                  <l>Thy roſeat lips my flow'rs I'd make,</l>
                  <l>And from them ſtore of ſweets would take;</l>
                  <l>And when I full from them did part,</l>
                  <l>I'd ſtore them in my hive, my heart.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="171" type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>171.</hi> A garden inclos'd is my ſiſter. <hi>ch. 4. v. 12.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>A garden, though inclos'd I be</l>
                  <l>To others, I am ope to thee:</l>
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:103970:34"/>
                  <l> A ſpring I am, ſhut up, what though?</l>
                  <l>My waters ſtill to thee-ward flow;</l>
                  <l>A fountain lockt? why Lord? that's ſmall:</l>
                  <l>The key of David opens all.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="172" type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>172.</hi> I ſleep, but my heart waketh. <hi>ch. 5. v. 2.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>Although my outward body ſleep,</l>
                  <l>My mind awake I alwayes keep;</l>
                  <l>Nor does my ſoul e're take a nap</l>
                  <l>In dull ſecurities ſoft lap:</l>
                  <l>In expectation, whilſt I waking wake,</l>
                  <l>My ſoul a ſweeter reſt then ſleep doth take.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="173" type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>173.</hi> He gave me no anſwer. <hi>ch. 5. v. 6.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>He will not anſwer give when thy ſinnes cry,</l>
                  <l>His love is prov'd in taciturnity.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="174" type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>174.</hi> Tell my beloved I am ſick of love. <hi>ch. 5. v. 8.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>Sick! Sick! yet ſick of ſuch a greif am I,</l>
                  <l>I love the cauſer, and the malady;</l>
                  <l>Of which, were I not truly ſoul-ſick, I</l>
                  <l>Am ſure, my ſick-ſoul would for ever die.</l>
                  <l>O wondrous ſickneſſe! where the very grief,</l>
                  <l>Is to it ſelf ſole-med'cine, ſoul-relief!</l>
               </div>
               <div n="175" type="epigram">
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:103970:34"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>175.</hi> What is thy beloved more then another. <hi>ch. 5. v. 9.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>What is he: nay, what is he not? who's he</l>
                  <l>Can be what my beloved is to me?</l>
                  <l>Would you the ſweetneſſe of my lover prove?</l>
                  <l>The onely way's, like me, to learn to love.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="176" type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>176.</hi> His legs are like pillars of marble. <hi>ch. 5. v. 15.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>How aptly Chriſt is here a pillar ſaid?</l>
                  <l>On whom the weight of all the Church is laid.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="177" type="epigram">
                  <head>177. <hi>Aliud.</hi> ch. 5.</head>
                  <l>Chriſt is a marble pillar; were not he,</l>
                  <l>Our ſinnes would cruſh him down immediately.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="178" type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>178.</hi> My dove, my undefiled, is but one. <hi>ch. 6. v. 9.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>Thy coat muſt have no ſeams, one Church muſt be</l>
                  <l>Alone ſav'd, Lord; and ſav'd alone by thee.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="179" type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>179.</hi> Many waters cannot quench love. <hi>ch. 8. v. 7.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>Love is a fire unquenchable; nor can</l>
                  <l>It be extinguiſh'd by the art of man.</l>
                  <l>What water can againſt this fire prevail!</l>
                  <l>Tears are a water, and yet love's beſt oyl:</l>
                  <l>Who hate this love, ſhall for their hatred pay,</l>
                  <l>Their fire ſhall be unquench'd too, at laſt day.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="180" type="epigram">
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:103970:35"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>180.</hi> We have a little Siſter, and ſhe hath no breaſts. <hi>ch. 8. v. 8.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>We have a little Siſter who can ſhew</l>
                  <l>No breaſts, what ſhall our little Siſter do?</l>
                  <l>This ſhall ſhe do; if breaſts her ſelf have none,</l>
                  <l>Suck at my breaſts of conſolation.</l>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="book">
               <head>ISAIAH.</head>
               <div n="181" type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>181.</hi> Therefore with joy ſhall ye draw. <hi>ch. 12. v. 3.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>TO draw, and draw with joy, implies; that, which</l>
                  <l>We toil for with ſuch joy, ſhall make us rich.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="182" type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>182.</hi> We have made a covenant with death. <hi>ch. 18. v. 15.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>You've bid farewell to God; and poaſt to evil,</l>
                  <l>Shook hands with God, and ſtruck hands with the devil.</l>
                  <l>You're now cock-ſure, you think, what e're enſue,</l>
                  <l>Of ſafety, and the devil's as ſure of you:</l>
                  <l>Your bond ſhall be in force, after you die,</l>
                  <l>And bear a date, even to eternity;</l>
                  <l>And he, your all in all, into whoſe pow'r</l>
                  <l>You give up, ſhall be your Executour;</l>
                  <l>And Executer, O! this bargain, then,</l>
                  <l>Undo, or you your ſelves are <hi>undone</hi> men.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="183" type="epigram">
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:103970:35"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>183.</hi> Wo to the rebellious children. <hi>ch. 30. v. 1.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>A Father, and a God omniſcient too;</l>
                  <l>To whom but thee ſhould they for counſel go?</l>
                  <l>They mean to dive down into hell, I fear,</l>
                  <l>And ſearch the depth of dev'liſh wiſdome there.</l>
                  <l>Wo to him who thinks hell a councell fit,</l>
                  <l>Fit 'tis that they, who take, partake of it.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="184" type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>184.</hi> And thine ear ſhall hear a voice behind thee. <hi>ch. 30. v. 31.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>Hear'ſt not a voice cry out of heav'n and ſay,</l>
                  <l>Sin-blinded wretch, th'art out of heavens way:</l>
                  <l>Turn thee, O quickly turn, leſt in a trice</l>
                  <l>Thou headlong fall into a precipice.</l>
                  <l>Direct thy ſteps to goodneſſe, and that's even</l>
                  <l>The plaineſt and <hi>directeſt</hi> way to heaven.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="185" type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>185.</hi> Wo to them that go down to Egypt. <hi>ch. 31. v. 1.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>Wo, wo to them that have at Egypt ſtaid,</l>
                  <l>Look'd down to that, not up to God, for aid;</l>
                  <l>Who in the ſpeed of courſers their truſt put,</l>
                  <l>And reſt ſecure within a Chariot.</l>
                  <l>Are they ſo farre enthrall'd, with ſinne, that fain</l>
                  <l>They'd have th' Egyptian bondage too again?</l>
                  <l>On Egypt ſtaid! but God doth help deny,</l>
                  <l>And then they may ſtay to Eternity,</l>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:103970:36"/>
                  <l> Yet come farre ſhort of hope; although they, to</l>
                  <l>Procure that hop'd, for ſuccour farre do go:</l>
                  <l>On chariots they rely, but O 'twere well,</l>
                  <l>That thoſe the <hi>Chariots were of Iſrael.</hi>
                  </l>
               </div>
               <div n="186" type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>186.</hi> I have blotted out as a thick cloud. <hi>ch. 44. v. 22.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>A ſullen cloud of ſinne our head hangs o're,</l>
                  <l>Which threats to break in judgement evermore;</l>
                  <l>Till with a vengeance falling it oppreſſe</l>
                  <l>The Land, and turn it to a wilderneſſe.</l>
                  <l>Black clouds! black deeds! yet theſe thick fogs of hell</l>
                  <l>The ſunne of glory, riſing, ſhall diſpell.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="187" type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>187.</hi> As one whom his Mother comforteth. <hi>ch. 66. v. 13.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>O comfortable words! words which do prove,</l>
                  <l>The Mothers greater then the Fathers love;</l>
                  <l>Their tender babes they dandle on their knee,</l>
                  <l>And of his babes of grace, as tender's he.</l>
                  <l>O Quinteſſence of happineſſe! if thus,</l>
                  <l>The Father through the Sonne, would comfort us.</l>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="book">
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:103970:36"/>
               <head>JEREMIAH.</head>
               <div n="188" type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>188.</hi> Moreover the word of the Lord. <hi>ch. 1. v. 11.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>THis prophet ſcarce was call'd, when again, God</l>
                  <l>Call'd to ask what he ſaw: an almond rod,</l>
                  <l>By which 'twas ſignifi'd, how ſoon God will,</l>
                  <l>The tenour of his ſacred word fullfill:</l>
                  <l>Bleſt Saint! ſo lately call'd, and yet to ſhoot</l>
                  <l>Thus ſoon, in bringing forth ſuch early fruit.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="189" type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>189.</hi> Runne ye through the ſtreets. <hi>ch. 5. v. 1.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>Runne through Jeruſalem, and find, who can,</l>
                  <l>(If there be one to find) a pious man:</l>
                  <l>Runne through the turning wayes, and ſee if any</l>
                  <l>Do turn his wayes to God among thoſe many:</l>
                  <l>Perſiſt not in that ill, which to <hi>your</hi> ill</l>
                  <l>Will prove: execute judgement, or God will.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="190" type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>190.</hi> O that my head were waters! <hi>ch. 9. v. 1.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>A ſweeping deluge now was coming on,</l>
                  <l>Threatning a generall deſtruction.</l>
                  <l>The prophet this o'reflowing judgement fears,</l>
                  <l>And meets the tidings with a tide of tears;</l>
                  <l>He wiſheth that his head, made water-rills,</l>
                  <l>Might wail their ſinnes the <hi>head</hi>-ſpring of thoſe ills.</l>
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:103970:37"/>
                  <l> The Seer hath <hi>beheld</hi> much miſeries,</l>
                  <l>That now for water he would change his eyes:</l>
                  <l>His eyes, though water, could not vie that floud,</l>
                  <l>Though bloud-ſhed, not enough, bewails the bloud.</l>
                  <l>Crying to heav'n; he could not drown the cry</l>
                  <l>Their ſinnes made, therefore cries perpetually.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="191" type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>191.</hi> Wo is me for my hurt, <hi>&amp;c. ch. 10. v. 19.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>Wo, wo! for what? thou haſt a wound; and he</l>
                  <l>Who gave that wound can give thee remedy:</l>
                  <l>Then bear't with reſolution; let no grief</l>
                  <l>Exceed thy patience, though't exceeds relief.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="192" type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>192.</hi> For mine eyes are upon all. <hi>ch. 16. v. 17.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>Go ſeek, blind wretches, ſome blind hole, wherein</l>
                  <l>You think you may with ſafety act your ſinne:</l>
                  <l>Grope 'midſt Cymmerian darkneſſe, and commit</l>
                  <l>Such crimes, as adde another night to it.</l>
                  <l>Light, if you can, on ſuch a dusky place,</l>
                  <l>Where light ne're came, where Sol ne're ſhew'd his face.</l>
                  <l>Wear hills upon your backs; bid mountains fall</l>
                  <l>On you, yet God from his high mount ſees all:</l>
                  <l>O then repent in time, who e're thou art,</l>
                  <l>Leſt that thou feel, God ſees, unto thy ſmart.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="193" type="epigram">
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:103970:37"/>
                  <head>193. <hi>So they drew up</hi> JEREMIAH. ch. 38. v. 13.</head>
                  <l>Telling what hap unto his king ſhould be,</l>
                  <l>Himſelf firſt taſtes of his own prophecy;</l>
                  <l>He's caſt into a dungeon, and therein</l>
                  <l>As much bemir'd with filth, as Jews with ſinne;</l>
                  <l>But this <hi>black</hi> Eunuchs help's more <hi>candid</hi> farre,</l>
                  <l>To him, then thoſe of his own countrey are:</l>
                  <l>Where for not letting his life be (as they</l>
                  <l>Would hav't) he has his own life for a prey.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="194" type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>194.</hi> And it was ſo that when, <hi>&amp;c. ch. 41. v. 7.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>Judah laid waſte, and Gedaliah ſlain,</l>
                  <l>Leſt any of the people ſhould remain:</l>
                  <l>Iſmael contrives, and doth his worſt and beſt,</l>
                  <l>In a dire pit-fall to entrap the reſt:</l>
                  <l>His plot's effected: O the <hi>rufull</hi> ſight!</l>
                  <l>He proves himſelf here a true I ſhmaelite.</l>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="book">
               <head>LAMENTATIONS.</head>
               <div n="195" type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>195.</hi> See, O Lord, and conſider, for I am become vile. <hi>ch. 1. v. 11.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>SEE Lord how vile we are, our ſinnes do lie</l>
                  <l>Before our God's, before the nations eye:</l>
                  <l>For our <hi>deſert</hi> the land lies <hi>deſart;</hi> beaſts</l>
                  <l>Here couch: birds from our ruines build their neſts.</l>
                  <l>Vile as we are, 'twould be ſome comfort though,</l>
                  <l>Could we (blind we) but our own vileneſſe know.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="196" type="epigram">
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:103970:38"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>196.</hi> All thine enemies have, <hi>&amp;c. ch. 2. v. 16.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>Behold thine enemies, on every ſide,</l>
                  <l>With bloudy jaws, like ſerpents, yawning wide:</l>
                  <l>Yet ere they ſwallow down their morſell, hiſſe</l>
                  <l>To ſee how contemptible prey it is:</l>
                  <l>No ſnake ere harm'd with his three-forked tongue,</l>
                  <l>Like thoſe biſulced, which do doubly wrong;</l>
                  <l>They ſhew their teeth; grin, ſnarl, and gnaſh, ſuppoſing</l>
                  <l>They ſhall not ſnap ſhort, and catch naught ith' clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing:</l>
                  <l>But God, who their outrageous madneſſe ſeeth,</l>
                  <l>Provides a place, where they ſhall gnaſh their teeth.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="197" type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>197.</hi> Thou haſt covered thy ſelf, <hi>&amp;c. ch. 3. v. 44.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>What cloud's ſo thick, or what condenſed air</l>
                  <l>'S not broke with the Artillery of pray'r.</l>
                  <l>Pray'r hath omnipotence, 'twill rend aſunder</l>
                  <l>Thoſe lets, and parl with Heav'n in Heav'ns thunder.</l>
                  <l>Then let him muffle up his face; no doubt</l>
                  <l>Well break thoſe clouds untill his face break out:</l>
                  <l>Not breaking off our ſuit, nor till then part,</l>
                  <l>While we through clouds force paſſage to his heart.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="198" type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>198.</hi> They ſhall be ſlain with the ſword. <hi>ch. 4. v. 9.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>To die by ſword, or famine, I confeſſe</l>
                  <l>The choice is ſomewhat hard; yet, ne'retheleſſe,</l>
                  <l>Give me a ſouldiers death; for who would lie</l>
                  <l>Protracting with his life his miſerie:</l>
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:103970:38"/>
                  <l> Yet I'd chuſe hunger, were't my maker's will</l>
                  <l>I after righteouſneſſe might hunger ſtill.</l>
                  <l>Grant me that thirſt which brings not death, but life,</l>
                  <l>Or with the Goſpells ſword decide this ſtrife.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="199" type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>199.</hi> The Crown is fallen from our head, <hi>&amp;c. ch. 5. v. 16.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>Our gracefull crown from off our head is thruſt,</l>
                  <l>And gone to lay its ſplendour in the duſt.</l>
                  <l>That crown is faln, and wo to us: more wo,</l>
                  <l>Our crown of grace is fallen from us too.</l>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="book">
               <head>EZEKIEL.</head>
               <div n="200" type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>200.</hi> Take this stony heart out, <hi>&amp;c. ch. 11. v. 19.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>MY ſtony heart O take away;</l>
                  <l>Give me heart of fleſh I pray;</l>
                  <l>But when thou this haſt giv'n, this ſuit I'd move,</l>
                  <l>My heart of fleſh, a fleſhly heart ne're prove.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="201" type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>201.</hi> Therefore ye ſhall no more ſeek vanity, <hi>&amp;c. ch. 13. v. 23.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>No, no, 'ts not fit Gods ſervants ſhould rely</l>
                  <l>On each vain preſage, and forg'd prophecy;</l>
                  <l>Should they Sibylls dark leaves conſult? no: rather,</l>
                  <l>Leave Satan, ſire of lies: fly to the Father</l>
                  <l>Of everlaſting truth; ſo not incline</l>
                  <l>To <hi>divinations,</hi> but what's more <hi>divine.</hi>
                  </l>
               </div>
               <div n="202" type="epigram">
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:103970:39"/>
                  <head>202. AHAHOLAH <hi>and</hi> AHOLIBAH. ch. 23. v. 1.</head>
                  <l>Two wretched Siſters, who in wedlock-ſtate</l>
                  <l>Participated, and in wofull fate.</l>
                  <l>The one on captains altogether plac'd</l>
                  <l>Her love, and ſhe came poorly off at laſt.</l>
                  <l>The other on Chaldeans dotes, and ſhall</l>
                  <l>By means of thoſe her greateſt lovers, fall:</l>
                  <l>She who took others captive with her love,</l>
                  <l>Her ſelf a worſe way now muſt captive prove.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="203" type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>203.</hi> The dry bones revived, <hi>&amp;c. ch. 37. v. 2,</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>See here dry bones cements Gods word alone,</l>
                  <l>The skin with the now long eſtranged bone:</l>
                  <l>Life is infus'd, and they who lately lay</l>
                  <l>Diſperſed skeletons, ſet in array,</l>
                  <l>Now make a numerous army: Iſra'ls ſtate</l>
                  <l>God by his viſion here doth intimate:</l>
                  <l>Their ruines he together joyns, nay more</l>
                  <l>Joyns them to him, which ne're ſo near before.</l>
                  <l>Gods <hi>arm</hi> this <hi>army</hi> form'd, his name be prais'd,</l>
                  <l>Which hath ſuch companies ſo ſtrangely <hi>rais'd.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Raiſe</hi> we his glory then, and pray he grant</l>
                  <l>We prove, like thoſe troops, his Church militant.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="204" type="epigram">
                  <head>204. GOOS <hi>buriall.</hi> ch. 39. v. 15.16. &amp;c.</head>
                  <l>Gog, ſlain, lies yet unburied: bloudy feaſt,</l>
                  <l>To which each vultur's an invited gheſt:</l>
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:103970:39"/>
                  <l> Suck in the clotted gore of theſe accurſt,</l>
                  <l>Who would have quench'd their own unſatiate thirſt</l>
                  <l>In ſuch another flood: they laid a ginne,</l>
                  <l>And thought to catch the harmleſſe dove therein,</l>
                  <l>But were eſcap'd; revenge us though, that they</l>
                  <l>That would have birds, may be to fowls a prey.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="205" type="epigram">
                  <head>205. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> cap. ult. v. ult.</head>
                  <l>Thrice happy city, which includ'ſt what e're</l>
                  <l>Heav'n makes its boaſt of, that the Lord is there.</l>
                  <l>How can thy greatneſſe well be meaſur'd, ſince</l>
                  <l>Thy bleſſings are unmeaſur'd, as thy prince:</l>
                  <l>Were I a Citizen of thee, I'd near</l>
                  <l>Th' aſſaults of the infernall legions fear;</l>
                  <l>Yet then too, had I but my choice, 't ſhould be,</l>
                  <l>Not to live there, ſo God might live in me.</l>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="book">
               <head>DANIEL.</head>
               <div n="206" type="epigram">
                  <head>206. SHADRACH, MESHACH, <hi>and</hi> ABEDNEGO. ch. 3.</head>
                  <l>IT pleas'd our God his mighty power to ſhew</l>
                  <l>By Shadrah, Meſhach, and Abednego.</l>
                  <l>Theſe three juſt perſons ſtoutly did deſie</l>
                  <l>The Kings commands, though death 'twas to deny;</l>
                  <l>So hot their ſite of zeal was, that thoſe three</l>
                  <l>To th' golden image would not bow the knee.</l>
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:103970:40"/>
                  <l> Wherefore it was the heathen Kings <hi>deſire,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>They ſhould be caſt ith' ſcortching flames of fire:</l>
                  <l>Which forth with then was done; yet to forbear</l>
                  <l>The fire was forc't, and durſt not ſindge a hair.</l>
                  <l>'Twas ſtrange, yet not ſo ſtrange; for, without doubt,</l>
                  <l>Their fire within o'recame the fire without.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="207" type="epigram">
                  <head>207. <hi>Aliud.</hi> ch. 3.</head>
                  <l>The fiery fornace, ſeven fold hotter now,</l>
                  <l>Then ever's made for thoſe who would not bow</l>
                  <l>Unto the golden Idoll; but in vain:</l>
                  <l>Untouched they, in midſt oth' flames, remain!</l>
                  <l>I wonder not that they were hurt no more,</l>
                  <l>Since they were throughly purifi'd before.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="208" type="epigram">
                  <head>208. NEBUCHADNEZAR <hi>metamorphoſed.</hi> ch. 4.</head>
                  <l>By pride, I fear, O great Chaldean King,</l>
                  <l>A ſev'n years penance on thy ſelf thou'lt bring;</l>
                  <l>And come, at laſt, to eat graſſe with the beaſts,</l>
                  <l>Who us'dſt each day to frolick it in feaſts:</l>
                  <l>Thou now a higher then thy ſelf wilt ſee,</l>
                  <l>Since thou'rt deprived of all dignitie.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="209" type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>209. DANIEL</hi> caſt into the lions den. <hi>ch. 6. v. 16.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>You ſalvage Monſters, crueller by farre</l>
                  <l>Then lions, although beaſts of prey they are:</l>
                  <pb n="69" facs="tcp:103970:40"/>
                  <l> Is thus his piety rewarded then,</l>
                  <l>Straight to be thruſt into the lions den:</l>
                  <l>They ſay thoſe creatures never harm kings ſeed,</l>
                  <l>But fawn on them, 'tis true in him indeed:</l>
                  <l>Then courage, Daniel, and pluck up thy heart,</l>
                  <l>Thou the adopted ſonne of heavens King art.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="210" type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>210.</hi> His accuſers devoured, <hi>&amp;c. ch. 6. v. 24.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>The beaſts their ſtomach now could find at laſt,</l>
                  <l>When, who caſt him into their den were caſt;</l>
                  <l>Whoſe bodies mangled by thoſe lions pow'r,</l>
                  <l>A farre <hi>worſelion</hi> did their ſouls devour.</l>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="book">
               <head>HOSEA.</head>
               <div n="211" type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>211.</hi> Come, and let us return unto the Lord. <hi>ch. 6. v. 1.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>COme, jointly, let's return unto the Lord,</l>
                  <l>Who made the ſore can onely balme afford;</l>
                  <l>And th' onely balm; our hurt by him thus bound</l>
                  <l>Will be more firm, then e're it was a wound.</l>
                  <l>He ſmites, but ſhews his love, in ſmiting, beſt;</l>
                  <l>Let us too ſmite our ſelves upon the breſt.</l>
                  <l>Like fawning ſpaniels, let us love the more</l>
                  <l>The Maſter, from whoſe hands the ſtroke we bore:</l>
                  <l>Whilſt thus we undergo theſe ſufferings,</l>
                  <l>Each blow is ſtruck will cure the ſmart it brings.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="212" type="epigram">
                  <pb n="70" facs="tcp:103970:41"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>212.</hi> Rejoyce not, O Iſrael, for joy as other people. <hi>ch. 9. v. 1.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>But little reaſon for true joyes have we,</l>
                  <l>'Midſt worldly joyes, whilſt wallowing we be:</l>
                  <l>Alas! a whoring from our God we're led,</l>
                  <l>And joy in wrongs we do our nuptiall bed.</l>
                  <l>Rejoyce not we like other people, no,</l>
                  <l>But drown falſe pleaſures in th' abyſſe of wo.</l>
                  <l>This done, and God once more propitious,</l>
                  <l>No other people ere <hi>ſhould joy like</hi> us.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="213" type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>213.</hi> When Iſrael was a child, then I loved him <hi>&amp;c. ch. 11. v. 1.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>Oraculous ſence! an Evangelick dream</l>
                  <l>Infolded in abſtruſe prophetick ſcheme.</l>
                  <l>Epitome of what was paſt, yet doom</l>
                  <l>Of what in future ages was to come:</l>
                  <l>A ſure foretoken Iſr'el was belov'd;</l>
                  <l>When for their ſake from Egypt God was mov'd</l>
                  <l>To call his ſonne: and he calls us, could we</l>
                  <l>Call on his ſacred name unceſſantly:</l>
                  <l>Since he's from Egypt call'd, there's little doubt</l>
                  <l>Our ſouls from thence ſhall be deliver'd out.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="214" type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>214.</hi> Who is wiſe, he ſhall underſtand theſe things. <hi>ch. 14. v. the laſt.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>To underſtand Gods wayes aright would we,</l>
                  <l>We muſt our ſelves be right, as thoſe wayes be:</l>
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:103970:41"/>
                  <l> All earthly knowledge too, we ſhould decline</l>
                  <l>To gain experience in Gods laws divine</l>
                  <l>This prophet ſure the way of wiſedome took,</l>
                  <l>In it, he ends his life, with it, his book.</l>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="book">
               <head>JOEL.</head>
               <div n="215" type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>215.</hi> Awake ye drunkards, <hi>&amp;c, ch. 1. v. 5.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>ROuze you from out your death like Lethargy,</l>
                  <l>Drunkards, that on your couches ſnorting lie.</l>
                  <l>'Ts not to carouſe, (miſtake me not) no ſack,</l>
                  <l>But rather <hi>ſackcloth</hi> 'tis, my friends, you lack.</l>
                  <l>The bluſhing liquour late you drunk, I fear,</l>
                  <l>Muſt now grow paler, and turn to a tear.</l>
                  <l>What makes you look ſo <hi>friday-fac'd</hi> to day,</l>
                  <l>O're preſt with wo! <hi>our preſt</hi> wine tane away.</l>
                  <l>'Ts cut from your mouth, and with your ſwill to part,</l>
                  <l>No mar'l it cuts you to the very heart.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="216" type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>216.</hi> Beat your plough-ſhares into ſwords, and your pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning-hooks into ſpears. <hi>ch. 3. v. 10.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>Beat up the drummes, and ſound alarm, all-arm;</l>
                  <l>Let numerous companies together ſwarm:</l>
                  <l>Beat, beat, your plough-ſhares into ſwords, learn now</l>
                  <l>To handle weapons, who erſt held a plough:</l>
                  <l>Turn pruning-hooks to ſpears, and what ere are</l>
                  <l>The inſtruments of peace, let be of warre.</l>
                  <pb n="72" facs="tcp:103970:42"/>
                  <l> Ploughs, thus employ'd, 'twill be to us I fear,</l>
                  <l>An hard, to death a too too plenteous, year.</l>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="book">
               <head>AMOS.</head>
               <div n="217" type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>217.</hi> Ye who turn judgement to wormwoood, and leave off righteouſneſse in the earth. <hi>ch. 5. v. 7.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>IS righteouſneſſe quite out of faſhion then!</l>
                  <l>And will you never put it on agen?</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Were</hi> you but wiſe, you'd <hi>wear</hi> it; leſt you be</l>
                  <l>Your ſelves <hi>worn out</hi> with <hi>war</hi> and miſery;</l>
                  <l>And you, who <hi>juſtice</hi> call a wormwood-cup,</l>
                  <l>Shall <hi>juſtly</hi> drink a farre more bitter up.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="218" type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>218.</hi> Behold the dayes come, ſaith the Lord God, that I will ſend a famine in the land; not a famine of bread, nor a thirſt for water, <hi>&amp;c. ch. 8. v. 11.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>A famine, yet no want of bread! can be</l>
                  <l>Abundance, plenty, and yet ſcarcitie:</l>
                  <l>Are contrarieties then joyn'd! can now</l>
                  <l>A man be hungry, and yet filled too:</l>
                  <l>Yet ſo it is: although the bodi's fed,</l>
                  <l>The ſoul may want its food of heav'nly bread.</l>
                  <l>Much better 'twere, the firſt were pin'd away,</l>
                  <l>Then the laſt have not its ambroſia:</l>
                  <l>Yet could we truly hunger for Gods word,</l>
                  <l>Heav'ns Granaries abundance would afford.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="219" type="epigram">
                  <pb n="73" facs="tcp:103970:42"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>219.</hi> Though they dig into hell, thence ſhall mine hand take them. <hi>ch. 9. v. 2.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>You'll then dig deep enough; I cannot tell</l>
                  <l>A pit you have more title to, then hell:</l>
                  <l>Or will you climbe 'bove the mid region,</l>
                  <l>Where thunder to reward you there is none?</l>
                  <l>Yet there you can't ſtay long, your ſinnes deny</l>
                  <l>A receptacle for you in the sky.</l>
                  <l>That God ſhould take you up from hell, (prophane)</l>
                  <l>'Tis with more force to hurl you down again.</l>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="book">
               <head>OBADIAH.</head>
               <div n="220" type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>220.</hi> Behold, I have made thee ſmall among the heathen: thou art greatly deſpiſed. <hi>v. 2.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>DEſpis'd, contemn'd, of all the heathen folk;</l>
                  <l>Their publick laughing-ſtock, their open talk.</l>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="book">
               <head>JONAH.</head>
               <div n="221" type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>221. JONAH</hi> ſwallowed by a fiſh. <hi>ch. 1.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>He's ſwallow'd by the whale, who doth become</l>
                  <l>To him drown'd, yet alive, a living tombe:</l>
                  <l>Himſelf, ingulſ'd in double ſea, he knows,</l>
                  <l>Being now, truly, in the depth of woes:</l>
                  <pb n="74" facs="tcp:103970:43"/>
                  <l> But yet the fiſh <hi>quickly</hi> diſgorg'd him <hi>quick;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And for his welfare was her ſelf ſea-ſick:</l>
                  <l>Though 'twas a miracle, yet all things ſcan'd,</l>
                  <l>This was the ſooneſt way t' have come to land.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="222" type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>222.</hi> And the Lord prepared a gourd, and made it to come over Jonah, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But God prepared a worm, <hi>&amp;c. ch. 4. v. 6.7.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>How ſoon grown up, and yet how ſoon 'tis gone,</l>
                  <l>Ere thought upon:</l>
                  <l>Of which, longer to write, I could afford;</l>
                  <l>But I'll cut ſhort, and imitate the gourd.</l>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="book">
               <head>MICAH.</head>
               <div n="223" type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>223.</hi> Wo to them that deviſe iniquity, and work evil up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their beds: when the morning is light they practiſe it. <hi>ch. 2. v. 1.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>HEar</hi> God in juſtice, <hi>here</hi> pronounce a wo,</l>
                  <l>On thoſe which they would fain bring others to.</l>
                  <l>Who hatch that miſchief on their beds, which they</l>
                  <l>Intend to perpetrate th' enſuing day:</l>
                  <l>Whilſt thus they ſhew their pow'r they'l underſtand</l>
                  <l>At laſt themſelves the pow'rs of Gods right hand.</l>
                  <l>They merit it, whoſe onely <hi>care</hi>'s to make</l>
                  <l>Others the more and greater <hi>care</hi> to take.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="224" type="epigram">
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:103970:43"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>224.</hi> But thou Bethlehem-Ephratah, though thou be little amongſt the thouſands of <hi>JU<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DAH, &amp;c. ch. 6. v. 2.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>Thrice happy Bethlehem, though thou little art,</l>
                  <l>Of Judahs thouſands ſcarce the thouſandth part,</l>
                  <l>Yet out of <hi>little</hi> thee, by Gods fore-doome,</l>
                  <l>An <hi>immenſe</hi> Saviour was foretold to come.</l>
                  <l>This Micah could diſcern far off; his eye,</l>
                  <l>Clear'd by bright rayes, made it appear more nigh:</l>
                  <l>And yet his purblind countrey-men ſcarce ſaw</l>
                  <l>The light ariſing out of Ephratah.</l>
                  <l>When we, far diſtant Iſles, deſcry it; ſure</l>
                  <l>The too near ſplendour did their ſight obſcure.</l>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="book">
               <head>NAHUM.</head>
               <div n="225" type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>225.</hi> The mountains quake at him, and the hills. <hi>ch. 1. v. 6.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>SEE how the mountains quake, as if they meant</l>
                  <l>To th' centre through themſelves a way to rent.</l>
                  <l>The hils' gin melt, earth burns with a deſire</l>
                  <l>She might be turn'd to elementall fire:</l>
                  <l>God's preſent; that's the cauſe: yet all this light</l>
                  <l>Is dim'd by his refulgence farre more bright.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="226" type="epigram">
                  <pb n="76" facs="tcp:103970:44"/>
                  <head>226. <hi>The ruine of</hi> NINEVEH. ch. 3.</head>
                  <l>Great Nineveh is faln: the burden, late</l>
                  <l>Good Nahum bore, is turn'd upon their ſtate.</l>
                  <l>Sad ſtate of things: what had ſo populous been,</l>
                  <l>O'rethrown, is now depopulated <hi>clean!</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Yet were it <hi>clean;</hi> fire never had com there,</l>
                  <l>If matter none, combuſtible, there were.</l>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="book">
               <head>HABAKKUK.</head>
               <div n="227" type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>227.</hi> And the Lord anſwered and ſaid, Write, <hi>&amp;c. c. 2. v. 2.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>VVHen mute things ſhall to cry begin,</l>
                  <l>O think how crying is thy ſinne!</l>
               </div>
               <div n="228" type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>228.</hi> What profiteth the graven image, <hi>&amp;c. ch. 2. v. 18.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>From him that form'd you, you expect no good;</l>
                  <l>Yet do, from what your ſelves have formed, wood.</l>
                  <l>Were you not wood, and ſtonyhearted too,</l>
                  <l>You'd give God his, not them what's not their due.</l>
                  <l>Whilſt you frame images by hel-bred arts;</l>
                  <l>You quite deface Gods image in your hearts.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="229" type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>229.</hi> Was the Lord diſpleaſed againſt the rivers? was thine anger againſt the rivers? was thy wrath against the ſea? <hi>&amp;c. ch. 3. v. 8.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>Though figtrees bloſſome not, or bloſſoming,</l>
                  <l>Let fall their ſcarce-form'd buds, blaſted ith' ſpring:</l>
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:103970:44"/>
                  <l> Though olives bear no fatneſſe, and the vine,</l>
                  <l>Empty of cluſters, bring no ſtore of wine;</l>
                  <l>Yet whilſt we have Gods favour, oil of gladneſſe,</l>
                  <l>We ne're ſhall want of wine to baniſh ſadneſſe.</l>
                  <l>Though all elſe barren are, we'll fruitfull be,</l>
                  <l>And conſecrate our firſt-fruits, Lord, to thee.</l>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="book">
               <head>ZEPHANIAH.</head>
               <div n="230" type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>230.</hi> And it ſhall come to paſſe, at that time, that I will ſearch eruſalem with a candle, <hi>&amp;c. ch. 1. v. 12.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>O Time of diſmall darkneſſe! horrid night,</l>
                  <l>When heav'n it ſelf is forc'd to uſe a light.</l>
                  <l>Iſr'el purſues th' Egyptians ſinnes, I fear,</l>
                  <l>For they have got their quondam darkneſſe here:</l>
                  <l>God lights a candle, 'cauſe you Jews ('tis plain)</l>
                  <l>Have put out yours, and muſt, I fear, remain</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n night eternall: as your candle you</l>
                  <l>Put out, from heav'n you put your ſelves out too.</l>
                  <l>Y' extinguiſh grace, and natures light, to dwell</l>
                  <l>Midſt th' unextinguiſhable flames of hell.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="231" type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>231.</hi> This is the rejoycing citie, that dwelt careleſly, <hi>&amp;c. ch. 2. v. 15.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>Ingodly joyes, mirth, pleaſure, pride; to what</l>
                  <l>A ſad condition brought you Judahs ſtate?</l>
                  <l>A place for beaſts to lie in, yet not more,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r viler beaſts, then there were in't before.</l>
                  <pb n="78" facs="tcp:103970:45"/>
                  <l> What's Gods they wreſt to their deſtruction,</l>
                  <l>Who is indeed, and there's beſide him none:</l>
                  <l>Yet now, with little change, 'tis made their own,</l>
                  <l>They'r (miſerable) and beſide them none.</l>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="book">
               <head>HAGGAI.</head>
               <div n="232" type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>232.</hi> Ye have ſown much, but ye bring in little: ye eat, but ye have not enough. <hi>ch. 1. v. 6.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>YOu clothe you, but no warmth you get;</l>
                  <l>No fire of zeal inflames you yet:</l>
                  <l>From hence, alas, the reaſon came,</l>
                  <l>You cloth'd you not with wooll oth' Lamb.</l>
                  <l>Unholy folk, your gains bring curſes,</l>
                  <l>You put your coin in holely purſes</l>
                  <l>Without a bottome, for therein</l>
                  <l>You lay the wages up of ſinne;</l>
                  <l>Which yet, I fear, you will not loſe,</l>
                  <l>But keep them to your lives laſt cloſe,</l>
                  <l>Untill they weigh you down that precipice</l>
                  <l>Where, like, your purſes, there no bottome is.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="233" type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>233.</hi> In that day, ſaith the Lord of hoſts, I will take the ſonnes of Zerubbabel, and will make them a ſignet, <hi>&amp;c. ch. 2. ver. laſt.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>What greater ſigne of favour can be had,</l>
                  <l>Then thus to be a ſignet made?</l>
                  <l>A ſignet which was us'd, in times of yore,</l>
                  <l>On great mens right hands to be wore.</l>
                  <pb n="79" facs="tcp:103970:45"/>
                  <l> This grace didſt thou, Shealtiel's ſonne, obtain;</l>
                  <l>And now doſt at Gods right hand reign:</l>
                  <l>O grant, good God, though I a ſignet ne're</l>
                  <l>Shall prove, I may thy impreſſe bear.</l>
                  <l>Vouchſafe I may, in theſe my infant dayes,</l>
                  <l>Be made a cignet to reſound thy praiſe.</l>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="book">
               <head>ZECHARIAH.</head>
               <div n="234" type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>234.</hi> Yea they made their hearts as an adamant ſtone, leſt they ſhould hear the law, <hi>&amp;c. ch. 7. v. 12.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>HArd hearts, and yet I fear if all were known,</l>
                  <l>Not ſo precious as that ſtone.</l>
                  <l>If hard as adamant, methinks 'twere fit</l>
                  <l>Gods laws were in ſuch tables writ:</l>
                  <l>But ſince they will not have it ſo, their ſinne</l>
                  <l>Is wrote with laſting characters therein.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="235" type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>235.</hi> Rejoyce greatly daughter of Sion, ſhout daughter of Jeruſalem. <hi>ch. 9. v. 9.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>As if with aged eyes he could behold,</l>
                  <l>What he fore told.</l>
                  <l>As if he ſaw what heav'n is proud of; ride</l>
                  <l>Without all pride.</l>
                  <l>As if he heard the peoples clamours ringing,</l>
                  <l>Hoſannah ſinging.</l>
                  <l>He long before, might, I have a dim caſt</l>
                  <l>Of what is paſt:</l>
                  <l>But ſince I cannot, Heav'n reſerve a room,</l>
                  <l>That I, with joy, may ſee the pomp to come.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="236" type="epigram">
                  <pb n="80" facs="tcp:103970:46"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>236.</hi> And in that day ſhall there be upon the bells of the horſes, <hi>HOLINESSE UNTO THE LORD. ch. 14. v. 20.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>Aſſes bore holineſſe of late; and now</l>
                  <l>Muſt horſes too?</l>
                  <l>What Aarons bels and plate did whilome bear,</l>
                  <l>Theſe beaſts muſt wear.</l>
                  <l>Their bridles have't ingrav'd, though their mute tongue</l>
                  <l>Doth want a ſong.</l>
                  <l>Gods ſervants in their hearts keep holineſſe,</l>
                  <l>Theſe on their breaſts:</l>
                  <l>We in the Scriptures, and theſe ſteeds have it</l>
                  <l>In holy writ.</l>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="book">
               <head>MALACHI.</head>
               <div n="237" type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>237.</hi> A ſonne honoureth his Father, and a ſervant his Maſter: if then I be a Father, where is my honour? if a Maſter, where is my fear? <hi>ch. 1. v. 6.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>A Maſter fear hath due to him, a Syre</l>
                  <l>Doth honour from his progeny require.</l>
                  <l>If God our heavenly Father be, O where</l>
                  <l>'S his Honour? if a Maſter, where's his fear?</l>
                  <l>If ſenſe of duty nought in us will do,</l>
                  <l>Honour for fear, fear not to honour though.</l>
               </div>
               <trailer>The end of the Old Teſtament.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="testament">
            <pb n="81" facs="tcp:103970:46"/>
            <div type="book">
               <head>The Goſpel of our Saviour JESUS CHRIST According to <hi>S. MATTHEW.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="epigram">
                  <head>The bleſſed Virgin.</head>
                  <l>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Virgin bleſt 'bove all in Iſrael,</l>
                  <l>In that th' art mother of Emanuel.</l>
                  <l>But O more bleſt in that thou undefil'd</l>
                  <l>With ſin, art made the daughter of thy child.</l>
               </div>
               <div type="epigram">
                  <head>The nativity of our Saviour <hi>JESUS CHRIST. ch. 2.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>Emanuel is born, O where ſhall we,</l>
                  <l>Bleſt babe, find out thy place, and worſhip thee?</l>
                  <l>Where li'ſt thou? at an Inne? left I ſhould rove</l>
                  <l>Tell me the ſigne, is't not the ſigne of love?</l>
                  <l>Let me at thy celeſtiall manger feed,</l>
                  <l>And eat thy body which is bread indeed:</l>
                  <l>The heav'ns have ſent their ſtarry Meſſenger,</l>
                  <l>To bid my ſoul take up her lodging here.</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>nes, which to publick ſinnes were once abus'd,</l>
                  <l>Are now by us to publick worſhip us'd.</l>
                  <l>Temples farewell; heav'n prompts me 'tis no ſinne,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> ſuch a caſe to make my Church an Inne.</l>
               </div>
               <div type="epigram">
                  <pb n="82" facs="tcp:103970:47"/>
                  <head>The miracle of the loaves. <hi>ch. 15.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>Thou fed'ſt their bodies, Lord, and then</l>
                  <l>Thou brak'ſt the bread of life agen;</l>
                  <l>Who can this wondrous banquet tell,</l>
                  <l>But as a double miracle?</l>
                  <l>Where to be ſure they might be fed,</l>
                  <l>Thou mad'ſt thy body, Lord, the bread.</l>
               </div>
               <div type="epigram">
                  <head>The blind receiving ſight. <hi>ch. 20.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>He gave ſight, and repentance, to the blind,</l>
                  <l>At once enlightning both their eyes and mind.</l>
               </div>
               <div type="epigram">
                  <head>JUDAS <hi>ſelling his</hi> LORD. ch. 26. v. 15.</head>
                  <l>Judas, whilſt thou thy maſter thus doſt ſell,</l>
                  <l>Traitour, thou mak'ſt thy ſelf a price for hell.</l>
               </div>
               <div type="epigram">
                  <head>JUDAS <hi>his kiſſe.</hi> ch. 26. v. 49.</head>
                  <l>Thy falſhood, Judas, thou wouldſt hide in this</l>
                  <l>By candying thy poiſon in a kiſſe:</l>
                  <l>That kiſſe thou everlaſtingly ſhalt wail;</l>
                  <l>Thy heart meant <hi>hale,</hi> 'twas but thy lips ſaid <hi>Hail.</hi>
                  </l>
               </div>
               <div type="epigram">
                  <head>Peter denying Chriſt. <hi>ch. 26. v. 74.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>Why, Peter, doſt thou thus deny</l>
                  <l>Thy Lord ſo oft, ſo bitterly?</l>
                  <l>How doſt thou think, that he will own</l>
                  <l>Thee, when thou plead'ſt before his throne?</l>
                  <l>O let the cock, whoſe voice ſounds thy offence,</l>
                  <l>Lend the a ſpur to tears and penitence.</l>
               </div>
               <div type="epigram">
                  <pb n="83" facs="tcp:103970:47"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>PILATH</hi> judgeing our Saviour. <hi>ch. 27.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>Whom doſt thou judge, fond man? what pow'r is given</l>
                  <l>To thee, O wretch, to judge the judge of heaven?</l>
                  <l>When he ſhall come with troops of Angels hem'd,</l>
                  <l>For that condemning thou ſhalt be condemn'd;</l>
                  <l>Onely this different ſentence he ſhall give,</l>
                  <l>Thou him condemn'ſt to die, he thee to live.</l>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="book">
               <head>The Goſpel of our Lord and Saviour <hi>JESUS CHRIST</hi> according to <hi>S. MARK.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="epigram">
                  <head>I will make you fiſhers of men. <hi>ch. 1.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>TWill be an happy occupation, then,</l>
                  <l>To fiſh for the immortall ſouls of men.</l>
                  <l>Their hook's the word, by w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> our ſouls are ſaught,</l>
                  <l>And wo betide that fiſh which is not caught.</l>
               </div>
               <div type="epigram">
                  <head>And all the devils beſought him, ſaying, if thou caſt us out, <hi>&amp;c. ch. 5. v. 12.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>Inveterate malice, though they cannot do</l>
                  <l>Miſchief to man, they'll work the creatures wo.</l>
                  <l>A legion of ſpight t' whom ere they come,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> marvell not they drive him to his tombe;</l>
                  <l>But from this one expuls'd, I fear, they mean</l>
                  <l>To quench their hate (though that can't make them clean)</l>
                  <l>In a whole ſea, one eas'ly might divine</l>
                  <l>That filthy company they choſe, were ſwine</l>
                  <l>Or ſwiniſh men, when once they'd drove them in</l>
                  <l>To th' mire, I fear, they'll ne're return agin.</l>
               </div>
               <div type="epigram">
                  <pb n="84" facs="tcp:103970:48"/>
                  <head>The daughter of Herodias. <hi>ch. 6.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>Damſell thy feet a fatall meaſure tread,</l>
                  <l>That thus do ſpurn againſt the Baptiſts head;</l>
                  <l>Which in a <hi>charger</hi> plac'd, thou mak'ſt thy play,</l>
                  <l>With that be ſure he'll charge thee at laſt day.</l>
               </div>
               <div type="epigram">
                  <head>And he looked up and ſaid, I ſee men as trees walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>&amp;c. ch. 8. v. 24.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>The man, late blind, gins re-ſalute the light,</l>
                  <l>And now is a probationer for ſight;</l>
                  <l>And yet how perfectly at firſt he ſees,</l>
                  <l>That ſaw the ſenſeleſſe Jews to walk like trees!</l>
               </div>
               <div type="epigram">
                  <head>The penitent chief. <hi>ch. 23. v. 40.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>He ſtole, and with his life did pay the price,</l>
                  <l>Yet dying ſtole both life and paradiſe.</l>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="book">
               <head>The Goſpel of our Lord, and Saviour <hi>JESUS CHRIST</hi> according to <hi>S. LUKE.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="epigram">
                  <head>When Jeſus heard theſe things he marvelled at him, and turned about and ſaid, <hi>&amp;c. ch. 7. v. 9.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>NOt ſo great faith was found in Iſrael,</l>
                  <l>None found ſo faithfull as an Infidell.</l>
                  <l>He that believ'd Chriſt could his ſervant cure,</l>
                  <l>Might have believ'd and ſo himſelf aſſure,</l>
                  <pb n="85" facs="tcp:103970:48"/>
                  <l> That whilſt pray'rs for his ſervant he did make,</l>
                  <l>Chriſt would himſelf into his ſervice take.</l>
               </div>
               <div type="epigram">
                  <head>If a ſonne ſhall ask bread of any of you that is a father, will he give him a stone? <hi>ch. 11. v. 11.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>Ask'ſt thou for bread? a ſtone God will not give,</l>
                  <l>But bread of life, whereby thy ſoul ſhall live;</l>
                  <l>Or if heav'n gives a ſtone'ts a precious one,</l>
                  <l>'Tis Chriſt the rock of hope, the corner ſtone.</l>
               </div>
               <div type="epigram">
                  <head>Ye hypocrites, ye can diſcern the face of the sky and of the earth, but how is it, that ye diſcern not this time? <hi>ch. 12. v. 56.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>What fooliſh ſtar gazer is there but knows</l>
                  <l>We ſhall have heat when ſulph'rous Auſter blows?</l>
                  <l>When muddy Zephyre calls up from the ſea</l>
                  <l>A ſpungy cloud, we trow there rain will be.</l>
                  <l>Heav'ns face 'tis eaſie to diſcern, but pry</l>
                  <l>Not into Heav'ns inviſibility.</l>
               </div>
               <div type="epigram">
                  <head>ZACCHAEUS. ch. 19.</head>
                  <l>What need Zaccheus climb upon a tree,</l>
                  <l>Who with faiths eyes his Saviour could ſee!</l>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="book">
               <head>The Goſpel of our Lord and Saviour <hi>JESUS CHRIST</hi> according to <hi>S. JOHN.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="epigram">
                  <head>And when the ruler of the feaſt had taſted, <hi>&amp;c. ch. 2. v. 9.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>CHriſt was invited to a nuptiall feaſt,</l>
                  <l>Not ſo much made by th' diſhes as the gheſt;</l>
                  <pb n="86" facs="tcp:103970:49"/>
                  <l> But lo, in midſt of all this jollity,</l>
                  <l>The wine'gins fail; which, or he muſt ſupply,</l>
                  <l>Or they muſt want: he ſtraight doth give command;</l>
                  <l>And wine is made of water out of hand:</l>
                  <l>The bridegroom could not chuſe but like ſuch wine,</l>
                  <l>That had a reliſh of that heavenly Vine.</l>
               </div>
               <div type="epigram">
                  <head>Except a man be born again, <hi>&amp;c. ch. 3. v. 3.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>Again muſt I be born? again muſt I</l>
                  <l>Shrunk up within my mothers bowels lie?</l>
                  <l>Again receive my birth? O ſtrange! muſt heav'n,</l>
                  <l>A price to things impoſſible, be given?</l>
                  <l>'Tis true (O Nicodemus) for again</l>
                  <l>Thou muſt be born through faith, pray'r, faſting, pain.</l>
                  <l>Chriſt is thy father muſt beget thee here,</l>
                  <l>The Church that mother is that thee muſt bear.</l>
               </div>
               <div type="epigram">
                  <head>JESUS <hi>wept.</hi> ch. 11. v. 35.</head>
                  <l>Moſes, whilſt with his wand the rock he ſmites,</l>
                  <l>Gives water to the thirſty Iſra'lites;</l>
                  <l>Laz'rus, like him, had travell'd long to find</l>
                  <l>Another promis'd land, which was aſſign'd</l>
                  <l>For bleſſed ſouls above; but here, by th' way,</l>
                  <l>Like his forefathers, drops: being forc'd to lay</l>
                  <l>His weary limbs under a rock, and wait</l>
                  <l>For ſuch a remedy in ſuch a ſtrait;</l>
                  <l>When lo a rock, a mov'ng rock comes near</l>
                  <l>This weary tir'd-out traveller to chear,</l>
                  <l>Out of his eyes a double ſpring doth flow,</l>
                  <l>Not to refreſh his thirſt alone; but lo</l>
                  <pb n="87" facs="tcp:103970:49"/>
                  <l> It brings the dead to life: fear not to die,</l>
                  <l>Laz'rus, ſince thou haſt life's well-ſpring ſo nigh.</l>
               </div>
               <div type="epigram">
                  <head>I am the true vine. <hi>ch. 15. v. 1.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>Art thou the vine, dear Saviour? happy's he</l>
                  <l>Who ſhall a branch in that ſtock grafted be:</l>
                  <l>Thou art a vine, as ſadly ſhews the loſſe</l>
                  <l>Of thy dear bloud at, the wine-preſſe, the croſſe.</l>
               </div>
               <div type="epigram">
                  <head>This is my commandment, that ye love one another, <hi>&amp;c. ch. 15. v. 12.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>On peace, ſince that is the delight of God,</l>
                  <l>Fix to continue ſoul thy ſole abode;</l>
                  <l>That ſo a chain of concord there may be,</l>
                  <l>Betwixt thy conſcience, thy God, and thee.</l>
               </div>
               <div type="epigram">
                  <head>Incredulous Thomas. <hi>ch. 20. v. 27.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>Incredulous, who thy belief doſt tie</l>
                  <l>Unto no other witneſſe then thine eye:</l>
                  <l>But if thou doſt deſire a ſurer band</l>
                  <l>Unto thy faith; here, Thomas, feel mine hand.</l>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="book">
               <head>The Acts of the <hi>APOSTLES.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="epigram">
                  <head>ANANIAS <hi>and</hi> SAPPHIRA. ch. 5. v. 5. and v. 10.</head>
                  <l>VVHy, when you'd ſold all your poſſeſſion,</l>
                  <l>Kept you a part oth' price? give all, or none.</l>
                  <l>When you to Peter came, and gave him that,</l>
                  <l>You parted with your lives at a dear rate.</l>
               </div>
               <div type="epigram">
                  <pb n="88" facs="tcp:103970:50"/>
                  <head>Aliud.</head>
                  <l>At the Apoſtles feet thou laidſt a part,</l>
                  <l>Lay not thy treaſure down, lay ope thy heart.</l>
               </div>
               <div type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Saint</hi> STEPHEN <hi>stoned.</hi> ch. 7. v. 59.</head>
                  <l>Cares he for tortures, or for death think you,</l>
                  <l>Who hath his haven, heaven, in full view?</l>
                  <l>Theſe ſtones, which would have clogg'd another quite,</l>
                  <l>Adde wings (O Stephen) to thy ſpirits flight.</l>
                  <l>In vain you think this martyr'd ſaint to ſtay,</l>
                  <l>His eyes already have prepar'd his way.</l>
               </div>
               <div type="epigram">
                  <head>SIMON MAGUS. ch. 8. v. 18.</head>
                  <l>Simon in bitterneſſe is thy abode,</l>
                  <l>Who thinkſt with coyn to buy the gift of God.</l>
                  <l>Thy money-good, bad Simon, keep to thee,</l>
                  <l>For thou may'ſt purchaſe hell without a fee.</l>
               </div>
               <div type="epigram">
                  <head>The baptized Eunuch. <hi>ch. 8. v. 38.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>O Eunuch, treaſurer to Candace, here</l>
                  <l>A greater treaſure is approching near:</l>
                  <l>Though tis but water, yet that water may</l>
                  <l>Waſh all the blackneſſe of thy mind away.</l>
               </div>
               <div type="epigram">
                  <head>SAULS <hi>converſion.</hi> ch. 9. v. 3.</head>
                  <l>The light thou ſaw'ſt from heav'n did make thee blind;</l>
                  <l>And yet, O Saul, gave light unto thy mind.</l>
               </div>
               <div type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Peters deliverance.</hi> ch. 12. v. 7, 8, &amp;c.</head>
                  <l>Peter, the doors flew ope for thy</l>
                  <l>Egreſſe to former liberty.</l>
                  <pb n="89" facs="tcp:103970:50"/>
                  <l> Thy hearts-doores to fly ope begin,</l>
                  <l>Joy with the angel enters in.</l>
               </div>
               <div type="epigram">
                  <head>Sirs, What ſhall I do to be ſaved? &amp;c. <hi>ch. 16. v. 30.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>What ſhouldſt thou do O Jaylour? why repent,</l>
                  <l>Hear the glad tidings of the Goſpel ſent,</l>
                  <l>Perform thy function, thou a Jaylour art,</l>
                  <l>Impriſon Gods commandments in thy heart.</l>
               </div>
               <div type="epigram">
                  <head>PAUL <hi>beaten,</hi> ch. 16. v. 37.</head>
                  <l>When thou with ſtripes wert beat, thou didſt begin</l>
                  <l>To ſay thou wert a Romane Citizen:</l>
                  <l>But when the day of judgement comes, O Paul,</l>
                  <l>Thou'lt plead thy freedome of another Hall.</l>
               </div>
               <div type="epigram">
                  <head>The viper ſhook into the fire. <hi>ch. 28. v. 5.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>Thou Murd'rous beaſt who by unnat'rall ſtrife,</l>
                  <l>Doſt break a paſſage thorough death to life;</l>
                  <l>And now with fell intent upon the hand</l>
                  <l>Of godly Paul, who ſcorns thy pow'r, doſt ſtand;</l>
                  <l>Think'ſt thou, when he hath ſcapt the raging ſea</l>
                  <l>That he on land ſhall find his death by thee?</l>
                  <l>Or doſt thou but to kiſſe his hand aſpire?</l>
                  <l>He ſcap'd the ſea, trie if thou canſt, the fire.</l>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="book">
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:103970:51"/>
               <head>The Epiſtle of <hi>PAUL</hi> the Apostle to the <hi>ROMANS.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="epigram">
                  <head>Who will render to every man according to his deeds. <hi>ch. 2. v. 6.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>IF labourers are worthy of their hire,</l>
                  <l>I've undeſerv'd thy love, deſerv'd thine ire:</l>
                  <l>My work, O heavenly Father, alwayes hath</l>
                  <l>Been the more amply to deſerve thy Wrath,</l>
                  <l>Not working in thy vineyard, but have ſown</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Tares'</hi> ſted of <hi>tears</hi> to my confuſion;</l>
                  <l>Nor ſhould I reap in joy theſe fruits, but hell</l>
                  <l>Would fall to my lot, and I ſhould have fell</l>
                  <l>To it, yet though poor wretch I contrary</l>
                  <l>Have been to thee ſtill, let my wages be</l>
                  <l>Contrary to my merits and though I</l>
                  <l>Cannot thy mercy by my actions buy,</l>
                  <l>My <hi>labour</hi> being nought <hi>worth,</hi> yet be't thy will</l>
                  <l>That I may <hi>labour</hi> to be <hi>worthy</hi> ſtill.</l>
               </div>
               <div type="epigram">
                  <head>Aliud.</head>
                  <l>The earth with gratefull tribute doth reſtore</l>
                  <l>The ſeed we put into her truſt before,</l>
                  <l>But that is earthly fruit, ſow then with toyl</l>
                  <l>Heaven's ſeeds, for that's a farre more fertill ſoyl;</l>
                  <l>For God takes care that thoſe who <hi>mean</hi> to give</l>
                  <l>Their lives to him, ſhall nere want <hi>means</hi> to live.</l>
               </div>
               <div type="epigram">
                  <pb n="91" facs="tcp:103970:51"/>
                  <head>For I am perſwaded that neither heighth nor depth, &amp;c. <hi>ch. 8. v. 28.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>The Poets fancy that a chain of gold,</l>
                  <l>Which doth, alone, bound to Jove's chair, uphold</l>
                  <l>The earth, the ſea, and all things elſe; but we</l>
                  <l>Have better chains in our Divinity:</l>
                  <l>Whoſe links are nought but amity, and love</l>
                  <l>Which binds us faſt unto our God above:</l>
                  <l>So held by Chriſt that no ſiniſter fate,</l>
                  <l>Nor World nor Devils ſhall us ſeparate.</l>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="book">
               <head>The firſt Epiſtle of <hi>PAUL</hi> the Apoſtle to the <hi>CORINTHIANS.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="epigram">
                  <head>And now abideth Faith, hope and charity: but the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt of theſe is charity. <hi>ch. 13. v. the laſt.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>CHarity is a grace, whence all the reſt,</l>
                  <l>Do take their riſe, and is of all the beſt.</l>
                  <l>This grace God us'd, to give us grace, which he</l>
                  <l>Had never given, but for charity:</l>
                  <l>This proper is to God. each other grace</l>
                  <l>That in mans heart doth find a biding place</l>
                  <l>Doth die with him; but this no end ſhall ſhall have</l>
                  <l>Nor reſt within the compaſſe of a grave:</l>
                  <l>This ſhews Gods image in us; ſeek it then:</l>
                  <l>This makes us earthly Gods; thoſe, onely men.</l>
               </div>
               <div type="epigram">
                  <pb n="92" facs="tcp:103970:52"/>
                  <head>Now if Chriſt be preached that he roſe from the dead, how ſay ſome amongſt you that there is no reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction? but now is Chriſt riſen from the dead, &amp;c. For as in Adam all die, ſo in Chriſt ſhall all be made alive. <hi>ch. 15. ver. 12.20, 22.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>The execration's dreadfull, yet therein</l>
                  <l>There's nought ſo terrible as is the finne.</l>
                  <l>Has Chriſt ſo ill deſerv'd of us that we</l>
                  <l>Should pay him thus again unthankfully!</l>
                  <l>Let love breed love, kindling an equall fire In our deſire.</l>
                  <l>Contemplate on his ſuff'rings, let them move:</l>
                  <l>The greateſt curſe is, not our Lord to love.</l>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="book">
               <head>The ſecond Epiſtle of <hi>PAUL</hi> the Apoſtle to the <hi>CORINTHIANS.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="epigram">
                  <head>Nevertheleſſe though we walk in the fleſh, yet we do not warre after the fleſh. <hi>ch. 10. v. 3.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>WHat though we live on earth, our nobler part</l>
                  <l>Hath learn'd to ſubjugate by heavenly art</l>
                  <l>Our terrene droſſe, our viler heart that ſtill</l>
                  <l>Moves warre, and is repugnant to his will,</l>
                  <l>So diſſonant they are, that midſt their ſtrife</l>
                  <l>They both do mutually endanger life.</l>
                  <l>Yet when that's gone, this ſtill my comfort ſhall</l>
                  <l>Be found, I have a life ſpirituall.</l>
               </div>
               <div type="epigram">
                  <pb n="93" facs="tcp:103970:52"/>
                  <head>And I will very gladly ſpend, and be ſpent for you, &amp;c. <hi>ch. 12. v. 15.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>Spend, and be ſpent, and all that he thereby</l>
                  <l>Might us enrich; this prodigalitie</l>
                  <l>Is too too much! O no, he doth no more</l>
                  <l>Then what our Saviour's ſelf did heretofore;</l>
                  <l>He for mankind lay'd down his life, and ſhall</l>
                  <l>Not we too of our lives be prodigall?</l>
                  <l>What's Paul's unto our Saviour's? and what are</l>
                  <l>Our lives if them we do with Paul's compare?</l>
                  <l>Sure farre below him: grant good God that we</l>
                  <l>May follow him as he hath follow'd thee.</l>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="book">
               <head>The Epiſtle of <hi>PAUL</hi> the Apoſtle to the <hi>GALATIANS.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="epigram">
                  <head>Am I therefore become your enemie becauſe I tell you the truth? <hi>ch. 4. v. 16.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>IF truth breed enmity, he who's truths foe</l>
                  <l>An enemy to th' God of truth is too.</l>
                  <l>Shall paraſitick lies, oyl'd phraſes gain</l>
                  <l>Acceptance, where truth can no grace obtain?</l>
                  <l>It truly ſhews we've none: who then will dare</l>
                  <l>To put's in mind we men, and mortall are?</l>
                  <l>Then flie baſe ſycophants, count him thy ſoe</l>
                  <l>That fawning would not have thee think him ſo.</l>
                  <l>This is the wholeſom'ſt counſel can be given</l>
                  <l>Like this, or th' art not <hi>like</hi> to come to heaven.</l>
               </div>
               <div type="epigram">
                  <pb n="94" facs="tcp:103970:53"/>
                  <head>For I bear in my body the marks of the Lord Jeſus. <hi>ch. 6. v. 17.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>(Paul) in thy body the Lords marks I find,</l>
                  <l>But farre more legible are in thy mind.</l>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="book">
               <head>The Epiſtle of <hi>PAUL</hi> the Apostle to the <hi>EPHESIANS.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="epigram">
                  <head>Redeeming the time, becauſe the dayes are evil. <hi>ch. 6. v. 16.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>If time for no man waits, but poaſteth on;</l>
                  <l>Who can recall the time that's paſt and done.</l>
                  <l>It ſeems perhaps unto our weaker eye</l>
                  <l>To redeem time, impoſſibility.</l>
                  <l>But heaven will teach it by an art divine,</l>
                  <l>Look back upon thy grandſires age, then thine.</l>
                  <l>See their integrity, and quiet life,</l>
                  <l>Thine full of falſhood tending to all ſtrife;</l>
                  <l>Tread in their paths, to imitate them ſtrive;</l>
                  <l>So't may be ſaid that age doth ſtill ſurvive.</l>
               </div>
               <div type="epigram">
                  <head>Stand therefore having your loyns girt about with, &amp;c. <hi>ch. 6. v. 14.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>Arm, arm, againſt an enemy, a foe</l>
                  <l>More to be fear'd, then any here below.</l>
                  <l>Weapons of Steel fram'd by a mortalls hand</l>
                  <l>Cannot the on-ſets of this pow'r withſtand:</l>
                  <pb n="95" facs="tcp:103970:53"/>
                  <l> True holineſſe within our ſimple hearts</l>
                  <l>Muſt be our ſafeguard from hells fiery darts:</l>
                  <l>Strike down all luſts that cannot give the word,</l>
                  <l>That word will wound theſe foes more then thy ſword.</l>
                  <l>When th' haſt or'ecome, lay not thy weapons down,</l>
                  <l>Acknowledge 'twas Gods might, and not thine own,</l>
                  <l>Elſe to thy ſelf, thy ſelf a foe art grown,</l>
                  <l>Thou, none aſſaulting, ſhalt be overthrown.</l>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="book">
               <head>The Epiſtle of <hi>PAUL</hi> the Apoſtle to the <hi>PHILIPPIANS.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="epigram">
                  <head>Let nothing be done through contention or vain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glory, &amp;c. <hi>ch. 2. v. 3.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>TIs fit each one of others better deem;</l>
                  <l>Himſelf in loweſt rank of all eſteem.</l>
                  <l>Nought in vain-glory do, nor oſtentation,</l>
                  <l>Ioyn not humility with affectation.</l>
                  <l>And 'midſt the mad applauſe of th' vulgar rout,</l>
                  <l>With conſciouſneſſe of ſecret faults keep out</l>
                  <l>All pride, thus ſinne within, this good hath done,</l>
                  <l>To give no other intromiſſion.</l>
                  <l>Debarring pride, here fix thy firm abode,</l>
                  <l>The loweſt nigheſt is to th' higheſt God.</l>
               </div>
               <div type="epigram">
                  <pb n="96" facs="tcp:103970:54"/>
                  <head>Let your moderation be known unto all men: the Lord is at hand. <hi>ch. 4, v. 5.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>The coming of our Lord is near, and we</l>
                  <l>Should alwayes for that time prepared be,</l>
                  <l>So let our moderation now be ſhown</l>
                  <l>That he may vindicate us for his own,</l>
                  <l>Onely at that time waiting for ſuch profit,</l>
                  <l>Immoderate be in expectation of it.</l>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="book">
               <head>The Epiſtle of <hi>PAUL</hi> the Apoſtle to the <hi>COLOSSIANS.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="epigram">
                  <head>Set your affections on things above, and not on things below, &amp;c. <hi>ch. 3. v. 2.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>WHo can, then him who gave affects to th' mind</l>
                  <l>A fitter object of affection find?</l>
                  <l>Shall ſordid earth bemire th' immortall ſoul</l>
                  <l>Which elſe woul ſoar aloft above the Pole?</l>
                  <l>Shall dunging land, ſhall carts our buſineſſe be</l>
                  <l>Whilſt we deſpiſe th' ethereall <hi>axeltree?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Shall all thoſe vaſt dimenſions of Heav'ns globe</l>
                  <l>A Ptolomy could take in's Aſtrolabe,</l>
                  <l>Be thought room big enough to entertain</l>
                  <l>My vaſt aſpiring mind? no; all's but vain:</l>
                  <l>With zeal imp'd I'le mount higher, till I ſee</l>
                  <l>The ſtarres as farre below me, as I, thee:</l>
                  <pb n="97" facs="tcp:103970:54"/>
                  <l> I'le fly, at one caſt have at heaven, at all,</l>
                  <l>Take pride in climbing, and yet fear no fall.</l>
               </div>
               <div type="epigram">
                  <head>But he that doth wrong ſhall receive for the wrong that he hath done, and there is no reſpect of perſons. <hi>ch. 3. v. the laſt.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>Thou Monarch of the World, whoſe pow'rfull hand</l>
                  <l>Doth ſway the nations all at thy command;</l>
                  <l>Deal'ſt with all juſtly, letſt it not be ſed</l>
                  <l>Thy laws are like Arachne's fine-ſpun web.</l>
                  <l>Where little flies are caught and kil'd, but great</l>
                  <l>Paſſe at their pleaſures and break down the net.</l>
                  <l>Let not through their injuſtice fools provoke</l>
                  <l>The God of Heav'n, he ſtrikes an equall ſtroke;</l>
                  <l>Strikes at the Crown as well as at the feet,</l>
                  <l>And often makes both head and tail to meet.</l>
               </div>
               <div type="epigram">
                  <head>For what is our hope, or joy, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Yes, ye are our glory and joy. <hi>ch. 2. v. 19.20.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>Twill adde another Diadem to thee</l>
                  <l>Good Paul, when at the laſt day thou ſhalt ſee</l>
                  <l>Thoſe Theſſalonians circled with divine</l>
                  <l>Rayes of bright glory, which, though theirs, are thine:</l>
                  <l>To hear them bleſſe that gracious God who ſent</l>
                  <l>Of their converſion thee the inſtrument.</l>
                  <l>But when Chriſt comes, and claims thee for his own,</l>
                  <l>Their joyes will mount to th' higher region.</l>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="book">
               <pb n="98" facs="tcp:103970:55"/>
               <head>The firſt Epiſtle of <hi>PAUL</hi> the Apoſtle to the <hi>THESSALONIANS.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="epigram">
                  <head>Quench not the Spirit. <hi>ch. 5. v. 19.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>A Sacred heat inſpires me; and ſhall I</l>
                  <l>Fling water on't? or lay the fuell by?</l>
                  <l>No, let it have its work, this burning ſure</l>
                  <l>My ſafety doth from others flames procure.</l>
                  <l>But when I feel the heat decreaſe and gone</l>
                  <l>Almoſt; I'le caſt the Spirits unction on:</l>
                  <l>Or wanting that, poure tears; ſalt water will</l>
                  <l>Re-kindle it, and keep't in vigour ſtill:</l>
                  <l>That like as Chymiſts keep continuall fire</l>
                  <l>T' obtain the rich extraction they deſire;</l>
                  <l>So I may ſtudy ('twould more fruitfull prove)</l>
                  <l>To keep the Spirit the quinteſſence of love.</l>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="book">
               <head>The ſecond Epiſtle of <hi>PAUL</hi> the Apoſtle to the <hi>THESSALONIANS.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="epigram">
                  <head>And ye brethren be not weary in well-doing. <hi>ch. 3. v. 13.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>MAy noble Titus name long live, who thought</l>
                  <l>That day was ſpent in worſe then doing nought</l>
                  <l>Wherein he did no good. ſo kind was he,</l>
                  <l>Of indefatigable charity.</l>
                  <l>In our religion, ſhall an ethnick thus</l>
                  <l>Be ſaid to have preeminence o're us!</l>
                  <pb n="99" facs="tcp:103970:55"/>
                  <l> Though for's vaſt empire none did ere excell</l>
                  <l>That Prince; each ſtrive at leaſt in doing well:</l>
                  <l>To be above him, imitate him who</l>
                  <l>Ne're ceaſeth good to us and ours to do,</l>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="book">
               <head>The Epiſtle of <hi>PAUL</hi> the Apoſtle to <hi>TIMOTHY.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="epigram">
                  <head>And having food and raiment let us be therewith content. <hi>ch. 6. v. 8.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>GLuttons, you are deceiv'd; and ſo are you</l>
                  <l>Fine ſilken Gallants too</l>
                  <l>Which place your <hi>ſummum bonum</hi> in ſuch things</l>
                  <l>As <hi>ſummum malum</hi> brings.</l>
                  <l>High fare and ſumptuous you think, no doubt,</l>
                  <l>To life will ſet you out,</l>
                  <l>To wit for fools; O rather be content</l>
                  <l>With that which God hath ſent;</l>
                  <l>Yet not content; but, ſince God thinks it good,</l>
                  <l>Pray for ſpirituall raiment, heav'nly food.</l>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="book">
               <head>The ſecond Epiſtle of <hi>PAUL</hi> the Apoſtle to <hi>TIMOTHY.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="epigram">
                  <head>Ever learning, and never able to come to the knowledge of the truth. <hi>ch. 3. v. 7.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible: in gutter" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>S this your learning? O 'tis ſurely then</l>
                  <l>Backwards to learn agen.</l>
                  <pb n="100" facs="tcp:103970:56"/>
                  <l> So often to commence, yet never paſt</l>
                  <l>Maſter o'th' art <hi>at laſt.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Backwards you learn the <hi>holy</hi> tongue I know,</l>
                  <l>I fear you <hi>holineſſe</hi> it ſelf learn ſo.</l>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="book">
               <head>The Epiſtle of <hi>PAUL</hi> the Apoſtle to <hi>TITUS.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="epigram">
                  <head>The profeſſe that they know God, but in works they deny him, <hi>ch. 1. v. the laſt.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>PRofeſſing Heaven, he's in a helliſh ſtate</l>
                  <l>That nere is candid, though a candidate:</l>
                  <l>No man at any time Jehovah knew,</l>
                  <l>Much leſſe (if not a man) you beſtiall crue;</l>
                  <l>Though you profeſſe much, yet my faith's but ſmall</l>
                  <l>That you have any faith in you at all.</l>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="book">
               <head>The Epistle to <hi>PHILEMON.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="epigram">
                  <head>Yet for loves ſake I rather beſeech thee, being ſuch a one as Paul the aged, and now alſo a priſoner of Jeſus Chriſt. <hi>verſe 9.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>VVHo would not rather ſuch a pris'ner be,</l>
                  <l>Then of the richeſt potent'ſt city, free?</l>
                  <l>A pris'ner: but 'tis better farre to die,</l>
                  <l>Then ſeek apoſtatizing libertie.</l>
                  <pb n="101" facs="tcp:103970:56"/>
                  <l> O happy Paul who hadſt the honour thus</l>
                  <l>To be his priſoner who redeemed us.</l>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="book">
               <head>The Epistle to the <hi>HEBREWS.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="epigram">
                  <head>It is a fearfull thing to fall into the hands of the living God. <hi>ch. 10. v. 31.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>IN what a ſtupid and a ſottiſh age</l>
                  <l>Do we now live, that we ſhould dread the rage</l>
                  <l>Of puniſhment, which is Gods harbinger,</l>
                  <l>And torments more then the tormentours fear!</l>
                  <l>Surely if that his inſtrument ſtrike ſore,</l>
                  <l>When he's the inſtrument 'twill be farre more:</l>
                  <l>Theſe rods like that Aſſyrian King have pow'r</l>
                  <l>From him who ſent them forth, not to devoure</l>
                  <l>But purge us, would untill 'tis ſet on fire,</l>
                  <l>Can give no heat. O then if you deſire</l>
                  <l>T' avoid the ſcorpions ſting of puniſhment;</l>
                  <l>Appeaſe him firſt who hath theſe ſcourges ſent.</l>
               </div>
               <div type="epigram">
                  <head>By faith, Moſes, when he was come to years, refuſed to be called the ſon of Pharaohs daughter, <hi>ch. 11. v. 24.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>Mild Moſes, was it through humility</l>
                  <l>Thou didſt deny</l>
                  <l>To be th' adopted heir of Pharaoh?</l>
                  <l>Or if not ſo,</l>
                  <l>What mov'd thee to refuſe a dignity</l>
                  <l>That ſu'd to thee?</l>
                  <pb n="102" facs="tcp:103970:57"/>
                  <l> No 'twas thy holy pride which ſhot upright</l>
                  <l>At heav'n, the white;</l>
                  <l>Thou chooſing God thy Father, 'twas not ſtrange</l>
                  <l>So chooſing, thou wert proud of ſuch a change.</l>
               </div>
               <div type="epigram">
                  <head>Chooſing rather to ſuffer affliction with the people of God, then to enjoy the pleaſures of ſinne for a ſeaſon, eſteeming the reproch of Chriſt, <hi>&amp;c. ch. 11. v. 25, 26.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>Cheap pennieworth affliction, when ſuch gain</l>
                  <l>It brings, and quits with ſo much joy our pain.</l>
                  <l>Cheap bought, yet dearly too, ſince 't doth conferre</l>
                  <l>On us what is both precious and dear.</l>
                  <l>Who then can Moſes diſcommend, that he</l>
                  <l>Suffer'd reproches ſo contentedly?</l>
                  <l>In caſe he had deny'd to bear them, then</l>
                  <l>He had deſerv'd reproch from all good men.</l>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="book">
               <head>The Epiſtle of the Apoſtle <hi>S. JAMES.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="epigram">
                  <head>For as the body without the ſpirit is dead, even ſo <hi>&amp;c. ch. 2. v. 26.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>YOu boaſt of faith, you ſay too, you have ſet</l>
                  <l>It ſafe, like jewels in a cabinet.</l>
                  <l>Why ſay you not (and I ſhould credit give,</l>
                  <l>Almoſt as ſoon) a carrion corps doth live</l>
                  <pb n="103" facs="tcp:103970:57"/>
                  <l> That doth not breathe? nor's thy faith joyn'd with works,</l>
                  <l>I'd ſooner take a charitable Turks;</l>
                  <l>And for your cabinet you keep it there</l>
                  <l>So ſafe, that we ſhall never ſee't, I fear.</l>
               </div>
               <div type="epigram">
                  <head>Therefore to him that knoweth how to do well, and doth is not, to him it is ſinne. <hi>ch. 4. v. 17.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>Oft with my ſelf as I have muſing ſate,</l>
                  <l>Weighing the fooliſh and the wiſe man's ſtate;</l>
                  <l>I've doubtfull been, which I might judge the beſt;</l>
                  <l>The wiſe man knows much good, but doeth leaſt.</l>
                  <l>The ſenſeleſſe doltiſh Idiot without wit,</l>
                  <l>Knows nought, and naught is able to commit.</l>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="book">
               <head>The firſt Epiſtle of the Apoſtle <hi>S. PETER.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="epigram">
                  <head>For it is better if the will of God be ſo, that ye ſuffer for well. doing, then for evil. <hi>ch. 3. v. 17.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>AFflictions are like med'cines, if they be</l>
                  <l>Giv'n to ſound bodies go down currently,</l>
                  <l>And trouble not; but if diſtempers grow,</l>
                  <l>And make the ſtomach queazy, 'tis not ſo;</l>
                  <l>They purge, and ſcoure, and ſearch, till nought re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main;</l>
                  <l>That's an ill humour then comes out again:</l>
                  <l>So 'tis with us. If we our ſelves prepare,</l>
                  <l>And with no great offence corrupted are;</l>
                  <pb n="104" facs="tcp:103970:58"/>
                  <l> Afflictions ſeem more ſweet, but if there lie</l>
                  <l>Upon the ſoul ſome foul enormity;</l>
                  <l>The burden weighs more heavy, and our God</l>
                  <l>Seems angry, ſtrikes hard with his iron rod.</l>
                  <l>If I muſt of that bitter purge partake,</l>
                  <l>May't be for triall, not for my ſins ſake.</l>
               </div>
               <div type="epigram">
                  <head>But it is unto them according to the proverb, The dog is returned to his own vomit, and the ſome that was waſhed, to her wallowing in the mire. <hi>ch. 2. v. 22. ep. 2.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>When thou art purg'd, and cleans'd haſt bin,</l>
                  <l>Be carefull leſt again thou ſin:</l>
                  <l>Behold the ſheep that once being waſh't</l>
                  <l>Is wary leſt ſhe ſhould be daſh't;</l>
                  <l>For otherwiſe 'twould labour be in vain</l>
                  <l>To waſh to filth, to filth to waſh again.</l>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="book">
               <head>The firſt Epistle of <hi>JOHN.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="epigram">
                  <head>He that loveth not, knoweth not God, for God is love. <hi>ch. 4. v. 8.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>OUr God is love, then why ſhould we</l>
                  <l>Live thus in wrath and enmity?</l>
                  <l>The bleſſed Trinity teach us love,</l>
                  <l>That we the liker them may prove;</l>
                  <l>To tie <hi>true-love's-knots</hi> now begin,</l>
                  <l>But yet at variance be with ſin.</l>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="book">
               <pb n="105" facs="tcp:103970:58"/>
               <head>The ſecond Epiſtle of <hi>JOHN.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="epigram">
                  <head>For he that biddeth him God ſpeed, is partaker of his evil works. <hi>v. 11.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>TO bid an evil man God ſpeed,</l>
                  <l>'S to be partaker of his deed;</l>
                  <l>But if unwittingly I ſpake,</l>
                  <l>My ſelf I conſcious did not make?</l>
                  <l>But muſt I firſt his buſineſſe know,</l>
                  <l>Whether it lawfull be or no?</l>
                  <l>What need of that? leave him to God,</l>
                  <l>And unto his revengefull rod:</l>
                  <l>Pray then that ſuch who unto ſins are bent,</l>
                  <l>God would with ſpeed bring them to puniſhment.</l>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="book">
               <head>The third epiſtle of <hi>JOHN.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="epigram">
                  <head>But I truſt I ſhall ſhortly ſee thee, and we ſhall ſpeak face to face. <hi>v. 14.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>A Greater bliſſe then peace no man can have,</l>
                  <l>He that gave peace, no doubt all things elſe gave.</l>
                  <l>Peace is the chief of graces, for thoſe were</l>
                  <l>Indeed no graces, which at diſcord are:</l>
                  <l>They, as the Poets fain, are link'd in one,</l>
                  <l>And virtue makes the full conjunction.</l>
                  <pb n="106" facs="tcp:103970:59"/>
                  <l> Behold how this one peace doth proſp'ring bleſſe</l>
                  <l>All temporall affairs with wiſh'd ſucceſſe.</l>
                  <l>The earth yields her increaſe, each under's vine</l>
                  <l>Sits down in peace, and drinks of his own wine.</l>
                  <l>More joy I cannot wiſh you, then farwell,</l>
                  <l>The peace of God be with you where you dwell.</l>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="book">
               <head>The epiſtle generall of <hi>JUDE.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="epigram">
                  <head>Yet Michael the Archangel, when contending with the devil, and diſputing about the body of <hi>MOSES,</hi> durst not blame him with curſed ſpeaking, but ſaid, The Lord rebuke thee. <hi>ver. 9.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>WHat argument of <hi>pro</hi> and <hi>con</hi> there was</l>
                  <l>With them I mean not to <hi>diſpute</hi> the caſe.</l>
                  <l>This onely I am certain of, the one</l>
                  <l>Would bring no railing accuſation:</l>
                  <l>For 'twas as farre below him to contend,</l>
                  <l>In bitter words, as was that ugly feind.</l>
                  <l>A <hi>body</hi> mov'd this ſtrife at firſt 'twixt thoſe</l>
                  <l>Who had <hi>no bodies,</hi> incorporeall foes.</l>
                  <l>Michael, in his <hi>mild</hi> words, without diſpute,</l>
                  <l>His words did to <hi>mild</hi> Moſes nature ſuit.</l>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="book">
               <pb n="107" facs="tcp:103970:59"/>
               <head>The Revelations of <hi>JOHN.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="epigram">
                  <head>The Revelation of Jeſus Christ. <hi>ch. 1. v. 1.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>THis revelation in your minds up hoord,</l>
                  <l>See Chriſt the word revealed in his word.</l>
               </div>
               <div type="epigram">
                  <head>Behold, he cometh with clouds, <hi>&amp;c. ch. 1. v. 7.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>With clouds he comes, a cloudy day 'twill be</l>
                  <l>With thoſe, Lord Jeſus, who deſpiſed thee:</l>
                  <l>But to the Saints happy, thrice happy houre,</l>
                  <l>Thoſe clouds ſhall melt in a ſweet honey ſhowre.</l>
               </div>
               <div type="epigram">
                  <head>I am he that liveth, and was dead. <hi>ch. 1. v. 18.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>No death could have the power over thee,</l>
                  <l>Thou freely did'ſt ſubmit thy ſelf to die;</l>
                  <l>Thou now doſt live; in ſinnes, Lord, I am dead;</l>
                  <l>Joyn me a member to thy ſelf the head.</l>
               </div>
               <div type="epigram">
                  <head>Be thou faithfull unto the death, <hi>&amp;c. ch. 2. v. 10.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>Haſt thou begun well? ſo perſever,</l>
                  <l>Runne on thy race, and alter never.</l>
                  <l>Hell is their portion, who begin</l>
                  <l>In piety, and end in ſinne;</l>
                  <l>And this will be another hell,</l>
                  <l>To think that they began ſo well.</l>
               </div>
               <div type="epigram">
                  <pb n="108" facs="tcp:103970:60"/>
                  <head>And I will give thee a crown of life. <hi>ch. 2. v. 10.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>In the bright throne thou ſhalt be ſet,</l>
                  <l>About thy head a coronet:</l>
                  <l>Thy faithfulneſſe, and conſtancy</l>
                  <l>Shall be reſounded in the skie;</l>
                  <l>And to have got this fame, with ſuch renown,</l>
                  <l>Shall adde a greater luſtre to thy crown.</l>
               </div>
               <div type="epigram">
                  <head>I am Alpha, and Omega. <hi>ch. 22. v. 13.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>God's the worlds <hi>Alpha,</hi> its creatour,</l>
                  <l>He formed all the works of nature:</l>
                  <l>He'll be the worlds <hi>Omega</hi> to</l>
                  <l>Bring to wicked men <hi>great</hi> WO.</l>
                  <l>Here's firſt and laſt; for th' <hi>middle</hi> man, who is't?</l>
                  <l>Who can that be, but <hi>Mediatour</hi> Chriſt?</l>
               </div>
               <div type="epigram">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Aliud.</hi> ch. 22. v. 13.</head>
                  <l>God doth himſelf Alph' and Omega call,</l>
                  <l>Yet no beginning hath, no end at all.</l>
               </div>
               <div type="epigram">
                  <head>Bleſsed are they that do his commandments. <hi>ch. 22. v. 14.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>O ſhut not up the book</l>
                  <l>Ere you a little further look:</l>
                  <l>A ſweet encouragement</l>
                  <l>(Read it) ith' cloſe is ſent.</l>
                  <pb n="109" facs="tcp:103970:60"/>
                  <l> The tree of life is yours</l>
                  <l>Who do endeavour to your pow'rs</l>
                  <l>Gods precepts to fulfill ith' beſt abode,</l>
                  <l>The tree ſhall yield more fruit to you, then you to God.</l>
               </div>
               <div type="epigram">
                  <head>Even ſo, Lord Jeſus, come quickly. <hi>ch. 22. v. 20.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>Make haſte, Lord Jeſus, quickly come,</l>
                  <l>And take my wandring ſpirit home:</l>
                  <l>Too long it hath been pleas'd with toies,</l>
                  <l>And ſought to lying vanities.</l>
                  <l>'Twixt two I am, and fain would be</l>
                  <l>Diſſolved, Lord, and come to thee:</l>
                  <l>O take me, Lord, and eaſe my fears;</l>
                  <l>Or elſe I ſhall diſſolve in tears:</l>
                  <l>Where is the temple? gently guide</l>
                  <l>My ſoul to it, thy virgin bride;</l>
                  <l>Or if no temple fit enough there be,</l>
                  <l>My ſoul's a temple conſecrate to thee.</l>
               </div>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="epigrams">
            <pb n="110" facs="tcp:103970:61"/>
            <head>An additionall corollary of divine Epigrams, ſuch as cannot be referred to any particular place of Scripture.</head>
            <byline>By J. H.</byline>
            <div type="epigram">
               <head>Saint Paul beheaded.</head>
               <l>THe end of thy appointed race is come,</l>
               <l>And thou muſt looſe thy rev'rend head at Rome:</l>
               <l>This crumme of comfort, yet, thy ſpirit fed;</l>
               <l>Thou art the member of another head.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="epigram">
               <head>Mary Magdalens joyes after mourning.</head>
               <l>Mourning, now be gone,</l>
               <l>Go ſeek ſome other place, depart;</l>
               <l>Joy muſt poſſeſſe thy throne,</l>
               <l>Now truly, now, thou mourning art.</l>
               <l>Her eyes have long rain'd April ſhowers,</l>
               <l>'Tis now full time ſhe crop May flowers.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="epigram">
               <head>S. PETER.</head>
               <l>Peter from <hi>petra</hi> comes, a rock, and on</l>
               <l>This rock the Papiſts lay foundation:</l>
               <l>This rock ſo narrow is, that there's no <hi>room,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For thoſe that would be ſav'd, on it to come;</l>
               <l>'T will prove a rock, but ſuch a rock indeed,</l>
               <l>As will their drowning, not ſalvation, breed.</l>
               <pb n="111" facs="tcp:103970:61"/>
               <l> They build upon the ſands, their own hopes mock,</l>
               <l>Since Peters ſelf was built on Chriſt his rock.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="epigram">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHRIST</hi> to me is gain.</head>
               <l>Croſſe others, if you wiſh there ſhould enſue,</l>
               <l>Croſſes, on croſſes, multipli'd on you:</l>
               <l>But if you'll needs be croſſing, 'tis no loſſe,</l>
               <l>But rather gain for you to learn Chriſts Χ.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="epigram">
               <head>PRAYER.</head>
               <l>The Devil, a roaring lion, ſeeks each hour</l>
               <l>Whom he unarm'd may find, and ſo devour.</l>
               <l>Let pray'r our buckler be, all night, all day,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Pray</hi> that thou beeſt not made the devils <hi>prey.</hi>
               </l>
            </div>
            <div type="epigram">
               <head>Heavenly love.</head>
               <l>Great love, no marriage, there's in heav'n above;</l>
               <l>Here is much marrying not a whit of love.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="epigram">
               <head>Soul-comfort.</head>
               <l>Look up to heaven with erected looks</l>
               <l>Of love, my ſoul, thou art much in Gods books.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="epigram">
               <head>On the end of the World.</head>
               <l>The wicked world, in waters, long ago</l>
               <l>Was ſteep'd; th' ill humours then from it did go:</l>
               <l>'Tis now infected with ungodly men,</l>
               <l>Which makes me fear that fire muſt purge't agen.</l>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="112" facs="tcp:103970:62"/>
            <head>A Divine Poem on the cruell death and Puſsion of our Lord and Saviour <hi>JESUS CHRIST.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>ANd now the time is come, dear Lord, is come,</l>
               <l>When not by Pilate's doom, but thy fore-doom</l>
               <l>Thou art to ſuffer; 'twas not his decree,</l>
               <l>But thine, ordain'd from all Eternity.</l>
               <l>Thy ſubject, man, infringed thy Laws juſt force,</l>
               <l>And thou, the Law-giver, ſuſtaind'ſt the curſe:</l>
               <l>When we ſo farre had from thy precepts ſwerv'd,</l>
               <l>That little we deſir'd, this leſſe deſerv'd.</l>
               <l>When we were <hi>did</hi> in ſinne of ſo deep grain,</l>
               <l>Onely thy <hi>dying</hi> could us cleanſe again;</l>
               <l>When we were all be-purpled o're, yet none</l>
               <l>Could bluſh at thoſe offences he had done.</l>
               <l>Strange miracle, that crimſon bloud ſhould ſo</l>
               <l>Turn our ſouls crimſon hue to pureſt ſnow!</l>
               <l>Beyond expreſſion, that he taſtes of death,</l>
               <l>Whoſe breath infus'd in ev'ry creature breath!</l>
               <l>To which ſad joyfull narrative we come,</l>
               <l>Drawn by his agonies preludium.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Our Saviour, having ſup'd his laſt, 'gan ſup</l>
               <l>The wholeſome liquour of the ſaving cup;</l>
               <l>Which did reſemble that his precious bloud</l>
               <l>Was to be ſhed for our eternall good:</l>
               <l>Now a more bitter one to drink he hath,</l>
               <l>The dregs of an incenſed Fathers wrath.</l>
               <l>Being to quaffe this wormwood-draught, alas,</l>
               <l>No mar'l he pray'd the cup from him might paſſe.</l>
               <pb n="113" facs="tcp:103970:62"/>
               <l> Now his firſt conflict comes, now drops of bloud</l>
               <l>Bedew the bluſhing earth, whereon he ſtood:</l>
               <l>Thoſe precious drops, which from him now down glide,</l>
               <l>Uſher the ſtreams muſt iſſue from his ſide.</l>
               <l>The inward torments of his ſoul were great,</l>
               <l>The outward ſignes whereof was bloudy ſweat;</l>
               <l>But greater follow, armed ſoul diers ſtand</l>
               <l>With holdberds, ſtaves, and knotty clubs, in hand;</l>
               <l>Ready to ſeiſe the prince of peace, and he</l>
               <l>Who could have guards of Angels preſently</l>
               <l>Attending on his ſummons, now can brook</l>
               <l>To be by mortall creatures pris'ner took:</l>
               <l>O would they bind him never to depart,</l>
               <l>The ſtrongeſt chain were love, to hold the heart;</l>
               <l>Or, happy they, could they ſo happy prove,</l>
               <l>Themſelves to be tane captives by his love:</l>
               <l>That, that had <hi>bound</hi> them <hi>to the peace,</hi> and ſo</l>
               <l>O'th' militant Church they had been ſouldiers too:</l>
               <l>But Peter not endures it, with zeal ſtir'd,</l>
               <l>Out of his ſheath he draws his keen edg'd ſword:</l>
               <l>Peter, if pleaſure thou in ſwords doſt take,</l>
               <l>The Goſpels two edg'd ſword thy weapon make;</l>
               <l>But he who came to heal his peoples ſinnes,</l>
               <l>To heal the high-prieſts ſervants eare beginnes.</l>
               <l>Who yet, poor creature, Gods call could not hear,</l>
               <l>Becauſe, alas, he wants the inward ear;</l>
               <l>And now the ſhepherd took; the ſheep, poor ſheep</l>
               <l>Are ſcatter'd, when their paſtour doth not keep</l>
               <l>Himſelf: the ſhepherd, ſaid, I? he became</l>
               <l>No more a ſhepherd now, but proves a lambe;</l>
               <pb n="114" facs="tcp:103970:63"/>
               <l> Whoſe fleece his ſervants faults for aye ſhould cover,</l>
               <l>That ſo his fathers wrath might them paſſe over.</l>
               <l>He ſuffers them to leave him, and doth make</l>
               <l>That th' means that he might never them forſake:</l>
               <l>This ſurely was his deepeſt grief, who here</l>
               <l>Deſerted was, of all whom he held dear.</l>
               <l>Accompani'd, but how? with foes, and none</l>
               <l>But would much rather, ſo, be left alone.</l>
               <l>Great are his ſuff'rings ſure, heavy his doom,</l>
               <l>Who ſuffers thus much e're his ſuff'rings come:</l>
               <l>Yet, meek and ſilent, giveth no occaſion</l>
               <l>For any one to think he is in <hi>paſsion:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Although he be, ſo patient bears his ſtate,</l>
               <l>Though full of paſſion, yet not paſſionate.</l>
               <l>Judas, <hi>perditions ſonne,</hi> 'twas led the van</l>
               <l>Of thoſe who came to take the <hi>Sonne of man.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Foul treas'rer who, to gain a little pelf,</l>
               <l>Haſt treaſured up great wrath unto thy ſelf.</l>
               <l>Our Saviour, gently, yet would call him <hi>Friend,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>How much more rightly were he ſtiled Friend!</l>
               <l>What wicked deed, baſe traitour, haſt thou done!</l>
               <l>Haſt thou no other way to <hi>kiſſe the Sonne?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Blind Phariſees Chriſts bounty do not know;</l>
               <l>He'll give himſelf, they need not buy him ſo:</l>
               <l>Think you a price for his life can be given,</l>
               <l>Who gives, that life, a price to purchaſe heaven:</l>
               <l>The traitour doth not long out-live the fact;</l>
               <l>But he who did incite him to this act,</l>
               <l>Invites him to another, to deſtroy</l>
               <l>His body, make that bear's ſoul company.</l>
               <pb n="115" facs="tcp:103970:63"/>
               <l> He hangs himſelf, compleating his ſinnes ſcore,</l>
               <l>Who was inſnar'd with love of hell before.</l>
               <l>Peter, who ſo of late his Saviour lov'd,</l>
               <l>Now runnes: the rock of Peters love is mov'd.</l>
               <l>Firſt led to Annas, next to Caiaphas;</l>
               <l>To Pilate twice, to Herod once he was:</l>
               <l>Both Jews and Gentiles his condemners be;</l>
               <l>Romans, Barbarians ſeem in cruelty.</l>
               <l>Thoſe who were foes before, now think it good</l>
               <l>Firſt to cement their friendſhip in his bloud:</l>
               <l>This reconcilements dire <hi>foundation</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Was built on, yet without the <hi>corner-ſtone:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>What wonder is it then that we have read</l>
               <l>Both bloud, and building fell upon their head?</l>
               <l>Falſe witneſſes were ſought, whoſe conſciences</l>
               <l>Witneſſe to them how falſe their witneſſe is.</l>
               <l>The temple, in three dayes he will deſtroy,</l>
               <l>And at the three dayes end reediſie</l>
               <l>Is of his body, yours too (would you yield</l>
               <l>Temples unto the holy Ghoſt) would build:</l>
               <l>This not enought, theſe Theo-cides begin</l>
               <l>To ſmite him on the cheeks, O horrid ſinne!</l>
               <l>Whilſt they disfigure thus with blows his face,</l>
               <l>Gods image clean from out themſelves they race;</l>
               <l>Whilſt on the face they ſmite him, happy wert</l>
               <l>Their conſciences could ſmite them on the heart.</l>
               <l>Buffets are added too, and they ſhall hear,</l>
               <l>If I may ſay't, on both ſides of their ear:</l>
               <l>Thoſe buffetings, I may with holy Paul</l>
               <l>Satans at leaſt, or Satans ſervants call.</l>
               <pb n="116" facs="tcp:103970:64"/>
               <l> How think ye, he your prayers will hear, who thus</l>
               <l>Have ſtrove to deaf <hi>him</hi> both to you and us?</l>
               <l>Thoſe hands which formed them, they impiouſly</l>
               <l>With blows would bring unto deformity:</l>
               <l>Thoſe hands they ſtrike, to heav'n he upward throws.</l>
               <l>They ſtrike upon a palm that upward grows:</l>
               <l>His eyes too in deriſion they blind,</l>
               <l>They'd have his eyes, it ſeems, like to their mind.</l>
               <l>How could thoſe wretches think to kood-wink him</l>
               <l>Who both lights organ gave and medium?</l>
               <l>They mock him, the eternall God, and he</l>
               <l>Will mock their hopes unto eternitie.</l>
               <l>They brag they'r Iſaac's ſeed, but who can know</l>
               <l>Now whether they are Iſhmaelites, or no?</l>
               <l>Firſt ſcoffing, and then down-right murd'ring, ſure</l>
               <l>They thought it difficult hell to procure;</l>
               <l>Elſe, certainly, they never ſo would wreſt</l>
               <l>It doubly, both by earneſt, and in jeſt:</l>
               <l>But this is nothing yet; diſloyally</l>
               <l>Peter whoerſt forſook, doth now deny</l>
               <l>His Maſter, and doth curſe himſelf; but he</l>
               <l>Whom he denies, denies his curſe ſhall be</l>
               <l>Fulfild on him, but gives him penitence;</l>
               <l>Eyes firſt to ſee, then weep for his offence.</l>
               <l>He had decreed to die before, and hence</l>
               <l>It was he ſpoke not in his own defence:</l>
               <l>Had he, for his juſt cauſe, but pleaded ſo,</l>
               <l>Injuſtice would be forc'd juſtice to do.</l>
               <l>He could have utter'd one ſuch ſentence then,</l>
               <l>Which ſhould have forc'd his judge change his agen</l>
               <pb n="117" facs="tcp:103970:64"/>
               <l> Who yet unwilling was, that one ſo Juſt</l>
               <l>Should die to ſatlsfie the peoples luſt.</l>
               <l>Fain would he have condemned one who was</l>
               <l>An homicide, ſeditious Barabbas.</l>
               <l>An homicide muſt be releas'd that they</l>
               <l>The homicides might with their Saviour play:</l>
               <l>Play, ſaid I? I recant, it was not true;</l>
               <l>Or if they play'd, at leaſt, they play'd the Jew.</l>
               <l>What madneſſe ſeis'd you, that you ſhould releaſe</l>
               <l>The peace's troubler, bind the Prince of peace?</l>
               <l>Much troubled in her dream was Pilates wife;</l>
               <l>And did her beſt to <hi>ſave</hi> our <hi>Saviours</hi> life.</l>
               <l>He hears her not, O wretch, how could it be,</l>
               <l>Unleſſe all goodneſſe were a <hi>dream</hi> to thee?</l>
               <l>Like <hi>dreams</hi> thy joyes ſhall vaniſh, pleaſures too;</l>
               <l>And, but hells pains, thou ſhalt have nothing true.</l>
               <l>Scribes, people, Phariſees, together cry</l>
               <l>Out with him; crucifie him, crucifie</l>
               <l>Their noiſe reſounds, and rends the air again,</l>
               <l>Aſcending high'r then they ſhall ere attain.</l>
               <l>That clamour, which cri'd crucifie him here,</l>
               <l>Thund'ring at heaven, demands for vengeance there:</l>
               <l>The voice aſcended upwards, but alas,</l>
               <l>That they the lower might deſcend it was.</l>
               <l>Why waſheſt thou thy hands? employ that art</l>
               <l>(Yet that were bootleſſe too) to cleanſe thine heart,</l>
               <l>Or in that bloud, from which thou ſain wouldſt free</l>
               <l>Thy ſelf, but waſh, and thou ſhalt cleanſed be:</l>
               <l>But O their cry prevails, who curſing ſtood,</l>
               <l>On them, and on their children be his bloud.</l>
               <pb n="118" facs="tcp:103970:65"/>
               <l> God, who ne're heard their pray'rs in ought but this,</l>
               <l>Fulfill'd the tenour of their direfull wiſh;</l>
               <l>Yet had they laid his bloud to heart, in ſtead</l>
               <l>Of that, God had not laid it on their head.</l>
               <l>Pilate begins himſelf now to beſtirre,</l>
               <l>Not like a judge, but Executioner.</l>
               <l>The ſcourge foreſhows what tortures are to come,</l>
               <l>Of which that is but the <hi>Proaemium.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Deep print theſe laſhes left; but we (unkind)</l>
               <l>Forget to have them printed in our mind:</l>
               <l>We may keep Gods commands, and yet keep theſe,</l>
               <l>No ſinne to have ſuch graven images.</l>
               <l>Stript naked from his clothes; if ever, now</l>
               <l>Truth naked is, we boldly may avow:</l>
               <l>Who of eternall rayes, himſelf before</l>
               <l>Had ſtript; clogg'd with humanity, once more</l>
               <l>Is ſtript of earthly garments, that ſo he</l>
               <l>Might clothe us with his immortalitie:</l>
               <l>But this was not enough; with more diſdain,</l>
               <l>Then ere they ſtrip'd, they clothe him now again:</l>
               <l>Little thoſe miſcreants thought, when thus they plaid,</l>
               <l>That they in ſearlet had their judge araid;</l>
               <l>This colour with his office well agrees,</l>
               <l>That bloudy fact, and our iniquities;</l>
               <l>Thus by anticipation be begins</l>
               <l>To be apparrell'd in his peoples ſinnes.</l>
               <l>A wreath of thorns ingirts his temples, and</l>
               <l>A reed, ſtead of a ſceptre in his hand.</l>
               <l>Thoſe thorns, which crown his brows, may ſeem to ſay,</l>
               <l>Who goes to heaven muſt go a thorny way.</l>
               <pb n="119" facs="tcp:103970:65"/>
               <l> How can the members better think to ſpeed,</l>
               <l>When he their <hi>head</hi> doth wear them on his <hi>head?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Never were thorns ſo rightly ſaid t' incloſe,</l>
               <l>As now they are, a full-blown purple roſe.</l>
               <l>He'll near prove ſteady Chriſtian, who ſticks</l>
               <l>Loth to embrace, kicking againſt theſe pricks.</l>
               <l>His ſceptre weak although it be, they need</l>
               <l>Not fear that he will break the bruiſed reed;</l>
               <l>And now they make obeyſance to him: how</l>
               <l>Their outward not their inward knee they bow!</l>
               <l>Prophetick 'tis, though little they intend</l>
               <l>It ſo, to him of right all knees muſt bend.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Hail, hail,</hi> long reigne the king, methinks I hear</l>
               <l>Their clam'rous mock-ſhouts rend the troubled air:</l>
               <l>As on thoſe goodly cities of the Plain</l>
               <l>He did, ſo wretches he on you will rain</l>
               <l>Snares, ſulphur, fire (your courages ſhall quail)</l>
               <l>And dreadfull ſtones of, what you wiſht him, <hi>hail.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Our Lord was ſpit upon, and we muſt too</l>
               <l>Expect through ſpittle unto heaven to go:</l>
               <l>But O they go about farre worſe then it,</l>
               <l>I fear they have not all their venome ſpit.</l>
               <l>The reed which ſtood before in's ſceptres ſtead,</l>
               <l>Has left his hand, and's flown unto his head:</l>
               <l>Which grieving their ſpites inſtrument to be,</l>
               <l>Hath from that time to this ſigh'd vocally.</l>
               <l>Through ſtrokes howe're the way may ſeem uneven,</l>
               <l>He goes a beaten path, that goes to heaven:</l>
               <l>Jeſting is paſt, and now their play muſt be</l>
               <l>Clos'd in a Tragicall <hi>Cataſtrophe.</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="120" facs="tcp:103970:66"/>
               <l> His own clothes are put on, he in ſhort ſpace</l>
               <l>Is led to's death, Mount Calvarie's the place:</l>
               <l>Simon takes up his croſſe, his others were</l>
               <l>Croſſes ſufficient for himſelf to bear;</l>
               <l>On whoſe back laid, beſides his grief, we find,</l>
               <l>The ſinnes, and puniſhment of all mankind;</l>
               <l>And now I come, where I (methinks) could ſtay,</l>
               <l>Raviſh'd in contemplation, for aye.</l>
               <l>What a ſad-joyfull object greets mine eye?</l>
               <l>Seeing his ſorrows, can I chuſe but cry?</l>
               <l>Both grief and gladneſſe, here at once there lies;</l>
               <l>And ev'n my very tears, are tears of joyes.</l>
               <l>Can I refrain to pour a briny floud,</l>
               <l>Which yet is drown'd in th' Ocean of his bloud?</l>
               <l>Can I refrain to joy? thoſe drops, I ſee,</l>
               <l>Are made the oyl of gladneſſe, Soul, to thee.</l>
               <l>Yet, can I chuſe but grieve, ſince paradice</l>
               <l>Is purchas'd for me at ſo dear a price?</l>
               <l>Yet, can I chuſe but joy in contemplation,</l>
               <l>That theſe his ſorrows work my ſouls ſalvation?</l>
               <l>Then ſhare me joyntly, joy and ſadneſſe: part</l>
               <l>Stakes in my leaping, yet diſſolving, heart;</l>
               <l>Or, ſince the world's a vale of tears, on earth</l>
               <l>I'll weep; in heav'n will make eternall mirth.</l>
               <l>The ſonne of man is lifted up, O ſee</l>
               <l>How heav'n and earth ſtrive for the deity!</l>
               <l>He in <hi>ſuſpenſe,</hi> as dubious, yet is loth</l>
               <l>To leave one for the other, but midſt both;</l>
               <l>Nor midſt his ſufferings, ſuffers to reſigne</l>
               <l>His humane nature, or put off's divine:</l>
               <pb n="121" facs="tcp:103970:66"/>
               <l> Yet though he doubly hath obſcur'd his light</l>
               <l>By humane nature, and with pains; too bright</l>
               <l>He is for my aſpect, my eyes grow dim;</l>
               <l>Thus long with gazing upon glorious him;</l>
               <l>He now drinks up the dregs of's cup, which are</l>
               <l>A mixt compound of gall and vineger.</l>
               <l>So he a dove in life, at his death ſhall</l>
               <l>Take in, what's not innate unto him, gall.</l>
               <l>The God of love drinks vineger; O pow'r</l>
               <l>Of love, which overcame with ſweet that ſoure!</l>
               <l>He takes that wormwood potion down that we</l>
               <l>Might <hi>in the gall of bitterneſſe</hi> ne're be.</l>
               <l>His hands are nail'd but not a-croſſe, he ſtands</l>
               <l>As ready to embrace with open hands,</l>
               <l>They've hit the proverb right. Sharp nails are ſped</l>
               <l>Through both the hands of him who is our head.</l>
               <l>O let theſe wounds ſuffice he doth ſuſtain,</l>
               <l>Let us not crucifie him o're again.</l>
               <l>Between two thieves he hangs, who held to be</l>
               <l>Equall with God no part of robberie:</l>
               <l>So I'twixt grace and ſin, but fain from ſin</l>
               <l>Would be diſſolv'd; O ſo a tract begin,</l>
               <l>My cauterix'd, my iron heart! one thief</l>
               <l>Upbraids: O th' impudence beyond belief!</l>
               <l>And were't not Goſpel, I ſhould take't to be</l>
               <l>As farre remote from all belief, as he</l>
               <l>Impenitently ſinfull, ſinfull more</l>
               <l>In this, then ere he ſhew'd himſelf before.</l>
               <l>(If thou beeſt Chriſt) he did his worſt I ſee</l>
               <l>To robbe our Lord of his Divinitie.</l>
               <pb n="122" facs="tcp:103970:67"/>
               <l> The other meekly chides him, and <hi>begins</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Now at his <hi>end</hi> t' ask pardon for his ſinnes.</l>
               <l>Good pious thief, who thus paſt hope haſt ſtole</l>
               <l>To heaven, and cheat'ſt the Devil of a ſoul.</l>
               <l>A title's o're our Saviour writ, and all</l>
               <l>In letters, like their own crime, <hi>capitall.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Now <hi>capitall</hi> it needs muſt be, becauſe</l>
               <l>Both o're his head, and 'againſt our Head it was:</l>
               <l>Hebrew, Greek, Roman, which may ſignifie</l>
               <l>He for all languages alike did die.</l>
               <l>This is the <hi>title</hi> of our King; by this</l>
               <l>He gives us <hi>title</hi> to a throne of bliſſe.</l>
               <l>This is the title of our King; nor need it</l>
               <l>Explained be, for he that runs may reade it.</l>
               <l>Our Saviours ſorrows are at heighth; each ſcribe,</l>
               <l>As he by-paſſes, ſpends ſome quip, ſome gibe.</l>
               <l>If thou be Chriſt (ſo ſaid the thief)'s to me</l>
               <l>Doubtfull, if he the Chriſt your Chriſt will be.</l>
               <l>(If thou beeſt Chriſt, come down) what would you do?</l>
               <l>Should he deſcend, you needs muſt lower go.</l>
               <l>(That we this miracle beholding may</l>
               <l>Give credence that thou art whom thou doſt ſay)</l>
               <l>(Come down, and ſave thy ſelf) what would you have?</l>
               <l>Should he himſelf, alas who ſhould you ſave?</l>
               <l>So difficult you are faith to receive,</l>
               <l>Twill be a miracle if you believe.</l>
               <l>Midſt pangs beyond our reaſons dull belief,</l>
               <l>Eternall torments and internall grief,</l>
               <l>Our Saviour cries in this extremitie</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Eli, Eli, lamaſabachthani.</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="123" facs="tcp:103970:67"/>
               <l> Heav'n now, heav'n gates are ſhut, they now begin</l>
               <l>T' refuſe to let the King of glory in.</l>
               <l>Thoſe doors againſt their maker cloſed be,</l>
               <l>By him for us op'd to eternity.</l>
               <l>His Fathers ear is ſtopt, juſtice doth move</l>
               <l>So much his fury that it clouds his love.</l>
               <l>Hell gapes, and the infernall monarch glories</l>
               <l>Hoping t' engulf him in his territories.</l>
               <l>Vaniſht Hoſannaes are: all ſignes of gladneſſe:</l>
               <l>Through th' <hi>univerſe</hi> an <hi>univerſall</hi> ſadneſſe.</l>
               <l>But the miſtaking Jews believe amiſſe,</l>
               <l>Elias to his help invoked is.</l>
               <l>Elias was not of that mournfull ſong</l>
               <l>The burden: but 'twas EL God farre more ſtrong</l>
               <l>Yet as that Sire in flaming chariots hurri'd,</l>
               <l>To th' Apotheioſis was rapt and carri'd.</l>
               <l>So he's to come, involv'd with flames of fire,</l>
               <l>And turn the world to cinders in his ire.</l>
               <l>Then happy thoſe, whom guilt doth not appall;</l>
               <l>Who theirs, can Iſraels carre, and horſemen, call.</l>
               <l>There now remains one thing for him to do,</l>
               <l>Then are his acts, and paſſions ended too.</l>
               <l>He thirſts: who thirſty unto him are brought</l>
               <l>He gives lifes waters for an heavenly draught.</l>
               <l>That ſponge of vineger, which they thought good</l>
               <l>Enough for him, he'l fill it with his blood.</l>
               <l>And as a ſigne their ſafety he doth mean</l>
               <l>Purge them with Hyſſop that they may be clean.</l>
               <l>And now 'tis finiſh'd. O that I and all</l>
               <l>Could in the houre of expiration call</l>
               <pb n="124" facs="tcp:103970:68"/>
               <l> On God, as he. My ſpirit I commit</l>
               <l>My God to thee, thou gav'ſt, receive thou it.</l>
               <l>Father, forgive their ſinnes, they do not know</l>
               <l>(Father, forgive their treſpaſſe,) what they do.</l>
               <l>O ſee his goodneſſe! in his greateſt pain</l>
               <l>He did not leave to intercede for man:</l>
               <l>Even in his change, when juſt he was to part,</l>
               <l>His ſp'rit flew forth in pray'rs to change their heart;</l>
               <l>And with theſe words reſigning quietly</l>
               <l>His ſoul, he who can never die, doth die.</l>
               <l>The ſunne amaz'd reins in his ſteeds, and ſhrouds</l>
               <l>His muffled face in black condenſed clouds;</l>
               <l>Thinking it more prepoſterous to ſee</l>
               <l>The ſunne of righteouſneſſe eclips'd, then he.</l>
               <l>A three houres darkneſſe ſtraight invelops all</l>
               <l>The land: the night is a night typicall,</l>
               <l>For each houre count a day, our Saviour hath</l>
               <l>Juſt ſo long walked in the vale of death.</l>
               <l>Nature's turn'd topſy-turvy from her ſtation,</l>
               <l>Earth's fabrick mov'd with fear moves her founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</l>
               <l>The rocks now that grand Rock of help is ſhook</l>
               <l>Tear their hard entrails up as thunder-ſtrook;</l>
               <l>Moſaick rites of right with him now ending,</l>
               <l>'Gin vail to him, the veil o'th temple rending,</l>
               <l>The heavens above flaſh lightnings out of meaſure;</l>
               <l>The earth reveals her own, and Gods beſt treaſure;</l>
               <l>The ſaints ariſe, and ſhew themſelves abroad,</l>
               <l>And in that ſhewing ſhew the power of God.</l>
               <l>Yet as the holy city now ſees them,</l>
               <l>They may ſee thoſe i'th' new Jeruſalem;</l>
               <pb n="125" facs="tcp:103970:68"/>
               <l> This the Centurion ſees, and, on the quaking</l>
               <l>O'th' earth, hath fixt his faith beyond all ſhaking.</l>
               <l>The Jews high-feaſt is nigh at hand, and they</l>
               <l>For greater celebration of the day,</l>
               <l>Ask't that the crucifi'd might forth with be</l>
               <l>Diſpatcht outright, and taken from the tree;</l>
               <l>Who, t' execute this hard command were ſent,</l>
               <l>Straight brake the two thieves legs. ſans comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</l>
               <l>Do break them. without help of legs, the one</l>
               <l>Will make a ſhift to paradiſe to run.</l>
               <l>But when they to our Saviour came, whoſe breath</l>
               <l>Was gone, they, ſatisfied with his death,</l>
               <l>Broke not a bone: the Scriptures ſo had ſpoke.</l>
               <l>Had they broke them, they Gods decrees had broke,</l>
               <l>Thoſe were the marble columnes his ſpouſe praiſed,</l>
               <l>On whom the baſis of the Church were raiſed.</l>
               <l>But one more boldly curious then the reſt,</l>
               <l>Reſolv'd to put the truth unto the teſt,</l>
               <l>And thruſt his ſpear into his ſide, a ſpout</l>
               <l>Of bloud and water ſeverally guſh'd out;</l>
               <l>Both ſtreams were for mankinds eternall good,</l>
               <l>Onely deny'd to him that made the flood.</l>
               <l>Why caſt they lots for's coat, ſince none would be</l>
               <l>'Mongſt them content to wear his livery?</l>
               <l>Oh think they, clad in that ſame woollen coat,</l>
               <l>Each ſhall a ſheep be thought, and not a goat?</l>
               <l>Alas! they can't act Saints parts; without doubt</l>
               <l>Th' all-knowing God will find diſſemblers out.</l>
               <l>Our Lord's yet on the Croſſe, but in the even</l>
               <l>Joſeph takes heart of grace, prayes to be given</l>
               <pb n="126" facs="tcp:103970:69"/>
               <l> To him Chriſts body. Pilate hears him: gives</l>
               <l>What Judas ſold, by him whoſe guilt he lives.</l>
               <l>His body is embalm'd. O could there be</l>
               <l>A ſent more aromatick then was he!</l>
               <l>Could ought more ſovereign then himſelf be had?</l>
               <l>Heav'ns ſovereign, precious balm of Gilead.</l>
               <l>Wrapt up in fine white ſindon, which (how e're)</l>
               <l>Cannot his whiter innocence come near.</l>
               <l>Clothe me with that pure raiment that I may</l>
               <l>Appearing (at the laſt and generall day)</l>
               <l>Not daunted; at that great mutation</l>
               <l>Be found to have my wedding garments on.</l>
               <l>His tomb's prepared of no rare Architect,</l>
               <l>With Imagery of Perſian marble deckt.</l>
               <l>What other ornament could that grave need,</l>
               <l>Wherein our Lord did deign to lay his head.</l>
               <l>From any former duſts pollution free;</l>
               <l>Gods holy one muſt no corruption ſee.</l>
               <l>But ſoft. I am too raſh that thus dare venture</l>
               <l>Boldly into this hallow'd place to enter.</l>
               <l>Yet oh! e're back I ſtep, 'tis all I crave</l>
               <l>To leave my ſins behind me in his grave.</l>
               <l>Alas the day-ſtar's clouded from my ſight;</l>
               <l>Alas the day! rather, alas the night!</l>
               <l>The Sun of righteouſneſſe is ſet, and I</l>
               <l>Groping to find the way ith' dark muſt cry</l>
               <l>At once my Saviour Lord, why leav'ſt thou me?</l>
               <l>The Sunne of righteouſneſſe is ſet: to riſe</l>
               <l>After repoſe more ſplendent in our eyes.</l>
               <l>The Sun of glory's ſet, what ſhould we do</l>
               <l>But turn our glory into ſadneſſe too?</l>
               <pb n="127" facs="tcp:103970:69"/>
               <l> Set in a ſea of bloud: who's he forbears</l>
               <l>At leaſt to bathe him in a ſea of of tears?</l>
               <l>The Sun of glory's ſet and I have done;</l>
               <l>Setting a period here with him my Sun.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="hymn">
            <head>An Hymn on the Reſurrection of our Lord and Saviour <hi>JESUS CHRIST.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg n="1">
               <head>1</head>
               <l>HE's roſe, not death the power could have</l>
               <l>To keep him longer in the grave,</l>
               <l>His duſty ſpoils among.</l>
               <l>He's roſe who ſet before to riſe</l>
               <l>With greater ſplendour in our eyes;</l>
               <l>And with him riſe my ſong.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="2">
               <head>2</head>
               <l>This tomb in which inclos'd did lie</l>
               <l>Mortall immortalitie,</l>
               <l>Left widdow'd ſince he went</l>
               <l>Though him it could not keep, ſhall be</l>
               <l>Conſerv'd it ſelf in memory;</l>
               <l>Be its own monument.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="3">
               <head>3</head>
               <l>How dire a journey did he take</l>
               <l>Of three dayes travell for our ſake,</l>
               <l>Riding his progreſſe on!</l>
               <l>Conquering even death it ſelf, and making</l>
               <l>The damned fiends, agaſt, ſtand quaking</l>
               <l>In their own region.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="4">
               <pb n="128" facs="tcp:103970:70"/>
               <head>4</head>
               <l>Who could a fitter Nuncius chooſe</l>
               <l>Then ſome bright cherub for this news?</l>
               <l>Tidings ſo ſweet they are</l>
               <l>As might create a ſtrife to tell</l>
               <l>Which doth the other moſt excell,</l>
               <l>The news, or meſſenger.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="5">
               <head>5</head>
               <l>Let ſuperſtitious Perſians follow,</l>
               <l>With bent knees their ador'd Apollo,</l>
               <l>From his Sabeans neſt;</l>
               <l>But my devotions courſe ſhall run,</l>
               <l>An heliotropium, to that Sun</l>
               <l>Ariſing in the Eaſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="6">
               <head>6</head>
               <l>Nor let Aſtrologers divine,</l>
               <l>Becauſe two ſunnes together ſhine,</l>
               <l>Death will enſue; but rather</l>
               <l>Life, which benignely flows from hence,</l>
               <l>Shewn by combined influence</l>
               <l>Of Spirit, Son, and Fathèr.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="hymn">
            <head>An Hymn on the glorious Aſcenſion of our Lord and Saviour Ieſus Chriſt.</head>
            <lg n="1">
               <head>1</head>
               <l>MAke clear thy opticks, Soul, and view,</l>
               <l>If wonder gives thee leave to ſee</l>
               <pb n="129" facs="tcp:103970:70"/>
               <l> Heav'n comes to claime from earth it's due</l>
               <l>Who not content is forc'd t'agree:</l>
               <l>The principall ſhee holdes it beſt</l>
               <l>To pay; yet keeps the intereſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="2">
               <head>2</head>
               <l>But loth her Lord ſo ſoon ſhould hence</l>
               <l>From ſome low vaile ſhee would not let</l>
               <l>Him part; but lingring brought her prince</l>
               <l>To th' top of high mount Olivet:</l>
               <l>From whence an envious cloud in ſpight</l>
               <l>Doth raviſh him from humane ſight.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="3">
               <head>3</head>
               <l>What joyes Heavn's Hierarchy among?</l>
               <l>What peales of Hallelujah's ring?</l>
               <l>The glorified quire 'ginne throng</l>
               <l>Together to ſalute their King.</l>
               <l>There gladneſſe is, on earth, greifes ſwell;</l>
               <l>Wrath, envy, black deſpaire, in Hell.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="4">
               <head>4</head>
               <l>Now thou art rais'd; why lingers heere</l>
               <l>Thy ſervant in this vale of wo?</l>
               <l>Let him be fixed in a ſpheare</l>
               <l>With thee, not wander heere below</l>
               <pb n="130" facs="tcp:103970:71"/>
               <l> Let him a ſtarre; no planet prove,</l>
               <l>A ſigne in heaven of thy love</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="5">
               <head>5</head>
               <l>My loadſtone's ſet aloft, attract</l>
               <l>With thy magnetick force my ſoule;</l>
               <l>That touched with faiths lively act</l>
               <l>May turne to thee as to the Pole:</l>
               <l>Theſe are my Oraiſons which god fulfill,</l>
               <l>And Chriſt's aſcenſion bids me hope he will.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="hymn">
            <pb n="131" facs="tcp:103970:71"/>
            <head>A Hymn on the day of Pentecoſt.</head>
            <lg n="1">
               <head>1</head>
               <l>HAile, o day, ſo highly famed</l>
               <l>Brighter be thou ſtill returning;</l>
               <l>For thy candour aye be named</l>
               <l>A white, a bleſt, a glorious morning.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="2">
               <head>2</head>
               <l>In whoſe juſt praiſe my muſe now writing</l>
               <l>Feares this honour'd feaſt ſhe wronges,</l>
               <l>Wanting, whilſt ſhe is reciting,</l>
               <l>What thoſe Saintes had, the guift of tongues.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="3">
               <head>3</head>
               <l>Tongues as diverſe, and as many,</l>
               <l>As upon th' Apoſtles fell;</l>
               <l>Yet amongſt them all not any,</l>
               <l>But kindled by the fire of zeale.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="4">
               <head>4</head>
               <l>Thoſe their tongues were clove aſunder,</l>
               <l>Their praiſes I intend to joyne</l>
               <pb n="132" facs="tcp:103970:72"/>
               <l> Till all as much are fill'd with wonder</l>
               <l>As they ſuppoſed to be with wine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="5">
               <head>5.</head>
               <l>But ſoft, raſh muſe, no further venture,</l>
               <l>That heat ſure doth not thee inſpire:</l>
               <l>Keep aloof, and dare not enter</l>
               <l>Leſt thou deſerve another fire.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
